<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" id="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R26-003" codify:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code">
  <num>SI-R26-003</num>
  <heading>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO COUNCIL RESOLUTION NO. SI-R26-003</heading>
  <heading type="law">Santa Fe Indian School Board of Trustees Contract for Water Rights Funding</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2026-05-12</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res">Council Resolution No. SI-R26-003</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2026-05-06</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <preamble>At a duly called meeting of the Council of San Ildefonso Pueblo on the 6<sup>th</sup> day of May, 2026, the following resolution was adopted:</preamble>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Santa Fe Indian School, Inc. ("SFIS") is a non-profit corporation created under the New Mexico Non-profit Corporation Act and is recognized as a charitable organization under §501(c)(3) of the United States Internal Revenue Code; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on December 27, 2000, the land on which the Santa Fe Indian School is located was transferred into trust pursuant to the Santa Fe Indian School Act, Public Law 106-568, §§821-824, 114 Stat. 2868, 2919, and is held in trust by the United States of America for the benefit of the nineteen Pueblos located in New Mexico (the "Santa Fe Indian School Trust Lands"); and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Members of the SFIS are the nineteen Indian Pueblos located in New Mexico; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Member Pueblos, through the SFIS Bylaws, delegated authority to the SFIS Board of Trustees, to act on behalf of the Member Pueblos, on all matters related to the SFIS; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on July 29, 2022, the SFIS was notified of FY2022 water rights funding in the amount of $40,000 from the Bureau of Indian Affairs for Water Resource Management Planning &amp; Predevelopment for the SFIS under provisions of the Indian Self Determination Act, P.L. 93-638 entering into contract A23AV00476; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on June 24, 2022, the Southwest Regional Office of the BIA requested the SFIS to submit a funding request for FY2023 funds for Water Resource Management Planning &amp; Predevelopment; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the SFIS was not awarded FY2023 funds for Water Resource Management Planning &amp; Predevelopment; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on July 25, 2023, the Southwest Regional Office of the BIA requested the SFIS to submit a funding request for FY2024 funds for Water Resource Management Planning &amp; Predevelopment; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on July 18, 2024, the SFIS was notified of FY2024 water rights funding awarded in the amount of $60,000.00 from the Bureau of Indian Affairs for Water Resource Management Planning &amp; Predevelopment for the SFIS under provisions of the Indian Self-Determination Act, P.L. 93-638, consequently Modification 0001 to include new award to existing contract A23AV00476 was entered into on April 28, 2025; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on May 8, 2024, the Southwest Regional Office of the BIA requested the SFIS to submit a funding request for FY2025 funds for Water Resource Management Planning &amp; Predevelopment; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on November 17, 2025, the Southwest Regional Office of the BIA notified the SFIS Superintendent Abeyta that the SFIS submittal for FY2025 Water Management, Planning &amp; Predevelopment (WMPPD) funding was awarded and additional $60,000 requesting the SFIS to submit a Scope of Work and Budget to modify existing contract A23AV00476: and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on January 27, 2026 via email correspondence the Southwest Regional Office of the BIA notified the SFIS Superintendent that the new award will be added to existing contract A23AV00476 Water Management, Planning &amp; Predevelopment (WMPPD) and requested a new "Tribal Resolution" to draw down the water rights funding; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Member Pueblos of the SFIS, through previous delegation of authority have authorized the SFIS to enter into a contract A23AV00476 Water Management, Planning &amp; Predevelopment (WMPPD) with the Bureau of Indian Affairs under provisions of the Indian Self-Determination Act, P.L. 93-638; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>that the SFIS recognizes that two Member Pueblos, the Pueblo of Santa Clara and the Pueblo de San Ildefonso through respective resolutions SCP No. 2010-16 and SI-R10-041 have retained all authority for matters related to governance which require consultation and to Permit Future Activities.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Council hereby enacts the attached resolution and laws entitled the "SANTA FE INDIAN SCHOOL BOARD OF TRUSTEES CONTRACT FOR WATER RIGHTS FUNDING"; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Member Pueblos of the SFIS through previous delegation of authority and following direct consultation with the Pueblo of Santa Clara and Pueblo de San Ildefonso, have authorized the SFIS Board of Trustees and Superintendent to execute modifications to contract A23AV00476 to accept the FY2025 BIA water rights funding award; Provided, that any future funding awards or subsequent modifications to this contract shall require further consultation and explicit approval from the Pueblo of Santa Clara and the Pueblo of San Ildefonso; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the SFIS shall make certain that all funds received through the federal contract shall be appropriated per contract guidelines, and that the SFIS shall submit all reports as required by contract.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>
        <u>CERTIFICATION</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on <u>May 6</u>, 2026, at a meeting with a vote of <u>8</u> in favor, <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining and <u>2</u> absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Denise Moquino, Council Secretary</text>
    <text>
      <strong>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE SPONSOR(S): </strong>
      <strong>
        <u>Council Representatives</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Tom Garcia</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Brandi Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Perry Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raelene Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raymond J. Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Denise Moquino</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Gary Alan Roybal</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Kenneth Weahkee</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION TO THE GOVERNOR:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>Resolution No. <u>SI-R26-003</u> was presented to the Governor of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso on the</text>
    <text><u>6</u><sup><u>th</u></sup> day of <u>May</u>, 2026, pursuant to the governing Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Agreement"), GOVERNOR, Sec. 4(c), and will become effective after signature by the Governor or veto override by the Council.</text>
    <text>Denise Moquino, Council Secretary</text>
    <subheading>GOVERNOR'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>{ X } APPROVED</text>
    <text>{   } VETO - RETURNED TO COUNCIL WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this <u>12</u> day of <u>May</u>, 2026.</text>
    <text>Christopher A. Moquino, Governor</text>
    <text>Presented by the Governor to the Council on the _______ day of ________________, 2026.</text>
    <subheading>COUNCIL'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>Override of Governor's veto:</text>
    <text>{   } YES</text>
    <text>{   } NO</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Tom Garcia</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Brandi Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Perry Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raelene Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raymond J. Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Denise Moquino</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Gary Alan Roybal</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Kenneth Weahkee</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>
        <u>CERTIFICATION</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on _________________, 2026, at a meeting with a vote of ______ in favor, _____ opposed, _____ abstaining and _____ absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Denise Moquino, Council Secretary</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <codify:insert path="|11.2" codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|11.2.28">
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>11.2.28</num>
      <heading>Santa Fe Indian School Board of Trustees Contract for Water Rights Funding</heading>
    </container>
  </codify:insert>
  <attachment id="law">
    <codified:at path="11.2.28"/>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO</strong>
    </text>
    <heading type="law">SANTA FE INDIAN SCHOOL BOARD OF TRUSTEES CONTRACT FOR WATER RIGHTS FUNDING</heading>
    <section>
      <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|11.2.28.010"/>
      <num codify:value="11.2.28.010">1.1</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text>This enactment shall be known as the "SANTA FE INDIAN SCHOOL BOARD OF TRUSTEES CONTRACT FOR WATER RIGHTS FUNDING" ("Act").</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|11.2.28.020"/>
      <num codify:value="11.2.28.020">1.2</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of this Act is to authorize the Santa Fe Indian School, Inc. ("SFIS") to apply for and accept water rights funding from the federal government.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|11.2.28.030"/>
      <num codify:value="11.2.28.030">1.3</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Santa Fe Indian School, Inc. ("SFIS") is a non-profit corporation created under the New Mexico Non-profit Corporation Act and is recognized as a charitable organization under §501(c)(3) of the United States Internal Revenue Code; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>On December 27, 2000, the land on which the Santa Fe Indian School is located was transferred into trust pursuant to the Santa Fe Indian School Act, Public Law 106-568, §§821-824, 114 Stat. 2868, 2919, and is held in trust by the United States of America for the benefit of the nineteen Pueblos located in New Mexico (the "Santa Fe Indian School Trust Lands"); and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Members of the SFIS are the nineteen Indian Pueblos located in New Mexico; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The Member Pueblos, through the SFIS Bylaws, delegated authority to the SFIS Board of Trustees to act on behalf of the Member Pueblos, on all matters related to the SFIS; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>On July 29, 2022, the SFIS was notified of FY2022 water rights funding in the amount of $40,000 from the Bureau of Indian Affairs for Water Resource Management Planning &amp; Predevelopment for the SFIS under provisions of the Indian Self Determination Act, P.L. 93-638, entering into contract A23AV00476; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>On June 24, 2022, the Southwest Regional Office of the BIA requested the SFIS to submit a funding request for FY2023 funds for Water Resource Management Planning &amp; Predevelopment; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>The SFIS was not awarded FY2023 funds for Water Resource Management Planning &amp; Predevelopment; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>On July 25, 2023, the Southwest Regional Office of the BIA requested the SFIS to submit a funding request for FY2024 funds for Water Resource Management Planning &amp; Predevelopment; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>On July 18, 2024, the SFIS was notified of FY2024 water rights funding awarded in the amount of $60,000.00 from the Bureau of Indian Affairs for Water Resource Management Planning &amp; Predevelopment for the SFIS under provisions of the Indian Self-Determination Act, P.L. 93-638, consequently Modification 0001 to include new award to existing contract A23AV00476 was entered into on April 28, 2025; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>On May 8, 2024, the Southwest Regional Office of the BIA requested the SFIS to submit a funding request for FY2025 funds for Water Resource Management Planning &amp; Predevelopment; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>On November 17, 2025, the Southwest Regional Office of the BIA notified the SFIS Superintendent Abeyta that the SFIS submittal for FY2025 Water Management, Planning &amp; Predevelopment (WMPPD) funding was awarded and an additional $60,000 requesting the SFIS to submit a Scope of Work and Budget to modify existing contract A23AV00476: and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(l)</num>
        <text>On January 27, 2026 via email correspondence, the Southwest Regional Office of the BIA notified the SFIS Superintendent that the new award will be added to the existing contract A23AV00476 Water Management, Planning &amp; Predevelopment (WMPPD) and requested a new "Tribal Resolution" to draw down the water rights funding; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(m)</num>
        <text>That the Member Pueblos of the SFIS, through previous delegation of authority, have authorized the SFIS to enter into a contract A23AV00476 Water Management, Planning &amp; Predevelopment (WMPPD) with the Bureau of Indian Affairs under provisions of the Indian Self-Determination Act, P.L. 93-638; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(n)</num>
        <text>That the SFIS recognizes that two Member Pueblos, the Pueblo of Santa Clara and the Pueblo de San Ildefonso, through respective resolutions SCP No. 2010-16 and SI-R10-041, have retained all authority for matters related to governance which require consultation and to Permit Future Activities.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|11.2.28.040"/>
      <num codify:value="11.2.28.040">1.4</num>
      <heading>Authorization</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso hereby authorizes the SFIS to apply for and receive water rights funds from the federal government in accordance with the terms of this Act, and further recognizes that the Member Pueblos of the SFIS through previous delegation of authority and following direct consultation with the Pueblo of Santa Clara and Pueblo de San Ildefonso, have authorized the SFIS Board of Trustees and Superintendent to execute modifications to contract A23AV00476 to accept the FY2025 BIA water rights funding award; Provided, that any future funding awards or subsequent modifications to this contract shall require further consultation and explicit approval from the Pueblo of Santa Clara and the Pueblo of San Ildefonso.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The SFIS shall make certain that all funds received through the federal contract shall be appropriated per contract guidelines, and that the SFIS shall submit all reports as required by contract.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </attachment>
</document>
