<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" id="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R26-005" codify:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code">
  <num>SI-R26-005</num>
  <heading>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO COUNCIL RESOLUTION NO. SI-R26-005</heading>
  <heading type="law">Chaco Canyon and the Chaco Environment Protection and Coordinated Strategy for the Defense of Public Land Order 7923</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2026-06-12</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res">Council Resolution No. SI-R26-005</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2026-06-10</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <preamble>At a duly called meeting of the Council of San Ildefonso Pueblo on the 10<sup>th</sup> day of June, 2026, the following law was adopted:</preamble>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo de San Ildefonso maintains a strong and continuous cultural connection to Chaco Canyon and the Greater Chaco Landscape, being an enduring and vital part of our history and heritage, a place of deep extraordinary cultural, spiritual and historic importance to our Pueblo, spoken about in our songs, oral narratives, and ceremonies; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on June 7, 2023, PLO No. 7923 withdrew approximately 336,404.42 acres of public land surrounding Chaco Canyon National Historic Park (CNHP) from location and entry under the United States mining laws, and from leasing under the mineral leasing laws for 20 years. The area generally encompasses a 10-mile-perimeter around CCNHP. Public Land Order 7923, carefully balance the federal government's domestic energy production priorities with honoring and protecting this irreplaceable landscape and its Tribal cultural properties; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Bureau of Land Management under President Trump's Executive Order 14154 unleashing American Energy, intends to revoke the withdrawal of Chaco Canyon and surrounding areas; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on October 30, 2025, the BLM Farmington Field Office notified Pueblos of a federal undertaking to consider revocation or modification of Public Land Order 7923 -- the 10-mile withdrawal protecting federal lands and minerals surrounding Chaco Culture National Historical Park; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>this action threatens to upend years of coordination among Tribal Nations, federal agencies, and congressional partners who have worked to safeguard the Greater Chaco landscape. The Public Land Order 7923 withdrawal remains one of the few meaningful protections for an area of profound cultural, spiritual, and historical significance to the Pueblo peoples of New Mexico; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Navajo Nation sued the United States, Navajo Nation v. United States, No. 1:25-cv-00055 (D.N.M.) challenging PLO 7923 alleging failure to conduct environmental justice analysis, failure to prepare an EIS, and failure to meaningfully consult. The Case was dismissed without prejudice pursuant to an out of court Settlement Agreement between the United States and the Navajo Nation; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>given the anticipated DOI decision on or before June 24 2026, a settlement excluding Pueblo parties, it is recommended Pueblos take proactive steps to prepare for future litigation to challenge any revocation or significant modification of PLO 7923; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Acoma Pueblo with the support of APCG is asking Pueblos to join together, creating coordinated strategy for the defense of PLO 7923 from anticipated litigation to maintain the 10-mile boundary by authorizing pre-litigation preparation to be used against the U.S. Department of the Interior upon anticipated federal agency actions to rescind or significantly modify PLO 7923; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Acoma and Laguna as Intervenors in the existing Navajo Nation v. US litigation invites other Pueblos wishing to participate in a coordinated strategy for defense of PLO 7923 in anticipated future litigation were encouraged to discuss engagement with their respective counsel and Kaplan Kirsch LLP; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Tribal Council authorizes $10,000 to contribute to the efforts of protecting Chaco Canyon and the Greater Chaco Canyon.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Council hereby enacts the attached resolution entitled the "Chaco Canyon and the Chaco Environment Protection and Coordinated Strategy for the Defense of Public Land Order 7923 Act" authorizing engagement of Kaplan Kirsch LLP to represent Pueblo de San Ildefonso and other Pueblos interested in a coordinated strategy in protecting the withdrawal around Chaco Canyon. The representation is limited in scope to the litigation concerning PLO 7923. Kaplan Kirsch is providing a discounted rate of $100 per hour shared collectively among all participating Pueblos. Pueblo de San Ildefonso has placed a $10,000 financial limit on engaging Kaplan Kirsch.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>
        <u>CERTIFICATION</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on <u>June 10</u>, 2026, at a meeting with a vote of <u>8</u> in favor, <u>0</u> opposed, <u>1</u> abstaining and <u>1</u> absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Denise Moquino, Council Secretary</text>
    <text>
      <strong>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE SPONSOR(S): </strong>
      <strong>
        <u>Council Representatives</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Tom Garcia</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Brandi Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Perry Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raelene Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raymond J. Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Denise Moquino</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Gary Alan Roybal</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Kenneth Weahkee</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION TO THE GOVERNOR:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>Resolution No. <u>SI-R26-005</u> was presented to the Governor of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso on the</text>
    <text><u>11</u><sup><u>th</u></sup> day of <u>June</u>, 2026, pursuant to the governing Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Agreement"), GOVERNOR, Sec. 4(c), and will become effective after signature by the Governor or veto override by the Council.</text>
    <text>Denise Moquino, Council Secretary</text>
    <subheading>GOVERNOR'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>{ X } APPROVED</text>
    <text>{   } VETO - RETURNED TO COUNCIL WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this <u>12</u><sup><u>th</u></sup> day of <u>June</u>, 2026.</text>
    <text>Christopher A. Moquino, Governor</text>
    <text>Presented by the Governor to the Council on the _______ day of ________________, 2026.</text>
    <subheading>COUNCIL'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>Override of Governor's veto:</text>
    <text>{   } YES</text>
    <text>{   } NO</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Tom Garcia</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Brandi Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Perry Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raelene Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raymond J. Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Denise Moquino</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Gary Alan Roybal</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Kenneth Weahkee</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>
        <u>CERTIFICATION</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on _________________, 2026, at a meeting with a vote of ______ in favor, _____ opposed, _____ abstaining and _____ absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Denise Moquino, Council Secretary</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <codify:insert path="|2.3" codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|2.3.20">
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>2.3.20</num>
      <heading>Chaco Canyon and the Chaco Environment Protection and Coordinated Strategy for the Defense of Public Land Order 7923</heading>
    </container>
  </codify:insert>
  <attachment id="law">
    <codified:at path="2.3.20"/>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO</strong>
    </text>
    <heading type="law">CHACO CANYON AND THE CHACO ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND COORDINATED STRATEGY FOR THE DEFENSE OF PUBLIC LAND ORDER 7923</heading>
    <section>
      <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|2.3.20.010"/>
      <num codify:value="2.3.20.010">1.1</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text>This enactment shall be known as the "Chaco Canyon And The Chaco Environment Protection And Coordinated Strategy For The Defense Of Public Land Order 7923 Act" ("Act").</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|2.3.20.020"/>
      <num codify:value="2.3.20.020">1.2</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of this Act is to authorize the engagement of legal counsel for the protection of Chaco Canyon and the Greater Chaco Landscape.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|2.3.20.030"/>
      <num codify:value="2.3.20.030">1.3</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Pueblo de San Ildefonso maintains a strong and continuous cultural connection to Chaco Canyon and the Greater Chaco Landscape, being an enduring and vital part of our history and heritage, a place of deep extraordinary cultural, spiritual and historic importance to our Pueblo, spoken about in our songs, oral narratives, and ceremonies.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>On June 7, 2023, PLO No. 7923 withdrew approximately 336,404.42 acres of public land surrounding Chaco Canyon National Historic Park (CNHP) from location and entry under the United States mining laws, and from leasing under the mineral leasing laws for 20 years. The area generally encompasses a 10-mile-perimeter around CCNHP. Public Land Order 7923, carefully balance the federal government's domestic energy production priorities with honoring and protecting this irreplaceable landscape and its Tribal cultural properties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Bureau of Land Management under President Trump's Executive Order 14154 unleashing American Energy, intends to revoke the withdrawal of Chaco Canyon and surrounding areas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>On October 30, 2025, the BLM Farmington Field Office notified Pueblos of a federal undertaking to consider revocation or modification of Public Land Order 7923 -- the 10- mile withdrawal protecting federal lands and minerals surrounding Chaco Culture National Historical Park.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>This action threatens to upend years of coordination among Tribal Nations, federal agencies, and congressional partners who have worked to safeguard the Greater Chaco landscape. The Public Land Order 7923 withdrawal remains one of the few meaningful protections for an area of profound cultural, spiritual, and historical significance to the Pueblo peoples of New Mexico.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Navajo Nation sued the United States, Navajo Nation v. United States, No. 1:25-cv-00055 (D.N.M.) challenging PLO 7923 alleging failure to conduct environmental justice analysis, failure to prepare an EIS, and failure to meaningfully consult. The Case was dismissed without prejudice pursuant to an out of court Settlement Agreement between the United States and the Navajo Nation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Given the anticipated DOI decision on or before June 24 2026, a settlement excluding Pueblo parties, it is recommended Pueblos take proactive steps to prepare for future litigation to challenge any revocation or significant modification of PLO 7923.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Acoma Pueblo with the support of APCG is asking Pueblos to join together, creating coordinated strategy for the defense of PLO 7923 from anticipated litigation to maintain the 10-mile boundary by authorizing pre-litigation preparation to be used against the U.S. Department of the Interior upon anticipated federal agency actions to rescind or significantly modify PLO 7923.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>Acoma and Laguna as Intervenors in the existing Navajo Nation v. US litigation invites other Pueblos wishing to participate in a coordinated strategy for defense of PLO 7923 in anticipated future litigation were encouraged to discuss engagement with their respective counsel and Kaplan Kirsch LLP.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso Tribal Council authorizes $10,000 to contribute to the efforts of protecting Chaco Canyon and the Greater Chaco Canyon.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|2.3.20.040"/>
      <num codify:value="2.3.20.040">1.4</num>
      <heading>Authorization</heading>
      <text>The Council hereby authorizes the engagement of Kaplan Kirsch LLP to represent Pueblo de San Ildefonso and other Pueblos interested in a coordinated strategy in protecting the withdrawal around Chaco Canyon. The representation is limited in scope to the litigation concerning PLO 7923. Kaplan Kirsch is providing a discounted rate of $100 per hour shared collectively among all participating Pueblos. Pueblo de San Ildefonso has placed a $10,000 financial limit on engaging Kaplan Kirsch.</text>
    </section>
  </attachment>
</document>
