<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" id="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R26-008" codify:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code">
  <num>SI-R26-008</num>
  <heading>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO COUNCIL RESOLUTION NO. SI-R26-008</heading>
  <heading type="law">Third Party Billing Authorization Act</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2026-06-12</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res">Council Resolution No. SI-R26-008</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2026-06-10</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <preamble>At a duly called meeting of the Council of San Ildefonso Pueblo on the 10th day of June, 2026, the following resolution was adopted:</preamble>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Pueblo") is a sovereign and self-governing Tribe, recognized as such by the United States of America; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the sovereign authority of the Pueblo is vested in its Council and Governor; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo formally established its Health and Human Services Department via Part 14.1.1.010 of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code, and Council Resolution No. SI-R12-022, dated June 18, 2012; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council enacted SI-R25-007, Part 6.5.39, "The P.L 93-638 Contract Authorization Act", which authorizes the Governor "to negotiate and execute a contract agreement and to take any other actions necessary to effectuate a contract for the following BIA-contracted, IHS-contracted, and other federal programs including but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Consolidated Tribal Government Program</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Indian Child Welfare Act Program</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Johnson O'Malley Program</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Scholarships Program</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>Community Health Representatives</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>Alcohol and Substance Abuse, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7.</num>
        <text>Any other IHS PFSA that is eligible to contract by the Pueblo in future contracts";</text>
      </para>
      <text>And,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council acknowledges the 2023 New Mexico State Plan Amendment ("SPA") 23-0011 and SPA 21-0014, allowing Medicaid reimbursement for services of certified Community Health Workers and Representatives and Non-Emergency Transportation; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the HHSD provides various health services to beneficiaries under the Community Health Worker/Representative program and to eligible community members under the Behavioral Health program through its identified behavioral health provider; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the HHSD will begin providing Non-Emergency Transport services, prevention services, and enhancing the community's access to behavioral health services; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council recognizes that future and existing services are considered "billable services" by third-party payers, including Medicaid and authorized Managed Healthcare Organizations; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council acknowledges the benefits to the Pueblo of engaging in third-party billing for providing critical health services; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council acknowledges all Federal and State regulations associated with implementing third party billing, including the requirement to reinvest all third party revenue back into health programs for support and enhanced services as found in 25 U.S.C. § 5325(m)1.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Council hereby enacts the attached resolution entitled the "THIRD PARTY BILLING AUTHORIZATION ACT".</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>
        <u>CERTIFICATION</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on <u> June 10</u>, 2026, at a meeting with a vote of <u>8</u> in favor, <u>0</u> opposed, <u>1</u> abstaining and <u>1</u> absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Denise Moquino, Council Secretary</text>
    <text>
      <strong>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE SPONSOR(S): </strong>
      <strong>
        <u>Council Representatives</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Tom Garcia</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Brandi Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Perry Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raelene Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raymond J. Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Denise Moquino</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Gary Alan Roybal</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Kenneth Weahkee</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION TO THE GOVERNOR:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>Resolution No. <u>SI-R26-008</u> was presented to the Governor of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso on the</text>
    <text><u>11</u><sup><u>th</u></sup> day of <u>June</u>, 2026, pursuant to the governing Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Agreement"), GOVERNOR, Sec. 4(c), and will become effective after signature by the Governor or veto override by the Council.</text>
    <text>Denise Moquino, Council Secretary</text>
    <subheading>GOVERNOR'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>{ X } APPROVED</text>
    <text>{   } VETO - RETURNED TO COUNCIL WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this <u>12</u><sup><u>th</u></sup> day of <u>June</u>, 2026.</text>
    <text>Christopher A. Moquino, Governor</text>
    <text>Presented by the Governor to the Council on the _______ day of ________________, 2026.</text>
    <subheading>COUNCIL'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>Override of Governor's veto:</text>
    <text>{   } YES</text>
    <text>{   } NO</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Tom Garcia</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Brandi Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Perry Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raelene Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raymond J. Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Denise Moquino</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Gary Alan Roybal</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Kenneth Weahkee</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>
        <u>CERTIFICATION</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on _________________, 2026, at a meeting with a vote of ______ in favor, _____ opposed, _____ abstaining and _____ absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Denise Moquino, Council Secretary</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <codify:insert path="|6.5" codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|6.5.42">
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>6.5.42</num>
      <heading>Third Party Billing Authorization Act</heading>
    </container>
  </codify:insert>
  <attachment id="law">
    <codified:at path="6.5.42"/>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO</strong>
    </text>
    <heading type="law">THIRD PARTY BILLING AUTHORIZATION ACT</heading>
    <section>
      <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|6.5.42.010"/>
      <num codify:value="6.5.42.010">1.1</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text>This enactment shall be known as the "Third Party Billing Authorization Act" ("Act")</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|6.5.42.020"/>
      <num codify:value="6.5.42.020">1.2</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of this Act is to authorize all programs of the Health and Human Services Department ("HHSD") to engage in third party billing for all eligible services, including services provided through Community Health Worker/Representative program, Non-Emergency Transportation, and Behavioral Health services.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|6.5.42.030"/>
      <num codify:value="6.5.42.030">1.3</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Pueblo formally established its Health and Human Services Department via Part 14.1.1.010 of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code, and Council Resolution No. SI-R12-022, dated June 18, 2012; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Council enacted SI-R25-007, Part 6.5.39, "The P.L 93-638 Contract Authorization Act", which authorizes the Governor "to negotiate and execute a contract agreement and to take any other actions necessary to effectuate a contract for the following BIA- contracted, IHS-contracted, and other federal programs including but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num codify:value="(1)">1.</num>
          <text>Consolidated Tribal Government Program</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num codify:value="(2)">2.</num>
          <text>Indian Child Welfare Act Program</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num codify:value="(3)">3.</num>
          <text>Johnson O'Malley Program</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num codify:value="(4)">4.</num>
          <text>Scholarships Program</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num codify:value="(5)">5.</num>
          <text>Community Health Representatives</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num codify:value="(6)">6.</num>
          <text>Alcohol and Substance Abuse, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num codify:value="(7)">7.</num>
          <text>Any other IHS PFSA that is eligible to contract by the Pueblo in future contracts"</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Council acknowledges the 2023 New Mexico State Plan Amendment ("SPA") 23- 0011 and SPA 21-0014, allowing Medicaid reimbursement for services of certified Community Health Workers and Representatives and Non-Emergency Transportation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The HHSD provides various health services to beneficiaries under the Community Health Worker/Representative program and to eligible community members under the Behavioral Health program through its identified behavioral health provider.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The HHSD will begin providing Non-Emergency Transport services, prevention services, and enhancing the community's access to behavioral health services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>The Council recognizes that future and existing services are considered "billable services" by third party payers including Medicaid and authorized Managed Healthcare Organizations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>The Council acknowledges the benefits to the Pueblo of engaging in third party billing for providing critical health services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>The Council acknowledges all Federal and State regulations associated with implementing third party billing, including the requirement to reinvest all third party revenue back into health programs for support and enhanced services as found in 25 U.S.C. § 5325(m)1.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|6.5.42.040"/>
      <num codify:value="6.5.42.040">1.4</num>
      <heading>Authorization</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Governor is authorized to negotiate and execute contract agreements and to take any other actions necessary to effectuate a contract with the following Third Party Payers:</text>
        <text>State Authorized Medicaid and Medicare programs<br/>Presbyterian Health Care<br/>Blue Cross Blue Shield<br/>Molina Health Care<br/>United Health Care</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Governor is authorized to determine whether, and to the extent, non-native clients may access the Pueblo's health services, if they are otherwise eligible.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Governor is authorized and directed to develop and implement such finance and accounting policies, procedures, and reporting requirements specific to third party billing, necessary for the Pueblo's compliance with all State and Federal regulations, laws, and requirements. Governor shall develop the third party billing policies and procedures and present them to the Council for approval within thirty (30) days of enactment of this Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The Governor and Executive Branch are hereby authorized to establish any necessary positions/offices within the HHSD to support efficient and policy compliant third party billing operations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The Governor is authorized to further pursue contracting all eligible IHS PSFAs that would result in enhanced health services to the Pueblo.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>The Governor or his designated representative shall provide financial reports on third party billing progress as often as directed by Council.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </attachment>
</document>
