<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" id="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014" codify:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codify:path="15.1">
  <num>SI-R23-014</num>
  <heading>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO COUNCIL RESOLUTION NO. SI-R23-014</heading>
  <heading type="law">Authorizing the San Ildefonso Housing Authority to Apply for a 2023 Indian Community Development Block Grant on Behalf of the Pueblo, Evidence of Citizen Participation and Commitment of Tribal Funds for the Project</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2023-09-08</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res">Council Resolution No. SI-R23-014</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2023-09-07</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <preamble>At a duly called meeting of the Council of San Ildefonso Pueblo on the 7th day of September, 2023, the following Resolution was adopted:</preamble>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Pueblo") is a sovereign and self-governing Tribe, recognized as such by the United States of America; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the sovereign authority of the Pueblo is vested in its Council and Governor; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>San Ildefonso Housing Authority ("SIHA") is the Tribally Designated Housing Entity ("TDHE") authorized to develop, rehabilitate and manage affordable housing activities for San Ildefonso and to participate in the design and implementation of comprehensive community and housing development activities; and; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo has determined that ICDBG Eligible families ability to purchase safe, sustainable and affordable housing throughout the reservation is essential to ensuring ICDBG Eligible families are able to remain living on the reservation and to ensure the health, safety and well-being of San Ildefonso Tribal members is critical to the viability of the Pueblo community; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo and SIHA have determined that the lack of financial and other assistance in the form of Homeownership Assistance is an impediment to ICDBG Eligible families in need of the ICDBG funding to acquire homes on the Pueblo to achieve homeownership; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>eligible Tribal Organizations are permitted to submit applications under the Indian Community Development Block Grant for Indian Tribes and Alaska Villages regulation 24 CFR 1003.5(b); and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>SIHA is recognized by the Bureau of Indian Affairs as an eligible Tribal Organization as defined in Title I of the Indian Self Determination Education and Assistance Act, and as a Tribal Organization, the Pueblo Housing Authority is also therefore an eligible recipient under that Act; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo must meet certain threshold requirements in order to be deemed eligible for ICDBG funding whether the application is made directly by the Pueblo or on the Pueblo's behalf by an eligible tribal organization and the Pueblo intends to fully comply with the threshold requirements and of the 2023 ICDBG application process, including the citizen participation requirements; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo, through activities carried by SIHA, sought and considered community input and posted the Citizen Participation Statement, Budget and Schedule for the Homeownership Assistance Project in advance of the 2023 Indian Community Development Block Grant Application in compliance with the Notice of Funding Availability governing the contents of the application for 2023 ICDBG funding expressed at 24 C.F.R. ยง 1003.604(a), and has considered comments received in preparing the application; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>SIHA has adopted a code of ethics policy and, in coordination with the Pueblo, prepared and disclosed to the public a statement of conflict of interests, specifically that no conflict of interest exists within the qualified applicants for the Homeownership Assistance project nor the criteria for the selection of the proposed beneficiaries; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>SIHA has adopted the Fiscal Management and Procurement and Contract Management policies that meets 2 CFR 200 requirements.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED THAT,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council hereby authorizes the San Ildefonso Housing Authority to apply for Fiscal Year 2023 ICDGB funding on behalf of the Pueblo.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Pueblo de San Ildefonso hereby,</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>commits $2,640,000 in forgivable mortgages to eligible homebuyers to acquire buildable lots;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>commits $225,000 in tribal funds for the Project;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>certifies the Citizen Participation requirements were followed as expressed in 24 C.F.R. ยง 1003.604(a) and therefore has met those requirements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>authorizes San Ildefonso Housing Authority to take any and all actions necessary to effectuate the intent of the Project and the 2023 ICDBG application and process.</text>
      </para>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>
        <u>CERTIFICATION</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on <u>September 7</u>, 2023, at a meeting with a vote of <u>9</u> in favor, <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining and <u>1</u> absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>________________________________</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
    <text>
      <strong>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE SPONSOR(S): </strong>
      <strong>
        <u>Council Representatives</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Tom Garcia</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>M. Wayne Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Michael Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Nichole Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Perry Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raymond J. Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Martinez</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Denise Moquino</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Irene Tse-Pe</td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION TO THE GOVERNOR:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>Resolution No. <u>SI-R23-014</u> was presented to the Governor of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso on the <u>7</u><sup><u>th</u></sup> day of <u>September</u>, 2023, pursuant to the Governing document of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Agreement"), GOVERNOR, Sec. 4(c), and will become effective after signature by the Governor or veto override by the Council.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
    <subheading>GOVERNOR'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>{ X } APPROVED</text>
    <text>{   } VETO - RETURNED TO COUNCIL WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this <u>8</u><sup><u>th</u></sup> day of <u> September</u>, 2023.</text>
    <text>Christopher A. Moquino, Governor</text>
    <text>Presented by the Governor to the Council on the _______ day of ________________, 2023.</text>
    <subheading>COUNCIL'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>Override of Governor's veto:</text>
    <text>{   } YES</text>
    <text>{   } NO</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Tom Garcia</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>M. Wayne Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Michael Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Nichole Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Perry Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Raymond J. Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thomas Martinez</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Denise Moquino</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Irene Tse-Pe</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>
        <u>CERTIFICATION</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on _________________, 2023, at a meeting with a vote of ______ in favor, _____ opposed, _____ abstaining and _____ absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|15.1.13">
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.13</num>
      <heading>Authorizing the San Ildefonso Housing Authority to Apply for a 2023 Indian Community Development Block Grant on Behalf of the Pueblo, Evidence of Citizen Participation and Commitment of Tribal Funds for the Project</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014"/>
    </container>
  </codify:insert>
  <attachment id="law">
    <codified:at path="15.1.13"/>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO</strong>
    </text>
    <heading type="law">AUTHORIZING THE SAN ILDEFONSO HOUSING AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR A 2023 INDIAN COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT BLOCK GRANT ON BEHALF OF THE PUEBLO, EVIDENCE OF CITIZEN PARTICIPATION AND COMMITMENT OF TRIBAL FUNDS FOR THE PROJECT</heading>
    <section>
      <codify:insert num-value="15.1.13.010" codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|15.1.13.010"/>
      <num>1.1</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text>This enactment shall be known as the "AUTHORIZATION FOR THE SAN ILDEFONSO HOUSING AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR A 2023 INDIAN COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT BLOCK GRANT ON BEHALF OF THE PUEBLO" ("Act").</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert num-value="15.1.13.020" codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|15.1.13.020"/>
      <num>1.2</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of this resolution is to authorize the San Ildefonso Housing Authority to apply for an Indian Community Development Block Grant for eligible families to be able to remain living on the reservation and to ensure the health, safety and well-being of San Ildefonso Tribal members is critical to the viability of the Pueblo community.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert num-value="15.1.13.030" codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|15.1.13.030"/>
      <num>1.3</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <text>The San Ildefonso Council hereby finds that,</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>San Ildefonso Housing Authority ("SIHA") is the Tribally Designated Housing Entity ("TDHE") authorized to develop, rehabilitate and manage affordable housing activities for San Ildefonso and to participate in the design and implementation of comprehensive community and housing development activities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Pueblo has determined that ICDBG Eligible families ability to purchase safe, sustainable and affordable housing throughout the reservation is essential to ensuring ICDBG Eligible families are able to remain living on the reservation and to ensure the health, safety and well-being of San Ildefonso Tribal members is critical to the viability of the Pueblo community.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Pueblo and SIHA have determined that the lack of financial and other assistance in the form of Homeownership Assistance is an impediment to ICDBG Eligible families in need of the ICDBG funding to acquire homes on the Pueblo to achieve homeownership.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Eligible Tribal Organizations are permitted to submit applications under the Indian Community Development Block Grant for Indian Tribes and Alaska Villages regulation 24 CFR 1003.5(b).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>SIHA is recognized by the Bureau of Indian Affairs as an eligible Tribal Organization as defined in Title I of the Indian Self Determination Education and Assistance Act, and as a Tribal Organization, the Pueblo Housing Authority is also therefore an eligible recipient under that Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>The Pueblo must meet certain threshold requirements in order to be deemed eligible for ICDBG funding whether the application is made directly by the Pueblo or on the Pueblo's behalf by an eligible tribal organization and the Pueblo intends to fully comply with the threshold requirements and of the 2023 ICDBG application process, including the citizen participation requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>The Pueblo, through activities carried by SIHA, sought and considered community input and posted the Citizen Participation Statement, Budget and Schedule for the Homeownership Assistance Project in advance of the 2023 Indian Community Development Block Grant Application in compliance with the Notice of Funding Availability governing the contents of the application for 2023 ICDBG funding expressed at 24 C.F.R. ยง 1003.604(a), and has considered comments received in preparing the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>SIHA has adopted a code of ethics policy and, in coordination with the Pueblo, prepared and disclosed to the public a statement of conflict of interests, specifically that no conflict of interest exists within the qualified applicants for the Homeownership Assistance project nor the criteria for the selection of the proposed beneficiaries.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>SIHA has adopted the Fiscal Management and Procurement and Contract Management policies that meets 2 CFR 200 requirements.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert num-value="15.1.13.040" codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="|15.1.13.040"/>
      <num>1.4</num>
      <heading>Authorizations</heading>
      <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso hereby,</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>commits $2,640,000 in forgivable mortgages to eligible homebuyers to acquire buildable lots.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>commits $225,000 in tribal funds for the Project.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>certifies the Citizen Participation requirements were followed as expressed in 24 C.F.R. ยง 1003.604(a) and therefore has met those requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>authorizes San Ildefonso Housing Authority to take any and all actions necessary to effectuate the intent of the Project and the 2023 ICDBG application and process.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </attachment>
</document>
