<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" codify:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codify:path="15.1" id="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005">
  <num>SI-R19-005</num>
  <heading>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO COUNCIL RESOLUTION NO. SI-R19-005</heading>
  <heading type="law">Confirming Delegation of Authority to the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority to Apply for Bureau of Indian Affairs, Department of Interior Office of Indian Energy and Economic Development, Energy and Mineral Development Grant to Conduct a Solar Energy Feasibility Assessment</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2019-02-13</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res">Council Resolution No. SI-R19-005</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2019-02-12</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <preamble>At a duly called meeting of the Council of San Ildefonso Pueblo on the 12th day of February, 2019, the following Resolution was adopted:</preamble>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Pueblo') is a sovereign and self-governing Tribe, recognized as such by the United States of America; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>On April 12, 2000 the Tribal Council adopted Ordinance No. SI-R00-001, establishing the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA); and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority ("NPHA") is the Tribally Designated Housing Authority ("TDHE") for the Pueblos of Tesuque, Picuris, and San Ildefonso, established by such Pueblos pursuant to § 4(18) and (21) of the Native American Housing and Self Determination Act of 1996, 25 U.S.C. §§ 4401 et seq. ("NAHASDA") for developing, operating, and managing housing units assisted by the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD); and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>in addition to the environmental benefits, the Pueblo de San Ildefonso is interested in developing solar photovoltaic (PV) opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso to reduce electric utility costs and/or generate additional revenue to support Tribal programs; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Tribal Leadership understands that the appropriate step towards developing solar</text>
      <text>PV opportunities is to hire a qualified consultant to conduct a feasibility assessment 	to identify and evaluate possible projects; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Bureau of Indian Affairs (BIA), Department of the Interior Office of Indian Energy and Economic Development, Division of Energy and Mineral Development (DEMD), Energy and Mineral Development Program (EMDP) is soliciting proposals for the Grant Program ("Funding Program") to Assess, Evaluate, and Promote Development of Tribal Energy and Mineral Resources (BIA-000-0009-TEDC).</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Council hereby certifies that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The Tribal Council hereby authorizes NPHA to coordinate with Pueblo de San Ildefonso staff to prepare and submit the application to the BIA DEMD in response to the Funding Program solicitation (BIA-000-0009-TEDC) on behalf of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>For the purposes of the Funding Program, the Tribal Council hereby designates the NPHA Executive Director, Jon Paul Romero, as the Tribal Project Lead to oversee the project work, make authorized decisions during the course of the project, and be responsible for submitting quarterly and final progress reports, plus financial status reports, as required by the Funding Program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>The Tribal Council hereby directs NPHA to hire a consultant to complete the feasibility assessment of solar PV opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso, in compliance with all applicable procurement requirements.</text>
      </para>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Council hereby certifies that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso is committed devoting appropriate resources and coordinating with NPHA and the consultant to facilitate successful completion of the feasibility assessment of solar PV project opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso is willing to consider developing viable solar PV projects, as determined by the completed feasibility assessment.</text>
      </para>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text/>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>That the Council hereby enacts the attached law entitled "CONFIRMING DELEGATION OF AUTHORITY TO THE NORTHERN PUEBLOS HOUSING AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR BUREAU OF INDIAN AFFAIRS, DEPARTMENT OF INTERIOR OFFICE OF INDIAN ENERGY AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT, ENERGY AND MINERAL DEVELOPMENT GRANT TO CONDUCT A SOLAR ENERGY FEASIBILITY ASSESSMENT;" and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>That this Resolution becomes effective immediately and that the Tribal Council hereby authorizes and directs the Governor or his designee to take such actions as deemed necessary to carry out the intent and purpose of this Resolution.</text>
      </para>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on February 12 , 2019, at a meeting with a vote of 10 in favor, 0 opposed, 0 abstaining and 0 absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
    <text>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE SPONSOR(S):    Council Representatives</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
          <th>YES</th>
          <th>NO</th>
          <th>ABSTAIN</th>
          <th>ABSENT</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>William Stuart Christian</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Glenda Fred-Weahkee</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Thelma Gonzales</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Christopher Moquino</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Raymond J. Martinez</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Tim Martinez</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>James L. Naranjo</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Leon T. Roybal</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Irene Tse-Pe</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION TO THE GOVERNOR:</text>
    <text>Resolution No. SI-R19-005 was presented to the Governor of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso on the 12th  day of February, 2019, pursuant to the Governing document of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Agreement"), GOVERNOR, Sec. 4(c), and will become effective after signature by the Governor or veto override by the Council.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
    <subheading>GOVERNOR'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>{    } 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>{    }	VETO - RETURNED TO COUNCIL WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this __________ day of _______________________, 2019.</text>
    <text>Perry Martinez, Governor</text>
    <text>Presented by the Governor to the Council on the _______ day of ________________, 2019.</text>
    <subheading>COUNCIL'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>Override of Governor's veto:</text>
    <text>{    } 	YES</text>
    <text>{    }	NO</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
          <th>YES</th>
          <th>NO</th>
          <th>ABSTAIN</th>
          <th>ABSENT</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>William Stuart Christian</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Glenda Fred-Weahkee</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Thelma Gonzales</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Christopher Moquino</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Raymond J. Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Tim Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>James L. Naranjo</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Leon T. Roybal</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Irene Tse-Pe</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on _________________, 2019, at a meeting with a vote of ______ in favor, _____ opposed, _____ abstaining and _____ absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <codify:insert codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="15.1.4">
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.4</num>
      <heading>Confirming Delegation of Authority to the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority to Apply for Bureau of Indian Affairs, Department of Interior Office of Indian Energy and Economic Development, Energy and Mineral Development Grant to Conduct a Solar Energy Feasibility Assessment</heading>
    </container>
  </codify:insert>
  <attachment id="law">
    <codified:at path="15.1.4"/>
    <text>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO</text>
    <heading>CONFIRMING DELEGATION OF AUTHORITY TO THE NORTHERN PUEBLOS HOUSING AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR BUREAU OF INDIAN AFFAIRS, DEPARTMENT OF INTERIOR OFFICE OF INDIAN ENERGY AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT, ENERGY AND MINERAL DEVELOPMENT GRANT TO CONDUCT A SOLAR ENERGY FEASIBILITY ASSESSMENT</heading>
    <section>
      <codify:insert num-value="15.1.4.010" codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="15.1.4.010"/>
      <num>1.1</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text>This enactment shall be known as "CONFIRMING DELEGATION OF AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR BUREAU OF INDIAN AFFAIRS, DEPARTMENT OF INTERIOR OFFICE OF INDIAN ENERGY AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT, ENERGY AND MINERAL DEVELOPMENT GRANT TO CONDUCT A SOLAR ENERGY FEASIBILITY ASSESSMENT" ("Act").</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert num-value="15.1.4.020" codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="15.1.4.020"/>
      <num>1.2</num>
      <heading>Definitions</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>"Agreement" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Governing Agreement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"Council" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>"Pueblo" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert num-value="15.1.4.030" codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="15.1.4.030"/>
      <num>1.3</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of this Act is to provide the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority, in coordination with the Pueblo, with authority to apply for grant funding to conduct a feasibility assessment for utilization in developing solar photovoltaic (PV) opportunities at the Pueblo.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert num-value="15.1.4.040" codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="15.1.4.040"/>
      <num>1.4</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <text>The Council hereby finds that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Northern Pueblos Housing Authority ("NPHA") is the Tribally Designated Housing Authority ("TDHE") for the Pueblos of Tesuque, Picuris, and San Ildefonso, established by such Pueblos pursuant to § 4(18) and (21) of the Native American Housing and Self Determination Act of 1996, 25 U.S.C. §§ 4401 <em>et seq</em>. ("NAHASDA") for developing, operating, and managing housing units assisted by the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>In addition to the environmental benefits, the Pueblo de San Ildefonso is interested in developing solar photovoltaic (PV) opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso to reduce electric utility costs and/or generate additional revenue to support Tribal programs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Tribal Leadership understands that the appropriate step towards developing solar PV opportunities is to hire a qualified consultant to conduct a feasibility assessment to identify and evaluate possible projects; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The Bureau of Indian Affairs (BIA), Department of the Interior Office of Indian Energy and Economic Development, Division of Energy and Mineral Development (DEMD), Energy and Mineral Development Program (EMDP) is</text>
        <text>soliciting proposals for the Grant Program ("Funding Program") to Assess, Evaluate, and Promote Development of Tribal Energy and Mineral Resources (BIA-000-0009-TEDC); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso is committed devoting appropriate resources and coordinating with NPHA and the consultant to facilitate successful completion of the feasibility assessment of solar PV project opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso is willing to consider developing viable solar PV projects, as determined by the completed feasibility assessment.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <codify:insert num-value="15.1.4.050" codified:doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code" codified:path="15.1.4.050"/>
      <num>1.5</num>
      <heading>Authorizations</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Council hereby authorizes NPHA to coordinate with the Pueblo de San Ildefonso staff to prepare and submit the application to the BIA DEMD in response to the Funding Program solicitation (BIA-000-0009-TEDC) on behalf of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>For the purposes of the Funding Program, the Tribal Council hereby designates the NPHA Executive Director, Jon Paul Romero, as the Tribal Project Lead to oversee the project work, make authorized decisions during the course of the project, and be responsible for submitting quarterly and final progress reports, plus financial status reports, as required by the Funding Program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Council hereby directs NPHA to hire a consultant to complete the feasibility assessment of solar PV opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso, in compliance with all applicable procurement requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso is committed devoting appropriate resources and coordinating with NPHA and the consultant to facilitate successful completion of the feasibility assessment of solar PV project opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Council hereby authorizes and directs the Governor or his designee to take such actions as deemed necessary to carry out the intent and purpose of this Resolution.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </attachment>
</document>
