<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" containing-doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>15</num>
  <heading>HOUSING</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>15.1</num>
    <heading>Housing</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.1</num>
      <heading>Housing Authority ICDBG Funding Act of 2016</heading>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes">This law was originally enacted pursuant to Council Resolution No. SI-R16-007, dated May 25, 2016.</annotation>
      </annotations>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.1.010</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Northern Pueblos Housing Authority ("NPHA") is the Tribally Designated Housing Authority ("TDHE") for the Pueblos of San Ildefonso, Picuris, and Tesuque, established by such Pueblos pursuant to § 4(18) and (21) of the Native American Housing and Self Determination Act of 1996, 25 U.S.C. §§ 4401 <em>et seq.</em> ("NAHASDA") for developing, operating, and managing housing units assisted by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development ("HUD");</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo has identified rehabilitation of low-income resident homes as an urgent, high priority housing need in its 2016 Indian Housing Plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Council wishes to authorize NPHA to apply for 2016 Indian Community Development Block Grant (ICDBG) funds on behalf of the Pueblo to finance the rehabilitation of homes of low-income Pueblo residents.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.1.020</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "Housing Authority ICDBG Funding Act of 2016."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.1.030</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Pueblo" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Act" means the Housing Authority ICDBG Funding Act of 2016.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.1.040</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this Act is authorize the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority to apply for and receive funds HUD ICDBG funds to rehabilitate fourteen low income residents' homes.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.1.050</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On April 12, 2000, the Council adopted Ordinance No. SI-R00-001, establishing the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>NPHA is the Tribally Designated Housing Authority ("TDHE") for the Pueblos of San Ildefonso, Picuris, and Tesuque, established by such Pueblos pursuant to §4(18) and (21) of the Native American Housing and Self Determination Act of 1996, 25 U.S.C. §§ 4401 <em>et seq.</em> ("NAHASDA") for developing, operating, and managing housing units assisted by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo has directed NPHA to maintain a waiting list of local residents requesting and eligible to receive home rehabilitation services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Home inspections of residents requesting services have confirmed numerous serious health, safety, energy efficiency, and code compliance issues that could be resolved by an Indian Community Development Block Grant (ICDBG) funded rehabilitation project;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The number of local residents requesting and eligible to receive home rehabilitation services exceeds all funds the Pueblo is eligible to obtain to provide the needed services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo has identified rehabilitation of low-income resident homes as an urgent, high priority housing need in its 2016 Indian Housing Plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Council wishes NPHA to apply for $605,000 in 2016 Indian Community Development Block Grant (ICDBG) on behalf of the Pueblo to finance the rehabilitation of fourteen homes of low-income Pueblo residents; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Pursuant to the Notice of Funding Availability for the ICDBG program, NPHA, acting on behalf of the tribe, must meet certain threshold requirements in order to be deemed eligible for funding; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Acting through NPHA, the Council intends to fully comply with the programmatic and project-related threshold requirements of the ICDBG program.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.1.060</num>
        <heading>Authorization</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby certifies that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A Community Development Statement pertaining to the authorized 2016 ICDBG application for housing rehabilitation, a record of the posting of the Statement, and public meeting record provided to the Council and to be included by NPHA in the ICDBG application documents that all requirements of citizen participation found at 24 C.F.R. 1003.604 have been met;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The 2016 ICDBG application for housing rehabilitation has been made available to residents;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>No public comments affecting the content of the ICDBG proposal were received pursuant to the opportunity provided for citizen participation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The methodology and information provided by NPHA for purposes of meeting ICDBG threshold and service standards, notably in respect to the certification of the income-eligibility of the intended beneficiaries of the project, were systematically collected, are reliable, and are independently verifiable, and are approved by the Council;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Council accepts the ICDBG funding condition that rehabilitation not be provided to any Current Assisted Stock (CAS) homeowner that is not current in their payments;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of ICDBG funding and program delivery, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the applicable provisions contained in the in the Building and Construction Codes as codified in Title 14 of the New Mexico Administrative Code as may be amended from time to time, or the International Building Codes, whichever is more stringent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of ICDBG funding and program delivery, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The NPHA Code of Conduct Policy Statement adopted on February 7, 2011 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 11-6;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The applicable provisions contained in the Ninth Amended and Restated NPHA Procurement, Inventory, Disposition, and Housing Standards Policy, adopted on February 7, 2011 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 11-6;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The Fifth Amended and Restated NPHA Management Policy, adopted on March 19, 2014 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2014-01;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The Fourteenth Amended and Restated Personnel Policy adopted on November 21, 2012 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2012-10;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The Fourth Amended and Restated NPHA Financial Management and Internal Controls Policy, adopted on February 7, 2011 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 11-6 in relation to administration of ICDBG funds;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>The Fourth Amended and Restated NPHA Housing Rehabilitation Standards and Policy adopted on January 19, 2011 by Board Resolution Number 11-1;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The Council affirms that $56,250 in funds set-aside for substantial housing rehabilitation in the Pueblo's 2016 Indian Housing Plan are intended for use as leverage funding in support of the authorized application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Council hereby specifically authorizes NPHA to apply 	for $605,000 in 2016 ICDBG funds on behalf of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The Council hereby approves and adopts this resolution in accordance with the requirements of the Agreement, according to published Council procedures, and authorizes and directs the Governor, or his designee, to take such actions as deemed necessary to carry out 	the intent of this Resolution and law.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.2</num>
      <heading>Confirming Delegation of Authority to the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority to Apply for 2017 ICDBG Funding for Rehabilitation of Existing Homes for Low-Income Pueblo Members</heading>
      <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.2.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as "CONFIRMING DELEGATION OF AUTHORITY TO THE NORTHERN PUEBLOS HOUSING AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR 2017 ICDBG FUNDING FOR REHABILITATION OF EXISTING HOMES FOR LOW- INCOME PUEBLO MEMBERS," or in the abbreviated form, the "2017 ICDBG GRANT APPLICATION."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.2.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this enactment is to provide the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA) with the authority to apply for 2017 funding under the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) Indian Community Development Block Grant (ICDBG) Program for rehabilitation of existing homes of low-income San Ildefonso Pueblo members.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.2.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On April 12, 2000, the Tribal Council adopted Ordinance No. SI-R00-001, establishing the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Northern Pueblos Housing Authority  is the Tribally Designated Housing Authority ("TDHE") for the Pueblos of San Ildefonso, Picuris, and Tesuque, established by such Pueblos pursuant to § 4(18) and (21) of the Native American Housing and Self Determination Act of 1996, 25 U.S.C. §§ 4401 <em>et seq.</em> ("NAHASDA") for developing, operating, and managing housing units assisted by the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A community meeting was held on April 19, 2017, and Rehabilitation of Existing Homes for Low-Income Pueblo Members was identified as a project priority for the ICDBG Program application and that Citizen (community) participation was adhered to.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.2.040</num>
        <heading>Certifications</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby certifies that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All requirements of citizen participation found at 24 C.F.R. 1003.604 have been met; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Council has considered all comments and views made by residents of the Pueblo; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Council has had the application modified, as necessary; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The ICDBG application has been made available to residents; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The methodology and information provided by NPHA for purposes of meeting ICDBG threshold and service standards, notably in respect to the certification of the income-eligibility of the intended beneficiaries of the project, were systematically collected, are statistically reliable, and to the greatest extent feasible, are independently verifiable, and are approved by the Council; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of ICDBG funding and program delivery, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the applicable provisions contained in the in the Building and Construction Codes as codified in Title 14 of the New Mexico Administrative Code as may be amended from time to time, or the International Building Codes, whichever is more stringent.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.2.050</num>
        <heading>Compliance and Provisions</heading>
        <text>For the purpose of ICDBG funding and program delivery, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with these provisions which collectively enumerate all essential ethics in contracting and conflicts of interest requirements, in relation to the administration and management of ICDBG funds and the delivery of services there under:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The NPHA Code of Conduct Policy Statement Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The applicable provisions contained in the Tenth Amended and Restated NPHA Procurement, Inventory, Disposition, and Housing Standards Policy, Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Seventh Amended and Restated NPHA Management Policy, Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Fifteenth Amended and Restated NPHA Personnel Policy Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>That for the purpose of administering ICDBG funding, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the Fifth Amended and Restated NPHA Financial Management and Internal Controls Policy, Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09 in relation to administration of ICDBG funds;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>That for the purpose of provision of rehabilitation services, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the Fourth Amended and Restated NPHA Housing Rehabilitation Standards and Policy adopted on January 19, 2011 by Board Resolution Number 11-1;</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="attachments|law|1.5" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.2.060</num>
        <heading>Grant Authorization</heading>
        <text>The Governor or his designee is hereby authorized to take such actions as deemed necessary to carry out the intent and purpose of this Resolution.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="attachments|law|1.6" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.3</num>
      <heading>Confirming Delegation of Authority to the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority to Apply for 2018 ICDBG Funding for Rehabilitation of Existing Homes for Low Income Pueblo Members</heading>
      <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.3.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as "CONFIRMING DELEGATION OF AUTHORITY TO THE NORTHERN PUEBLOS HOUSING AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR 2018 ICDBG FUNDING FOR REHABILITATION OF EXISTING HOMES FOR LOW- INCOME PUEBLO MEMBERS," or in the abbreviated form, the "2018 ICDBG GRANT APPLICATION."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.3.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this enactment is to provide the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA) with the authority to apply for 2018 funding under the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) Indian Community Development Block Grant (ICDBG) Program for rehabilitation of existing homes of low-income San Ildefonso Pueblo members.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.3.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On April 12, 2000, the Tribal Council adopted Ordinance No. SI-R00-001, establishing the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Northern Pueblos Housing Authority  is the Tribally Designated Housing Authority ("TDHE") for the Pueblos of San Ildefonso, Picuris, and Tesuque, established by such Pueblos pursuant to § 4(18) and (21) of the Native American Housing and Self Determination Act of 1996, 25 U.S.C. §§ 4401 <em>et seq.</em> ("NAHASDA") for developing, operating, and managing housing units assisted by the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A community meeting was held on April 19, 2017, and Rehabilitation of Existing Homes for Low-Income Pueblo Members was identified as a project priority for the ICDBG Program application and that Citizen (community) participation was adhered to.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.3.040</num>
        <heading>Certifications</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby certifies that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All requirements of citizen participation found at 24 C.F.R. 1003.604 have been met; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Council has considered all comments and views made by residents of the Pueblo; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Council has had the application modified, as necessary; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The ICDBG application has been made available to residents; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The methodology and information provided by NPHA for purposes of meeting ICDBG threshold and service standards, notably in respect to the certification of the income-eligibility of the intended beneficiaries of the project, were systematically collected, are statistically reliable, and to the greatest extent feasible, are independently verifiable, and are approved by the Council; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of ICDBG funding and program delivery, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the applicable provisions contained in the in the Building and Construction Codes as codified in Title 14 of the New Mexico Administrative Code as may be amended from time to time, or the International Building Codes, whichever is more stringent.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.3.050</num>
        <heading>Compliance and Provisions</heading>
        <text>For the purpose of ICDBG funding and program delivery, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with these provisions which collectively enumerate all essential ethics in contracting and conflicts of interest requirements, in relation to the administration and management of ICDBG funds and the delivery of services there under:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The NPHA Code of Conduct Policy Statement Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The applicable provisions contained in the Tenth Amended and Restated NPHA Procurement, Inventory, Disposition, and Housing Standards Policy, Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Seventh Amended and Restated NPHA Management Policy, Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Fifteenth Amended and Restated NPHA Personnel Policy Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>That for the purpose of administering ICDBG funding, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the Fifth Amended and Restated NPHA Financial Management and Internal Controls Policy, Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09 in relation to administration of ICDBG funds;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>That for the purpose of provision of rehabilitation services, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the Fourth Amended and Restated NPHA Housing Rehabilitation Standards and Policy adopted on January 19, 2011 by Board Resolution Number 11-1;</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="attachments|law|1.5" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.3.060</num>
        <heading>Grant Authorization</heading>
        <text>The Governor or his designee is hereby authorized to take such actions as deemed necessary to carry out the intent and purpose of this Resolution.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="attachments|law|1.6" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.4</num>
      <heading>Confirming Delegation of Authority to the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority to Apply for Bureau of Indian Affairs, Department of Interior Office of Indian Energy and Economic Development, Energy and Mineral Development Grant to Conduct a Solar Energy Feasibility Assessment</heading>
      <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.4.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as "CONFIRMING DELEGATION OF AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR BUREAU OF INDIAN AFFAIRS, DEPARTMENT OF INTERIOR OFFICE OF INDIAN ENERGY AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT, ENERGY AND MINERAL DEVELOPMENT GRANT TO CONDUCT A SOLAR ENERGY FEASIBILITY ASSESSMENT" ("Act").</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.4.020</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Agreement" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Governing Agreement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Council" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Pueblo" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.4.030</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this Act is to provide the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority, in coordination with the Pueblo, with authority to apply for grant funding to conduct a feasibility assessment for utilization in developing solar photovoltaic (PV) opportunities at the Pueblo.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.4.040</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Northern Pueblos Housing Authority ("NPHA") is the Tribally Designated Housing Authority ("TDHE") for the Pueblos of Tesuque, Picuris, and San Ildefonso, established by such Pueblos pursuant to § 4(18) and (21) of the Native American Housing and Self Determination Act of 1996, 25 U.S.C. §§ 4401 <em>et seq</em>. ("NAHASDA") for developing, operating, and managing housing units assisted by the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In addition to the environmental benefits, the Pueblo de San Ildefonso is interested in developing solar photovoltaic (PV) opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso to reduce electric utility costs and/or generate additional revenue to support Tribal programs; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Tribal Leadership understands that the appropriate step towards developing solar PV opportunities is to hire a qualified consultant to conduct a feasibility assessment to identify and evaluate possible projects; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Bureau of Indian Affairs (BIA), Department of the Interior Office of Indian Energy and Economic Development, Division of Energy and Mineral Development (DEMD), Energy and Mineral Development Program (EMDP) is</text>
          <text>soliciting proposals for the Grant Program ("Funding Program") to Assess, Evaluate, and Promote Development of Tribal Energy and Mineral Resources (BIA-000-0009-TEDC); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso is committed devoting appropriate resources and coordinating with NPHA and the consultant to facilitate successful completion of the feasibility assessment of solar PV project opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso is willing to consider developing viable solar PV projects, as determined by the completed feasibility assessment.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.4.050</num>
        <heading>Authorizations</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Council hereby authorizes NPHA to coordinate with the Pueblo de San Ildefonso staff to prepare and submit the application to the BIA DEMD in response to the Funding Program solicitation (BIA-000-0009-TEDC) on behalf of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For the purposes of the Funding Program, the Tribal Council hereby designates the NPHA Executive Director, Jon Paul Romero, as the Tribal Project Lead to oversee the project work, make authorized decisions during the course of the project, and be responsible for submitting quarterly and final progress reports, plus financial status reports, as required by the Funding Program; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Council hereby directs NPHA to hire a consultant to complete the feasibility assessment of solar PV opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso, in compliance with all applicable procurement requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso is committed devoting appropriate resources and coordinating with NPHA and the consultant to facilitate successful completion of the feasibility assessment of solar PV project opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Council hereby authorizes and directs the Governor or his designee to take such actions as deemed necessary to carry out the intent and purpose of this Resolution.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="attachments|law|1.5" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.5</num>
      <heading>Northern Pueblo Housing Authority Evaluation Act of 2021</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004"/>
      <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.5.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "NORTHERN PUEBLOS HOUSING AUTHORITY EVALUATION ACT OF 2021".</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.5.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of the NPHA Evaluation Act is to authorize and direct the completion of a comprehensive study, evaluation, and analysis of the current funding and management of the Northern Pueblo Housing Authority ("NPHA") including options for improving the operation and delivery of housing programs and services.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.5.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo currently contracts with the NPHA to operate, manage, and administer housing programs and services for the Pueblo, including receiving and expending federal grant funds on behalf of the Pueblo as a third-party contractor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>NPHA has experienced a number of detrimental events in the last several years including a high turnover rate in senior management positions and inadequate financial practices; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>NPHA has previously consisted of multiple northern Pueblos; however, NPHA currently</text>
          <text>consists of only two member Pueblos; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The administrative efficiencies of having multiple Pueblos sharing the costs of administrative functions has largely been lost by the departure of other member Pueblos from NPHA; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Council desires to study and evaluate the current funding and operations of the NPHA to determine the best method to provide housing programs and services to the citizens of the Pueblo, including whether to make any modifications to the structure, scope, and delivery of housing programs and services.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.5.040</num>
        <heading>NPHA Report of 2021</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Council hereby authorizes and directs the Governor, the Administrator, the Housing Committee or a designee, to conduct a written, comprehensive review, evaluation, and analysis of the current programs and services provided by NPHA and related issues ("NPHA Report of 2021").</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The NPHA Report of 2021 shall include the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The evaluation of the operation and delivery of housing programs and services provided to the Pueblo by NPHA;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>An evaluation of the management and staffing of NPHA including the status of the Board of Directors;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The types and amounts of funding received by NPHA on behalf of the Pueblo for housing services to the Pueblo;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The financial status of NPHA including current financial statements and practices, and the status of required financial audits;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The process to modify the current arrangement with NPHA or for dissolution of the corporation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>An evaluation of the funding requirements for the Pueblo to operate a minimum housing program including likely available grant funding and any unmet financial obligations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Any other observations and recommendations to assist the Council in evaluating the delivery of housing services by NPHA including methods to improve the delivery, type, and scope of services.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The NPHA Report of 2021 shall be completed and delivered to the Council within sixty (60) days of the effective date of the NPHA Evaluation Act.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.6</num>
      <heading>Housing Utility Infrastructure Authorization Act</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
      <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "HOUSING UTILITY INFRASTRUCTURE AUTHORIZATION ACT."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this Act is to: (1) Establish a process for members of the Pueblo to apply for home utility infrastructure services or to initiate a Utility Infrastructure Project; (2) ) Establish the standards, process, and requirements for approval of applications for home and homesite utility services; (3) Require public notice of any pending Utility Infrastructure Project with an opportunity for public comments prior to approval; and (4) Authorize the Governor to make final decisions on land use matters pursuant to this Act including applications for home and homesite utility infrastructure services and/or a Utility Infrastructure Project.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.030</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Act" means the Housing Utility Infrastructure Authorization Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Application" means a mandatory, written application completed by a member of the Pueblo to request or initiate a Utility Infrastructure Project.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"DNR" means the Department of Natural Resources of the Pueblo or a designee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>"IHS" means the U.S. Indian Health Service.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>"Project" means any and all home or homesite Utility Infrastructure Projects located on the Pueblo that is funded in whole or in part by or through a member of the Pueblo, a resident of the Pueblo, a private party, the Pueblo, and/or IHS or other governmental agency, as requested in a written Application and subject to the approval of the Governor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>"Pueblo" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso. "Pueblo" also means the lands over which the Pueblo has jurisdiction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>"Utility Infrastructure Project" means any and all projects to develop, repair, or improve water, wastewater, electric, gas, or internet services to a home or homesite.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.040</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The population of the Pueblo is increasing putting pressure on existing housing supplies and creating a need for new housing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Many members of the Pueblo have expressed the need for new housing and improvements to existing homes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo has some land parcels available that could be utilized for new housing purposes; however, these parcels often lack adequate utilities, ingress and egress, and other infrastructure needs; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo has issued land assignments to members of the Pueblo, in some cases decades ago, initially for farming purposes, and some members and their descendants have utilized or desire to utilize land assignments to develop or improve housing including manufactured and new construction homes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo desires to make land available for housing for members of the Pueblo in a fair and equal manner while taking into account the impacts new housing will likely have on neighboring land assignments, land use, the natural environment, culturally-sensitive areas, aesthetics, infrastructure, utilities, and overall policies established by the Pueblo; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The IHS has, from time to time, provided utility line construction and installation services to deliver certain utilities such as water and wastewater systems to members of the Pueblo, including to both existing homes and new homes, at a significant cost savings to the Pueblo and its members; however, the process to apply for IHS-funded services, and the process for the Pueblo to authorize IHS-funded construction services, has been haphazard and unclear, due in part to federal funding limitations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>As part of the <u>Aamodt</u> water rights litigation and settlement, the Pueblo is in the process of constructing a major water infrastructure project that will result in the availability of additional water resources to the Pueblo and its members including water for housing, farming, economic development, conservation, and other purposes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The amount of land available for housing purposes is limited, and any decisions regarding the development of new housing projects must be made in a thoughtful, systematic, and culturally-appropriate manner to protect against waste, duplication of services including utility infrastructure, and to reduce conflicts, while, at the same time, establishing fair and transparent rules and procedures for all members of the Pueblo to address their housing needs; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Council has determined that it is in the best interests of the Pueblo and its members to authorize and direct the Governor to address housing utility issues including the authority to approve and enter into agreements with the IHS to provide utility infrastructure services or to initiate a Utility Infrastructure Project to homes and homesites of members of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.050</num>
        <heading>Mandatory Approval Process for All Utility Infrastructure Projects</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All Utility Infrastructure Projects shall comply with the requirements of this Act. Any person or entity seeking approval of a Utility Infrastructure Project shall fila an Application with DNR. This Act shall not apply to minor repairs or normal; maintenance to home utility services.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.5" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.060</num>
        <heading>Process for Members to Apply for Approval of a Utility Infrastructure Project</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any member of the Pueblo shall be eligible to apply for approval of a Project by filing a written Application with the DNR, which shall be in addition to any application or process required by any other government. DNR may request additional information from an applicant which DNR determines is necessary for consideration and approval of the Project.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>It shall be the responsibility of the applicant to provide adequate information requested in the Application and to cooperate with reasonable requests from DNR for additional information that will assist in the consideration and approval of the Project.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.6" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.070</num>
        <heading>Responsibilities of the Department of Natural Resources</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><u>Application</u>. DNR shall develop a written Application for any member of the Pueblo to apply for approval of a Project.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><u>New Applications</u>. DNR shall keep a chronological list of all Applications for a Project received by the DNR. If an Application seeks assistance and funding from IHS for a Project, DNR shall cooperate with IHS to fulfill the requests for services contained in the Applications in the order the Application was received depending on the nature of the request and the availability of funding; Provided, that the Governor may alter the order of Projects in urgent or emergency situations to protect the health and safety of the citizens of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><u>Pending Applications and/or Requests for Assistance</u>. DNR shall keep a separate list of any known applications or requests for assistance previously filed with IHS and/or pending with IHS at the time of the approval of this Act. DNR shall apply this Act to the extent reasonably possible to all applications or requests for assistance pending at the time of the approval of this Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The DNR shall be authorized to promulgate a rule to establish design criteria for all Projects pursuant to notice and comment rule-making.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The DNR shall review each Application and shall consider the following factors:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The Applicant's land assignment or other indication of the Applicant's property</text>
            <text>interest in the home or homesite; Provided, that the burden of proof demonstrating a property interest shall be on the Applicant, and if DNR and/or the Governor cannot determine that a cognizable property interest exists, then DNR and/or Governor may decline to process the Application by providing a written explanation to the Applicant.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Whether the project is designated in an appropriate location including:</text>
            <para>
              <num>i.</num>
              <text>the nature of the surrounding area including the location of any nearby homes, buildings, and roads;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>ii.</num>
              <text>the amount of available land for the Project;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>iii.</num>
              <text>the length and duration of any disruption to the land;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>iv.</num>
              <text>the availability of all utilities including water, sewer, electricity, gas, and other necessary services, or an explanation of how all basic needs will be met;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>v.</num>
              <text>the impact of the Project on any surrounding or nearby land assignments and homes;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>vi.</num>
              <text>the impact of the Project on the natural environment and whether the least disruptive alternatives have been considered;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>vii.</num>
              <text>whether the project will change or alter the current use of the land;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>viii.</num>
              <text>whether the project will have an impact on future development in the area;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>ix.</num>
              <text>the availability of reasonable ingress and egress to the homesite;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>x.</num>
              <text>the type and condition of the structure to which the utilities will be provided, and whether the Project will improve existing utility service or provide new access to utility services;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Whether IHS has offered any comments or recommendations regarding the design, scope, and cost of the Project;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Whether the project will have any impact on any culturally significant site or have an impact on any religious practice;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Whether the Project will comply with the Pueblo's Tribal Historic Preservation Office requirements and laws including avoiding any disturbance to a culturally significant site;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Whether the Project complies with other applicable laws of the Pueblo.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text><u>Preliminary Review of the Application</u>. DNR shall consider the Project Application and the factors listed above, and any other factors that the DNR may reasonably consider to protect the health and safety of the Pueblo and its citizens. DNR shall recommend approval of the Project unless significant factors listed above exist to deny the Project, which DNR shall identify in writing to the Applicant. DNR shall provide the Applicant with an opportunity to address the factors identified that may be cause to deny the Project.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text><u>Public Notice and Comment</u>. Upon submission of a final Application for a Project, DNR shall provide General Public Notice of the Project for at least thirty (30) days, including Notice in at least one official monthly Pueblo bulletin or newsletter, in the Rio Grande Sun or similar newspaper of general circulation, and in at least two public locations on the Pueblo, and shall include DNR's preliminary recommendation regarding the Project. DNR shall provide Specific Notice of the Project to all known adjacent landowners or anyone with an adjacent property interest. DNR shall also provide the public and any adjacent interested party with at least thirty (30) days to provide comments and recommendations to DNR regarding the Project.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text><u>DNR Recommendation to the Governor</u>. After thorough consideration of the Application and public comments received regarding a Project, DNR shall make a final recommendation to the Governor regarding the approval or rejection of the Project and the reasons therefor. DNR shall provide a final recommendation on a Project within sixty (60) days of the close of the public comment period; provided that DNR may take up to an additional sixty (60) days as necessary by providing written notice of the need for additional time to the Applicant.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.7" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.080</num>
        <heading>Decision by the Governor</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Governor shall make a written decision on all Applications for a Project in a timely manner. A decision made by the Governor pursuant to this Act shall take precedence over any initial decision by IHS regarding a Project. The Governor may take any of the following actions regarding a Project:</text>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>if DNR recommends approval of the Project, the Governor may grant final approval of the Project;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ii.</num>
            <text>if DNR recommends approval of the Project, the Governor may deny the recommendation from DNR, and make a final decision to reject the Project;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iii.</num>
            <text>if DNR recommends denial of the Project, the Governor may make a final decision to reject the Project;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iv.</num>
            <text>if DNR recommends denial of the Project, the Governor may deny the recommendation from DNR and grant final approval of the Project; or,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>v.</num>
            <text>remand the Application to DNR with instructions for further investigation and study, which may include DNR requesting additional information from the Applicant or suggesting modifications to the Application and Project; Provided, that if the Applicant modifies the proposed Project, then DNR shall treat the modified Project as a new Application and shall begin the process anew.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upon approval of a Project by the Governor, the Governor shall be authorized to negotiate and execute agreements with the IHS as may be necessary to provide utility infrastructure services to homes and homesites.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>No Utility Infrastructure Project shall be constructed without the prior approval of the Governor in writing.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.8" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.090</num>
        <heading>Enforcement</heading>
        <text>The Governor or his designee shall be authorized to enforce this Act including by filing suit in the Courts of the Pueblo against any party who fails or refuses to comply with the requirements of this Act. The Court may award the costs of the enforcement of this Act against any party who has been found to have violated this Act.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.9" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.7</num>
      <heading>Northern Pueblos Housing Authority Orderly Dissolution Act</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-020"/>
      <annotation app="2021-09-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-020" eff="2021-09-17" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.7.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "NORTHERN PUEBLOS HOUSING AUTHORITY ORDERLY DISSOLUTION ACT."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-020"/>
          <annotation app="2021-09-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-020" eff="2021-09-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-09-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-020" eff="2021-09-17" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.7.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this Act is to authorize and direct an orderly dissolution of the NPHA in order to establish a Tribally Designated Housing Entity ("THDE") that serves the housing needs of the Pueblo.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-020"/>
          <annotation app="2021-09-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-020" eff="2021-09-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-09-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-020" eff="2021-09-17" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.7.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo contracts with the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA) to operate, manage, and administer housing programs and services for the Pueblo, including receiving and expending federal grant funds on behalf of the Pueblo as a third-party contractor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>NPHA has experienced many detrimental events in the last several years including a high turnover in senior management positions, non-compliance with the requirements of the Indian Housing Block Grant (IHBG), failure to implement key activities identified in the Pueblo's Indian Housing Plan (IHP); and poor performance resulting in the withdrawal of a kay partner Pueblo; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>NPHA has previously consisted on multiple northern Pueblos, however, NPHA currently consists of two Member Pueblos and the administrative and cost-sharing benefits of the organization have largely been lost by the departure of the other Member Pueblos from NPHA; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Council has authorized and reviewed the "NPHA Report of 2021" which found that NPHA cannot provide the Pueblo with assurances about if, how, or when the organization might regain the capacities of a full-service TDHE; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Council determines that the housing needs of the Pueblo can be best met through the establishment of a TDHE managed by the Pueblo; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Council wishes to implement an orderly transition out of NPHA into a fully operational TDHE managed by the Tribe that only serves the needs of Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-020"/>
          <annotation app="2021-09-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-020" eff="2021-09-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-09-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-020" eff="2021-09-17" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.8</num>
      <heading>Housing Authority Act</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
      <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "HOUSING AUTHORITY ACT ("Act")."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The Purpose of this Act is to establish a Housing Authority to address the Pueblo's housing needs including the planning, development, administration and maintenance of housing projects.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>There is a shortage of decent, safe and sanitary dwelling accommodations available at rents or prices that low-income citizens can afford; and that such shortage forces people to occupy unsanitary, unsafe and overcrowded dwelling accommodations or leave the Pueblo; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The establishment of a housing authority will aid in the provision of decent, safe and sanitary housing, will contribute to the overall economic welfare of the Pueblo, will provide employment opportunities for Pueblo members, and will establish desirable housing, neighborhoods, and communities on Pueblo Lands; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo has the authority to undertake the formation of a housing authority.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.040</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <text>For purposes of this Act, the term:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Act" means the Housing Authority Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Authority" or "Housing Authority" means the San Ildefonso Housing Authority.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Board" means the Board of Commissioners of the Authority.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>"Council" means the Council of San Ildefonso.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>"Court" means the Courts of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>"Homebuyer" means any person who has qualified for any of the Authority's homeownership programs and has executed a lease purchase agreement with OOHA for lease purchase of home.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>"Housing" means "affordable housing" as defined by section 4(2) of NAHASDA and other decent, safe and sanitary housing primarily for Tribal Members, including rental housing, residential housing, condominiums, buildings, land, leaseholds, equipment, facilities, and other real or personal property for necessary, convenient, or desirable appurtenances, for streets, sewers, water service, utilities, parks, site preparation or landscaping, and for administrative, community, health, recreational, welfare, or other purposes. The term "Housing" includes the planning and design of the housing, infrastructure, and improvements, the acquisition of real property or any interest therein, the demolition of existing structures, the construction, reconstruction, rehabilitation, alteration or repair of the housing, infrastructure, and improvements or other real property and all other work in connection therewith, and all other real and personal property and all tangible or intangible assets held or use in connection with Housing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>"HUD" means the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>"Low Income Family" means a family whose income does not exceed 80 percent of the median income for the area, as determined by the funding source providing assistance, and including exceptions provided by the funding source.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>"NAHASDA" means the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-Determination Act of 1996 and its implementing regulations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>"Obligation" means any note, bond, debenture, or other form of financial obligation issued by the Authority pursuant to this Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>"Obligee" means any holder of an obligation, a lessor demising property to the Authority to be used in connection with a Housing project, or HUD when it is a party to any contract with the Authority with respect to a Housing project.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>"Pueblo" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso, a federally-recognized Indian tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of the Interior or her designee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>"Pueblo Lands" means the Pueblo's land grant and all other lands subject to the jurisdiction of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.050</num>
        <heading>San Ildefonso Housing Authority</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Establishment. The Pueblo hereby establishes a public body to be known as the Housing Authority to carry out the purposes stated in section 1.5.b., below. The Authority is hereby designated to receive, on behalf of the Pueblo and on its own behalf, federal, state, or private financial assistance, including grants, for Housing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Purposes. The Authority shall be organized and operated for the following purposes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>To act as a recipient and receive block grant funds authorized under PL 104-330 and administer such funds in accordance with provisions of the Act, as authorized by the Council;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>To remedy unsafe and unsanitary housing conditions that are injurious to the public health, safety and morals;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>To Alleviate the acute shortage of decent, safe and sanitary dwellings for persons of low income;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>To Provide employment opportunities through the construction, reconstruction, improvement, extension, alterations or repair and operation of low-income dwellings;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>To Improve the quality of life in all areas serviced by the jurisdiction of the Pueblo;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>To Engage in activities that are directly or indirectly related to housing, including, but not limited to mortgage origination and servicing, housing development and management, and development and management of other housing-related services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>To Participate in entities formed to accomplish any of the above-described purposes including acting as a general partner of a limited partnership.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Management of the Authority. The day-to-day affairs of the Authority shall be managed by an Executive Director subject to oversight by the Board, which shall serve as the governing body of the Authority.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Agency. The Authority shall be an agency and instrumentality of the Pueblo and enjoy the same status and immunities of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.5" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.060</num>
        <heading>Board of Commissioners</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Membership. The Board shall be composed of five (5) commissioners.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Member Selection.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Appointments. The Governor shall nominate commissioners to serve on the Board subject to confirmation by the Council. Commissioners shall serve three-year staggered terms of office.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Qualifications of Commissioners.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Board members may be tribal members or non-tribal members; provided, that tribal members shall always constitute a majority of members of the Board.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>No person may be prohibited from serving as a member of the Board because that person is also a tenant or Homebuyer of Housing; provided, that <strong><em>anyone who is delinquent on housing payments due to the Authority shall be ineligible to serve on the Board.</em></strong></text>
            <text>A Board member may participate in all meetings concerning matters that affect all of the tenants or Homebuyers even though those matters may indirectly affect the Board member as well; however, no Board member, in their capacity as a member of the Board, may participate in or be present at any Board meeting concerning any matter involving the Board member's individual rights, obligations, or status as a tenant or Homebuyer, except that the Board member may participate in or be present at such meeting only in their capacity as a tenant or Homebuyer.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>"Board members shall not be convicted felons. Candidates for Board Member positions shall be subject to a background check."</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Term of office. Except as otherwise provided, the term of office of the members of the Board shall be three (3) years staggered. A vacancy on the Board shall be filled by a qualified person upon nomination of the Governor, subject to confirmation by the Council. A person selected to fill a vacancy shall serve for the length of the unexpired term. Unless a member of the Board has been removed as provided in section 1.6 (f), the Board member may continue to serve after the expiration of the term of office until his successor has been appointed by the Tribal Council or Governor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Officers. The Board shall select, by majority vote, from among its members, a Chair, a Vice Chair, a Secretary, and a Treasurer. A member of the Board may only hold one position. The Board shall prescribe the duties of the officers in the bylaws established by the Board.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Removal of members. The Governor may at any time remove any member of the Board with or without cause.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Compensation. The members of the Board may each receive from the Authority a stipend for their services except that the amount of the stipend may not to exceed $100.00 per meeting per month.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Quorum. Three (3) members of the Board, at least one (1) of which must be either the Chair or the Vice Chair, shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of business.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Meetings. The Board shall meet at regular intervals and other times as provided in the by- laws established by the Board.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.6" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-12-09" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-030" eff="2021-12-09" path="attachments|law|1.6|(c)|3." type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.070</num>
        <heading>Powers</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Perpetual Duration. The period of the Authority's duration shall be</text>
          <text>perpetual or until this Act is repealed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Powers. The Authority shall have the following powers:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The Authority is hereby designated to receive, on behalf of the Pueblo and on its own behalf, federal, state, or private financial assistance, including grants, for Housing.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Subject to the provisions of section 1.12, to sue and be sued in its name upon any contract, claim, or Obligation arising out of its activities under this Act.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>To adopt and use a seal.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>To enter into agreements, contracts, or other understandings with any person, organization, partnership, corporation, governmental agency, or other entity.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>To agree to any terms and conditions attached to the receipt of federal financial assistance for Housing.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>To lease real property from the Pueblo and others for periods as are authorized by federal or tribal law, and to hold and manage or to sublease the same.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>To borrow or lend money, to issue temporary or long-term evidence of indebtedness and to repay the same. The Obligation shall be issued and repaid in accordance with the provisions of section 1.8.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>To pledge the assets and receipts of the Authority as security for any Obligations; and to acquire, sell, lease, exchange, transfer, or assign personal property or interests therein.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>To purchase real property or any interests in real property or take the same by gift and to lease real property or any interests in real property to the extent provided by law.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>To undertake and carry out studies and analysis of Housing needs, to prepare Housing plans, to execute the same, to operate Housing projects or programs, and to provide for the construction, reconstruction, improvements, extension, alteration or repair of any Housing.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>With respect to any dwellings, accommodations, lands, buildings or facilities embraced within any Housing project (including individual cooperative or condominium units), to lease or rent, sell, enter into lease- purchase agreements or leases providing options to purchase; to establish and revise rents or monthly payments; to make rules and regulations as the Board may deem necessary and desirable to effectuate any power granted by this Act.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text>To finance the purchase of Housing by a qualified Tribal Member.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(13)</num>
            <text>To terminate any agreement when any tenant or Homebuyer has violated the terms of the agreement or has failed to meet any of its obligation thereunder, or when termination is otherwise authorized under the provisions of such agreement; and to bring legal action against the tenant or Homebuyer, including an action for eviction.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(14)</num>
            <text>To establish eligibility requirements and policies to ensure that Housing will be made available in accordance with funding requirements and this Act.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(15)</num>
            <text>To purchase insurance from any insurance company to insure any real or personal property or against any risk or hazards.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(16)</num>
            <text>To invest any funds that are not required for immediate disbursement.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(17)</num>
            <text>To establish and maintain bank accounts in the name of the Authority as may be necessary and convenient.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(18)</num>
            <text>To employ and terminate an executive director (subject to approval of the Council), and employ and terminate housing managers, and other officers and employees, permanent or temporary, as the Authority may require and to delegate to the executive director, housing managers, and other officers and employees any powers or duties as the Board shall deem proper.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(19)</num>
            <text>To take any further actions that are commonly engaged in by public bodies of this character as the Board may deem necessary and desirable to effectuate the purposes of the Authority.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(20)</num>
            <text>To join or cooperate with any other public housing agency operating under the laws of the state or another Indian tribe in the exercise, either jointly or otherwise, of any or all of the powers of the Authority and other public housing agency for the purpose of financing (including but not limited to the issuance of an Obligation and giving security therefore), planning, undertaking, owning, constructing, operating, or contracting with respect to Housing of the Authority or other public housing agency. For such purpose, the Authority may by resolution prescribe and authorize any other public housing agency to join or cooperate with the Authority to act on the Authority's behalf with respect to any or all powers, as the Authority's agent or otherwise, in the name of the Authority or the other public housing agency.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(21)</num>
            <text>To adopt bylaws consistent with this Act.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(22)</num>
            <text>To manage, on behalf of the Pueblo, the process by which a Member of the Pueblo may obtain Leases of and Leasehold Interests in Restricted Land or Trust Land subject to the jurisdiction of the Pueblo, and the process by which a Member of the Pueblo may Mortgage such Leasehold Interests. The Authority is hereby authorized to promulgate rules and regulations utilizing notice and comment rulemaking for the purpose of carrying out the duties prescribed by this subsection. . As used in this subsection, the terms "Lease," "Member," "Mortgage," "Restricted Land," and "Trust Land" have the definitions given to them in Section 15.3.1.010 of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Financial Assistance. The Authority shall do any and all things necessary or desirable to secure federal, state, and private financial aid or cooperation in the undertaking, construction, maintenance, or operation of the Authority or Housing.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.7" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.080</num>
        <heading>Obligations</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Issuance. The Authority may issue an Obligation for any of its purposes and may also issue refunding an Obligation for the purpose of paying or retiring an Obligation previously issued by it. The Authority may issue any type of Obligation, including an Obligation on which the principal and interest are payable:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Exclusively from the income and revenues of the Housing project financed with the proceeds of an Obligation, or with such income or revenues together with a grant from HUD or other federal agency in aid of the Housing project;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Exclusively from the income and revenues of certain designated Housing projects whether or not they were financed in whole or in part with the proceeds of an Obligation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>From its revenues generally. Any Obligation may be additionally secured by a pledge of any revenues of any Housing project or other property of the Authority.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>No Personal liability. The members of the Board or any person executing the Obligation on behalf of the Authority shall not be liable personally on the Obligation by reason of issuance thereof.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Separate obligations. The obligations of the Authority shall not be a debt of the Pueblo and the Obligation shall so state on its face.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Manner of issuance. The Obligation of the Authority shall be issued and sold only in the following manner:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The Board shall by resolution authorize any Obligation by the vote of a majority of the full Board and the Obligation may be issued in one or more series.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The Obligation shall bear such dates, mature at such times, bear interest at such rates, be in such denominations, be in such form, either coupon or registered, carry such conversion or registration privileges, have such rank or priority, be executed in such manner, be payable in such medium of payment and at such places, and be subject to such terms of redemption, with or without premium, as the resolution of the Board may provide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The Obligation may be sold at a public or private sale at not less than par value.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>If any Board member or other official, agent or employee of the Authority whose signature appears on any Obligation ceases to be a Board member or other official, agent or employee of the Authority before the delivery of the Obligation, then the signature shall nevertheless be valid and sufficient for all purposes, the same as if they had remained in office or employment until delivery.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Negotiable obligations. Any Obligation of the Authority shall be fully negotiable.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Terms and conditions of obligations. In connection with the issuance of an Obligation or incurring of an Obligation under leases and to secure the payment of the Obligation, the Authority, subject to the limitations in this Act, may:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Pledge all or any part of its revenues to which its right then exists or may thereafter come into existence.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Provide for the powers and duties of any Obligee and limit their liabilities, and provide the terms and condition on which the Obligee may enforce any covenants or rights securing or relating to the Obligation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Covenant against pledging all or any part of its revenues, or against mortgaging any or all of its real or personal property to which its title or right then exists or may thereafter come into existence, or permitting or suffering any lien on such revenues or property.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Covenant with respect to limitations on its right to sell, lease or otherwise dispose of any Housing project.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Covenant as to what other or additional debts or Obligation may be incurred by it.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Covenant as to the Obligation to be issued and as to the issuance of the Obligations in escrow or otherwise, and as to the use and disposition of the proceeds thereof.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Provide for the replacement of any lost, destroyed or mutilated document evidencing an Obligation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Covenant against extending the time for the payment of its Obligation or interest thereon.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>Redeem any Obligation and covenant for their redemption and provide the terms and conditions thereof.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>Covenant concerning the rents and fees to be charged in the Operation of a Housing project, the amount to be raised each year or other period of time by rents, fees and other revenues, and as to the use and disposition to be made thereof.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>Create or authorize the creation of special funds for moneys held for construction or operating costs, debt service, reserves or other purposes, and covenant as to the use and disposition of the moneys held in such funds.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text>Prescribe the procedure, if any, by which the terms of any contract with holders of an Obligation may be amended or abrogated, the proportion of outstanding Obligation the holders of which must consent thereto, and the manner in which such consent may be given.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(13)</num>
            <text>Covenant as to the use, maintenance and replacement of its real or personal property, the insurance to be carried thereon and the use and disposition of insurance moneys.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(14)</num>
            <text>Covenant as to the rights, liabilities, powers and duties arising upon the breach by it of any covenant, condition or Obligation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(15)</num>
            <text>Covenant and prescribe as to events of default and terms and conditions upon which any or all of its Obligation become or may be declared due before maturity, and as to the terms and conditions upon which such declaration and its consequences may be waived.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(16)</num>
            <text>Vest in any Obligation or any proportion of them the right to enforce the payment of the Obligation or any covenants securing or relating to the Obligation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(17)</num>
            <text>Exercise all or any part or combination of the powers granted in this section.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(18)</num>
            <text>Make covenants other than and in addition to the covenants expressly authorized in this section of like or different character.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(19)</num>
            <text>Make any covenants and do any acts and things necessary or convenient or desirable in order to secure its Obligation, or in the absolute discretion of the Authority, tending to make the Obligation more marketable although the covenants, acts or things are not enumerated in this section.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.8" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.090</num>
        <heading>Audits, Fiscal Accountability, and Reports</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Accounting System. The Authority shall establish and maintain a functioning accounting system that is operated in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Annual Audit. If required by law, the Authority shall have its financial statements audited annually by an independent auditor. The Authority shall provide to the Council a copy of its audited financial statements within ten days of its completion.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Housing Proposals and Programs. Before undertaking any Housing project or program whose projected cost is expected to exceed $250,000, the Authority shall submit a proposal to the Council for approval and appear before the Council to explain the advantages and disadvantages to the Pueblo of the proposal. The proposal must contain the following information:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>nature, scope, and projected cost of the project or program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>amount, type, and sources of financial assistance, including any financial contributions required from the Authority;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>evidence of financial condition (e.g., audited financial statements) of any third party providing financial assistance to the project or program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>evidence of experience of any third party in any state, federal, or tribal housing projects or programs, including any suspensions, debarments, or penalties imposed by any state, federal, or tribal agency;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>cost-benefit analysis of the proposed project or program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>schedule or timeline and budget for the project or program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>collateral or other security to be provided by the Authority;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>terms and conditions of any proposed contractual obligations of the Authority in connection with the project or program, including any potential legal consequences flowing from a breach of material terms and conditions by the Authority, and any potential for any third party to assume control or ownership of the project or program as a result of a breach by the Authority; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>financial benefits and other benefits of the project or program to the Authority, Pueblo community, and Tribal Members.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Debt Obligations. Thirty (30) days before issuing any Obligation, the Authority shall provide to the Council a description of the Obligation's purpose, amount, repayment schedule, required collateral, and anticipated source of repayment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Financial Reports. Each month, the Executive Director shall submit to the Council a summary report of the Authority's finances. Each quarter, the Executive Director shall submit to the Council the following quarterly financial reports concerning the Authority:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>budget variance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>statement of cash flows;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>income statement; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>balance sheet.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Fidelity bonds. The Board shall obtain adequate fidelity bond insurance for its officers, agents or employees who handle cash or who are authorized to sign checks or certify vouchers on behalf of the Authority.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Reports.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>For each fiscal year, the Board shall submit an annual performance report and other reports to HUD as required by federal law. The Authority shall submit to the Governor and the Council a copy of any report submitted to HUD.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>For each fiscal year, the Authority shall submit a written report to the Council showing:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>a summary of the Authority's activities;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>the financial condition of the Authority;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>the condition of all Housing under the Authority's management;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>the number of units and vacancies in any Housing project;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(E)</num>
              <text>any significant problems and accomplishments of the Authority;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(F)</num>
              <text>any plans for future Housing;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(G)</num>
              <text>the number of Tribal Members and non-tribal members living in any Housing project or program; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(H)</num>
              <text>any other information that the Board or the Council shall deem pertinent.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Indian Housing Plans. The Board shall, on behalf of the Pueblo, prepare and submit to HUD an Indian housing plan as required by federal law without the prior review of the housing plan by the Council; however, the Board shall submit a copy of the housing plan to the Council.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.9" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.100</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Local government cooperation agreements. The Authority may enter into an agreement, which shall provide for local government cooperation, with the governing body of any locality within which a Housing project will be situated.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Housing policies. The Authority shall prepare policies required by federal law or as needed to effectively and efficiently administer Housing. These policies shall be available for review by HUD, the Council, Tribal Administration and tribal members.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Conflicts of Interest.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>All federal laws governing conflict of interests within housing programs receiving federal financial assistance apply to the Authority and its Board members, officers, employees, and agents. The Board shall establish a conflict of interest policy that complies with federal law.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>In addition to the conflict of interest provisions under applicable federal law as stated in section 1.10 (c) (1), a Board member, officer, employee, and agent shall not, during their tenure and for one year thereafter:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>participate in any activity that competes with the Authority or deprives the Authority of business;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>allow business dealings on behalf of the Authority to be influenced (or appear to be influenced) by personal or family interests;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>accept or solicit gifts, loans, favors or other valuables from any person or entity for the privilege of doing business or proposing to do business with the Authority;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>accept or solicit bribes, payments, personal loans, kickbacks, special privileges or services from any person or entity, or give or offer any of these to any person or entity;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(E)</num>
              <text>engage in outside activities that interfere with their responsibilities to the Authority;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(F)</num>
              <text>use the Authority's name to perform any outside activities;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(G)</num>
              <text>solicit or distribute while at work any literature, pamphlets, or other materials that are not contrary to the views or purposes of the Authority;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(H)</num>
              <text>obtain a personal or financial interest or benefit from the Authority's activities. This prohibition shall apply to persons with whom a Board member, officer, employee, or agent has a business or immediate family relationship; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(I)</num>
              <text>engage in any other activity, including, but not limited to, discussions, meetings, and decision-making, in which Board member, officer, employee, or agent has a personal or private interest that interferes with or appears to interfere with their ability to perform their responsibilities fairly, ethically, and consistent with the Authority's best interests.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Every Board member, officer, employee, and agent shall disclose all actual and potential conflicts of interest to the Board, and unless allowed under federal or tribal law, remove themselves from participation in any discussion or action regarding the matter in which the Board member, officer, employee, or agent has an actual or potential conflict of interest.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any violation of section 1.10 c. constitutes misconduct for purposes of section 1.6(f).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Section 1.10 (c)(3). does not apply to the following circumstances:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>the acquisition of any interest in an Obligation issued in connection with any Housing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>the execution of agreements by banking institutions for the deposit or handling of funds in connection with Housing or to act as trustee under any trust indenture;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>utility services rates that are fixed or controlled by a governmental agency; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>members of the Board or employees of the Authority who acquire an interest in Housing as a tenant or homebuyer on the same basis as other tenants and homebuyers, so long as there is no conflict of interest under tribal law, the Board member or employee has made a public disclosure of the nature of the assistance to be provided and the specific basis for the selection of the Board member or employee, and a copy of the disclosure is provided to HUD before the assistance is provided.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Compliance with federal law. Each Housing project developed or operated under a contract providing for federal financial assistance, including block grants, shall comply with all requirements of the contract and applicable federal law and regulations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Operation of Housing. The Authority shall construct, operate, and use funds generated by its Housing activities to further the purpose of providing decent, safe, and sanitary Housing for Tribal Members.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Taxes.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>All other persons and entities doing business with the Authority, including construction contractors, are subject to applicable Pueblo taxes.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Exemption from execution or other judicial process. All personal and real property of the Authority shall be exempt from levy and sale by virtue of an execution, and no execution or other judicial process shall issue against the property nor shall any judgment against the Authority be a charge or lien upon the property. However, the provisions of this subsection (i) shall not limit the right of any Obligee to pursue any remedies for the enforcement of any pledge or the right of HUD or a funding source to pursue any remedies conferred upon it pursuant to the provisions of this Act, or the rights of the Authority or other party to bring eviction or foreclosure actions in accordance with section 1.7 b (13).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Exception to low-income requirement. For purposes of this Act, the Authority may provide Housing assistance or activities to individuals or families who are not low-income to the extent that such assistance or activities are not prohibited by applicable law or a funding source.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.10" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.110</num>
        <heading>Pueblo Corporation</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Pueblo agreements. For the purpose of aiding and cooperating in the planning, construction, or operation of any Housing, the Pueblo agrees that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>It shall not levy or impose any real or personal property taxes upon the Authority or any Housing assisted with federal funds.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>It shall provide tribal governmental services, including police and fire protection, roads, water, and sewage, to the Authority and Housing on the same basis that it provides those services to other residents of Pueblo Lands.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Insofar as it may lawfully do so, it shall grant deviations from any present or future tribal building code that are reasonable and necessary to promote economy and efficiency in the development and operation of Housing and at the same time safeguard health and safety of the Pueblo and its members.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>It shall do any and all things, within its lawful powers, necessary or convenient to aid and cooperate in the planning, undertaking, constructing, or operating of any Housing.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pueblo Courts.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The Authority shall utilize the Courts to enforce the provisions of any contract between the Authority and any Tenant or Homebuyer.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The Courts shall have jurisdiction to hear and determine any action for eviction of a Tenant or Homebuyer, or for breach of contract, or any foreclosure action against a borrower, or for any other matters arising out of this Act.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Effectiveness of provisions. The provisions of section 1.11(a) shall remain in effect with respect to any Housing for the following period, whichever is the longest:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>the Housing is owned by a public body or government agency;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>any contract between the Authority and any third party, for loans, guarantees, grants, or any financial contributions in connection with the Housing, remains in force and effect; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>any Obligation issued in connection with any Housing or any moneys due to a third party in connection with the Housing, remain unpaid. If, at any time, title to, or possession of, any Housing held by any public body or governmental agency, including HUD, transfers to a body or entity authorized by law to engage in the development or operation of Housing, the provisions of this section shall inure to the benefit of and be enforced by that body or governmental agency.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.11" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.120</num>
        <heading>Sovereign Immunity</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Immunities. The Authority, as an agency and instrumentality of the Pueblo, is entitled to all of the privileges and immunities of the Pueblo. The Authority, its Board, officers, employees, and agents while acting in their official capacities are immune from suit, and the assets and other property of the Authority are exempt from levy or execution, except as provided in this section 1.12.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Waiver of immunity. Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Authority is authorized to waive its sovereign immunity from suit for any particular contract, agreement, matter, or transaction that it may enter into to further the purposes of the Authority.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Procedure. Any waiver of immunity authorized by section 1.12(b) shall be in the form of a resolution duly adopted by the Board, which resolution shall not require the approval of the Council or the Secretary. The resolution shall</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>identify the party for whose benefit the waiver is granted,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>the transaction and the claims for which the waiver is granted,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>the property of the Authority that may be subject to execution to satisfy any judgment entered in the claim, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>the court in which suit against the Authority may be brought.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Authority assets. Any waiver of sovereign immunity by the Authority shall be limited to the assets and/or income of the Authority and the acts or omissions of the Authority, its Board, officers, employees or agents shall not create any liability, Obligation or indebtedness either of the Pueblo, or payable out of the assets, revenue or income of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>No Pueblo waiver. Any waiver of sovereign immunity of the Authority shall not be construed to waive any sovereign immunity of the Pueblo or any other agency or</text>
          <text>instrumentality of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.12" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.130</num>
        <heading>Amendments</heading>
        <text>This Act may be amended from time to time by the Council.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.13" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.140</num>
        <heading>Interpretation</heading>
        <text>The Council shall be the final decision-maker regarding the interpretation of this Act. Any questions relating to the interpretation of any provision of this Act shall be submitted to the Council for interpretation.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.14" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.150</num>
        <heading>Severability</heading>
        <text>If any provision of this Act is held invalid or application thereof to any person or circumstance is held invalid, then the invalidity does not affect other provisions or applications of the Act that can be given effect without the invalid provision or application, and to this end the provisions of this Act are severable.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.15" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.8.160</num>
        <heading>Effective Date</heading>
        <text>This Act and any amendments thereto shall take effect on the date enacted by the Council.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-026" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.16" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.9</num>
      <heading>Rural Community Assistance Corporation (RCAC) Loan Assumption Act</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027"/>
      <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.9.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "RURAL COMMUNITY ASSISTANCE CORPORATION (RCAC) LOAN ASSUMPTION ACT ("Act")."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.9.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso wishes to accept responsibility for RCAC Loan No. 6164-NPHA 01 due to the orderly dissolution of NPHA, the current borrower, by December 31, 2021. This Act authorizes the transfer of responsibility for the loan from NHPA to the San Ildefonso Housing Authority ("SIHA") subsequent to formation of SIHA and its designation as the Tribe's Tribally Designated Housing Entity.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.9.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Council is responsible for the health, safety, education and welfare of all community members; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On August 17, 2000, the Pueblo entered into a Joint Venture Agreement with Picuris, Taos, and Tesuque Pueblos that designated the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA) as the Tribally Designated Housing Entity (TDHE) for the four tribes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The two remaining members of the NPHA, the Pueblos of Tesuque and San Ildefonso, have determined that it is in each Pueblo's best interest to dissolve NPHA in accordance with Section 18 of the NPHA Joint Venture Agreement and distribute the assets and liabilities of NPHA to the member tribes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>in fulfillment of these terms, the Pueblo wishes to assume responsibility for RCAC Loan No. 6164-NPHA-01; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>RCAC requires the Pueblo to legally accept the loan as a condition of transferring responsibility from NPHA to the Pueblo de San Ildefonso; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>the Council has determined that the housing needs of the Pueblo can be best met through the of the San Ildefonso Housing Authority (SIHA) to serve as its Tribally Designated Housing Authority beginning on or about December 31, 2021.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.9.040</num>
        <heading>Assumption Responsibilities</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>SIHA is a new organization expected to be operational and designated as the Tribally Designated Housing Entity for the Pueblo by law on or about December 31, 2021. TDHE designation will constitute the initiation of operations, including establishment of its power to assume the RCAC loan on behalf of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In Section 1.7 b (6) of the San Ildefonso Housing Authority Act, the Authority is delegated the power to borrow money for the purpose of providing housing for tribal members.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>This Act authorizes the SIHA to assume responsibility for RCAC Loan No. 6164-NPHA- 01, which was used by NPHA to finance construction of the Deer Tail 1 housing development, at the earliest possible time after TDHE designation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo notes that on October 22, 2021, the Pueblo indicated its intention to assume the loan when it submitted a Governor-approved Indian Housing Plan (IHP) for FY 2022 to provide sufficient Indian Housing Block Grant (IHBG) funds to make full payment on this loan in 2022.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>By this Act, the Council directs the new SIHA Board of Commissioners to implement the program and budget of the 2022 IHP pertaining to the RCAC loan by executing a loan assumption agreement with RCAC and making full payment for the loan in 2022 using 2022 Indian Housing Block Grant funding programmed for this purpose.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>SIHA is hereby authorized to execute any and all documents required by RCAC relative to the assumption of RCAC Loan No. 6164-NPHA-01.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.9.050</num>
        <heading>Effective Date</heading>
        <text>This Act and any amendments thereto shall take effect on the date enacted by the Council.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-027" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.5" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.10</num>
      <heading>Tribally Designated Housing Entity Act of 2021</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028"/>
      <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.10.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "TRIBALLY DESIGNATED HOUSING ENTITY ACT OF 2021 ("Act")."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.10.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The Purpose of this Act is to designate the San Ildefonso Housing Authority as the Tribally Designated Housing Entity ("TDHE") for the Pueblo.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.10.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo has the authority to undertake the formation of a housing authority; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Council enacted a law to establish the San Ildefonso Housing Authority (SIHA); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Under the authority of the Native American Housing Assistance and Self Determination Act of 1996 (NAHASDA), Indian tribes may designate existing Indian Housing Authorities as a TDHE to provide and administer approved Indian housing activities.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.10.040</num>
        <heading>Designation of TDHE</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Council hereby designates the San Ildefonso Housing Authority as the Tribally Designated Housing Entity for the Pueblo effective January 1, 2022 in accordance with the Native American Housing Assistance and Self Determination Act of 1996.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As the TDHE, the San Ildefonso Housing Authority is authorized to develop and administer Indian Housing Plans on behalf of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028" eff="2021-11-29" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-11-29" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-028" eff="2021-11-29" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.11</num>
      <heading>Housing Improvement Program and Emergency Repair Program Authorization Act of 2022</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018"/>
      <annotation app="2022-10-24" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018" eff="2022-10-24" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.11.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "Housing Improvement Program and Emergency Repair Program Authorization Act of 2022" ("Act").</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018"/>
          <annotation app="2022-10-24" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018" eff="2022-10-24" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2022-10-24" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018" eff="2022-10-24" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.11.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this Act is to authorize the San Ildefonso Housing Authority ("SIHA") to operate housing programs and to administer appropriated funds for the Housing Improvement Program and the Emergency Repair Program for the People.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018"/>
          <annotation app="2022-10-24" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018" eff="2022-10-24" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2022-10-24" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018" eff="2022-10-24" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.11.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>the Pueblo has established SIHA to address the housing needs of the People including providing safe and affordable housing options; and,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>the Pueblo has received federal housing funds, including COVID-related grant funds, to assist the Pueblo in providing housing programs and services to the People; and,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>the US Department of Housing and Urban Development ("HUD") has made available Housing Improvement Program ("HIP") funds to eligible Indian tribes including the Pueblo; and,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>the Council finds it in the best interest of the Pueblo to authorize and direct the Housing Authority to administer a Housing Improvement Program and an Emergency Repair Program ("ERP") to provide critical housing services to the People.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018"/>
          <annotation app="2022-10-24" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018" eff="2022-10-24" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2022-10-24" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018" eff="2022-10-24" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.11.040</num>
        <heading>Authorization of Programs and Funds</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Council hereby authorizes and directs SIHA to establish and administer the Housing Improvement Program and the Emergency Repair Program to deliver needed housing services to the People.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>SIHA shall administer HIP and ERP in a fair and equitable manner including providing notice of the programs, the eligibility requirements for participation in the programs, an application process and 60-day open enrollment time period to apply for assistance, and a priority list of factors that SIHA will utilize to approve participation in the programs in recognition that the available funds are limited.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Council hereby authorizes up to $500,000 of available American Rescue Plan Act funds for use by SIHA for HIP and ERP services.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018"/>
          <annotation app="2022-10-24" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018" eff="2022-10-24" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2022-10-24" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-018" eff="2022-10-24" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2023-05-31" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-007" eff="2023-05-31" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.12</num>
      <heading>SIHA Lease Assignments Act of 2022</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023"/>
      <annotation app="2022-12-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023" eff="2022-12-14" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.12.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "SIHA LEASE ASSIGNMENTS ACT OF 2022" (the "Act").</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023"/>
          <annotation app="2022-12-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023" eff="2022-12-14" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2022-12-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023" eff="2022-12-14" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.12.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The Purpose of this Act is to authorize the Governor to execute a Quitclaim Deed, Assignment and Assumption, and Release document assigning the leasehold rights to sixteen properties which were formerly leased by the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA), to the San Ildefonso Housing Authority (SIHA).</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023"/>
          <annotation app="2022-12-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023" eff="2022-12-14" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2022-12-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023" eff="2022-12-14" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.12.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>NPHA has executed a Quitclaim Agreement assigning its interests in sixteen projects and leases to SIHA.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>SIHA wishes to assume all rights, obligations, and responsibilities therewith, including but not limited to all rights associated with these properties and has also executed the same Quitclaim Agreement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>By Resolution No. SI-R21-026, the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council created SIHA, and pursuant to SI-R21-028, the Tribal Council designated SIHA as the Pueblo's Tribally Designated Housing Entity (TDHE).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>SIHA must possess leasehold rights to properties named in the Quitclaim document to fulfill TDHE powers, duties and responsibilities granted by the Pueblos, specifically the management of leased properties and conveyance of paid off properties.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Council affirms its intention that leasehold rights formerly granted to NPHA be assigned to SIHA.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023"/>
          <annotation app="2022-12-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023" eff="2022-12-14" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2022-12-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023" eff="2022-12-14" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.12.040</num>
        <heading>Authorizations</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Council hereby authorizes the Governor to execute a Quitclaim Deed, Assignment and Assumption, and release the document assigning the leasehold rights to sixteen properties formerly leased from the Pueblo by the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA), to the San Ildefonso Housing Authority (SIHA).</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023"/>
          <annotation app="2022-12-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023" eff="2022-12-14" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2022-12-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R22-023" eff="2022-12-14" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.13</num>
      <heading>Authorizing the San Ildefonso Housing Authority to Apply for a 2023 Indian Community Development Block Grant on Behalf of the Pueblo, Evidence of Citizen Participation and Commitment of Tribal Funds for the Project</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014"/>
      <annotation app="2023-09-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014" eff="2023-09-08" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.13.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "AUTHORIZATION FOR THE SAN ILDEFONSO HOUSING AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR A 2023 INDIAN COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT BLOCK GRANT ON BEHALF OF THE PUEBLO" ("Act").</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014"/>
          <annotation app="2023-09-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014" eff="2023-09-08" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2023-09-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014" eff="2023-09-08" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.13.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this resolution is to authorize the San Ildefonso Housing Authority to apply for an Indian Community Development Block Grant for eligible families to be able to remain living on the reservation and to ensure the health, safety and well-being of San Ildefonso Tribal members is critical to the viability of the Pueblo community.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014"/>
          <annotation app="2023-09-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014" eff="2023-09-08" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2023-09-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014" eff="2023-09-08" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.13.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The San Ildefonso Council hereby finds that,</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>San Ildefonso Housing Authority ("SIHA") is the Tribally Designated Housing Entity ("TDHE") authorized to develop, rehabilitate and manage affordable housing activities for San Ildefonso and to participate in the design and implementation of comprehensive community and housing development activities.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo has determined that ICDBG Eligible families ability to purchase safe, sustainable and affordable housing throughout the reservation is essential to ensuring ICDBG Eligible families are able to remain living on the reservation and to ensure the health, safety and well-being of San Ildefonso Tribal members is critical to the viability of the Pueblo community.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo and SIHA have determined that the lack of financial and other assistance in the form of Homeownership Assistance is an impediment to ICDBG Eligible families in need of the ICDBG funding to acquire homes on the Pueblo to achieve homeownership.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Eligible Tribal Organizations are permitted to submit applications under the Indian Community Development Block Grant for Indian Tribes and Alaska Villages regulation 24 CFR 1003.5(b).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>SIHA is recognized by the Bureau of Indian Affairs as an eligible Tribal Organization as defined in Title I of the Indian Self Determination Education and Assistance Act, and as a Tribal Organization, the Pueblo Housing Authority is also therefore an eligible recipient under that Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo must meet certain threshold requirements in order to be deemed eligible for ICDBG funding whether the application is made directly by the Pueblo or on the Pueblo's behalf by an eligible tribal organization and the Pueblo intends to fully comply with the threshold requirements and of the 2023 ICDBG application process, including the citizen participation requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo, through activities carried by SIHA, sought and considered community input and posted the Citizen Participation Statement, Budget and Schedule for the Homeownership Assistance Project in advance of the 2023 Indian Community Development Block Grant Application in compliance with the Notice of Funding Availability governing the contents of the application for 2023 ICDBG funding expressed at 24 C.F.R. § 1003.604(a), and has considered comments received in preparing the application.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>SIHA has adopted a code of ethics policy and, in coordination with the Pueblo, prepared and disclosed to the public a statement of conflict of interests, specifically that no conflict of interest exists within the qualified applicants for the Homeownership Assistance project nor the criteria for the selection of the proposed beneficiaries.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>SIHA has adopted the Fiscal Management and Procurement and Contract Management policies that meets 2 CFR 200 requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014"/>
          <annotation app="2023-09-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014" eff="2023-09-08" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2023-09-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014" eff="2023-09-08" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.13.040</num>
        <heading>Authorizations</heading>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso hereby,</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>commits $2,640,000 in forgivable mortgages to eligible homebuyers to acquire buildable lots.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>commits $225,000 in tribal funds for the Project.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>certifies the Citizen Participation requirements were followed as expressed in 24 C.F.R. § 1003.604(a) and therefore has met those requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>authorizes San Ildefonso Housing Authority to take any and all actions necessary to effectuate the intent of the Project and the 2023 ICDBG application and process.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014"/>
          <annotation app="2023-09-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014" eff="2023-09-08" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2023-09-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-014" eff="2023-09-08" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.14</num>
      <heading>Authorizing the Governor to Enter into a Memorandum of Understanding with the Federal National Mortgage Association Also Known as Fannie Mae</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018"/>
      <annotation app="2023-12-22" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018" eff="2023-12-22" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.14.010</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><u>Legal Standards</u> shall mean the minimum requirements for legal standards and procedures established by the Tribe and acceptable in all respects to Fannie Mae relating to</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Conveyances of beneficial interests in Trust Land or Restricted Land to lenders as security for Mortgages to borrowers,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Creation and regulation of Assignment Rights and Assignment Mortgages, if the Tribe has a land assignment law,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Manufactured Housing, if applicable, to provide for foreclosure as real property and not a repossession of personal property</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Recording of Mortgages,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Mortgage foreclosure proceedings,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Evictions, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Transfer/resale restrictions.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><u>Tribe</u> shall mean the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Tribe, an Indian tribe, band, nation, village or other organization or community of Indians federally recognized as eligible for the services provided to Indian Tribes by the Secretary of the Interior because of its status as an Indian Tribe, according to standards published annually in the FEDERAL REGISTER pursuant to the Act of November 2, 1994 (108 Stat. 4791).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><u>Native American</u> shall mean a person who is a member of the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text><u>Designated Lender</u> shall mean one or more Fannie Mae-approved lenders that are approved as NACLI lenders and are selected by the Tribe to make loans to qualifying borrowers for the purchase of one- to four-family residences located on Trust Land or Restricted Land subject to such terms and conditions as may be established by the Designated Lender (in consultation with Fannie Mae) under NACLI. "Designated Lender" shall also include a successor to, or assign of, such entity.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text><u>Restricted Land</u> or land in restricted status shall mean land the title to which is owned by a tribe or an individual Native American and is subject to restrictions against alienation imposed by a federal statute. Generally, the restrictions are set forth in the patent or deed to the lands, except restricted lands held by the heirs of the allottees of the five Civilized Tribes in Oklahoma where such federal restrictions arise by virtue of limitations contained in the conveyance instrument pursuant to federal law or because of federal law directly imposing such limitations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text><u>Trust Land</u> or land in trust shall mean land the title to which is held in trust by the United States for an individual Native American or the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text><u>Eligible Borrower</u> shall be any one of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>An individual Native American,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The Indian Housing Authority affiliated with the Tribe ("IHA"),</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The "Tribally Designated Housing Entity" ("TDHE") affiliated with the Tribe, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The Tribe, provided, however, the Tribe may not act as Borrower where the subject of a Mortgage is a leasehold estate and there are no parties to the subject ground lease other than the Tribe and/or an IHA or Tribally designated entity.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text><u>Residential Ground Lease</u> is any lease of Restricted Land or Trust Land to an Eligible Borrower which is acceptable to Fannie Mae after review by its counsel. The "Residential Lease of Tribal-Owned Land" (which the Tribe represents is based on the lease attached to the "One-Stop Mortgage Center Initiative in Indian Country" issued in October 2000 by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development and the U.S. Department of the Treasury), attached hereto as <strong>Exhibit 1</strong>, as amended by the "Fannie Mae Rider to Residential Lease of Tribal Owned Land" (attached hereto as <strong>Exhibit 2</strong>) is a form of residential ground lease which is satisfactory to Fannie Mae under this agreement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text><u>Assignment</u> is any transfer of rights to occupy, control, build on, or otherwise exercise dominion over Restricted Land or Trust Land pursuant to a tribal Assignment law which has received the approval of the BIA.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018"/>
          <annotation app="2023-12-22" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018" eff="2023-12-22" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2023-12-22" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018" eff="2023-12-22" path="attachments|law/|1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.14.020</num>
        <heading>Support for Mortgage Lending</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Tribe shall consult with Fannie Mae to identify one or more Fannie Mae-approved lenders to act as "Designated Lenders."</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Tribe agrees to the establishment and maintenance of Legal Standards as long as Fannie Mae is the holder of any Mortgage originated pursuant to this MOU.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Tribe may satisfy the Legal Standards by adopting by ordinance, either</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The laws of the state where the mortgaged properties are located relating to such standards and procedures;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The "Model Tribal Lending Code" which is attached to the "One-Stop Mortgage Center Initiative in Indian Country" (issued in October 2000 by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development and the U.S. Department of the Treasury); or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Enacting conveyance, recordation, foreclosure and eviction laws which are specifically reviewed and approved by Fannie Mae's counsel, and by adopting appropriate ordinances governing Manufactured Housing and Land Assignments, as necessary.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Tribe shall ensure that each Eligible Borrower to whom a loan is made in connection with this MOU holds or possesses, at the time of such financing, either (i) a leasehold estate on Trust Land or Restricted Land pursuant to a Residential Ground Lease satisfactory to Fannie Mae that is entered into between the Tribe (or TDHE or IHA) and the Eligible Borrower (provided, however, the lessor and the lessee may not be the same entity; for example, if a TDHE or IHA is the lessor, that same TDHE or IHA may not be the lessee); (ii) a valid Assignment of Trust Land or Restricted Land pursuant to the Tribe's Land Assignment Law; or (iii) a sole beneficial interest in individual Trust Land or Restricted Land (as evidenced by a deed of allotment), and that such Borrower will acquire, construct or rehabilitate a dwelling on such property with the proceeds of the Mortgage or refinance an existing mortgage loan on such property.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Tribe shall ensure that each Eligible Borrower to whom a loan is made in connection with this MOU shall convey to the Designated Lender a security interest in the applicable real property interest described in Section 2 (d) above, by an appropriate instrument satisfactory to the Designated Lender, Fannie Mae and the Tribe, as security for a Mortgage made pursuant to NACLI.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Tribe, and the Eligible Borrower who applies for a Mortgage, will permit the Designated Lender or Fannie Mae, and their respective successors or assigns, to enter upon the Trust Land or Restricted Land, as applicable, for the purpose of carrying out such actions as the Designated Lender and Fannie Mae determine are necessary to evaluate the advisability of providing the Mortgage, to service the Mortgage after origination, and to otherwise carry out or enforce the terms of the Mortgage.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Tribe will, to the maximum extent possible, assist the Designated Lender and Fannie Mae, and their successors and assigns, in their efforts to facilitate the continued availability of conventional mortgage financing on the Trust Land or Restricted Land. Such assistance shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Assisting the Designated Lender and Fannie Mae in finding a qualified substitute purchaser of the mortgaged property if the initial borrower is unable to fulfill the obligations under the Mortgage;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Assisting the Designated Lender and Fannie Mae with the proper recordation of Mortgages and other legal instruments; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Supporting enforcement of foreclosures and evictions in connection with any default under a Mortgage in accordance with the Legal Standards.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The Tribe and Fannie Mae acknowledge and agree that Mortgages made pursuant to NACLI shall be recorded in (i) the appropriate Bureau of Indian Affairs Area Land Titles and Records Office, (ii) the county recorder's office in the state in which the mortgaged properties are located, and (iii) the following recording office established under Tribal law that are designated by the Tribe for the recording of Mortgages: <u>Realty Office of the Tribe</u>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>With respect to any leasehold estate or Assignment financed by a Mortgage, the Tribe, as lessor, agrees that it shall not attempt to cancel, modify, amend, terminate, surrender or forfeit any Residential Ground Lease, leasehold estate, or Assignment without the prior written consent of the Designated Lender and Fannie Mae, or their successors or assigns, as long as such Mortgage remains outstanding and the Designated Lender or Fannie Mae, or their successors or assigns, otherwise has an interest in such leasehold estate or Assignment.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018"/>
          <annotation app="2023-12-22" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018" eff="2023-12-22" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2023-12-22" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018" eff="2023-12-22" path="attachments|law/|2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.14.030</num>
        <heading>Fannie Mae Purchase of Mortgages</heading>
        <text>In consideration of the foregoing, Fannie Mae stands ready to purchase from the Designated Lender qualifying loans made to Eligible Borrowers secured by a Mortgage or Deed of Trust on Trust Land or Restricted Land, a leasehold interest thereon, or an Assignment thereof, to the extent permitted by applicable law.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018"/>
          <annotation app="2023-12-22" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018" eff="2023-12-22" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2023-12-22" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018" eff="2023-12-22" path="attachments|law/|3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.14.040</num>
        <heading>Consent to Jurisdiction</heading>
        <text>The Tribe and Fannie Mae hereby expressly consents to the jurisdiction of the <u>Pueblo de San Ildefonso Tribal Court and Supreme Court</u> with respect to any action brought to enforce the obligations owed by it to another party under this MOU.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018"/>
          <annotation app="2023-12-22" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018" eff="2023-12-22" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2023-12-22" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018" eff="2023-12-22" path="attachments|law/|4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.14.050</num>
        <heading>Termination</heading>
        <text>In the event that either party wishes to terminate the relationship established hereunder, this MOU shall terminate 30 days following receipt of written notice of such termination from either party. Provided, however, such termination shall not affect the Tribe's commitments under Sections 2(b), (f), (g), and (i) above, as long as Fannie Mae is the holder of any Mortgage originated pursuant to this MOU.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018"/>
          <annotation app="2023-12-22" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018" eff="2023-12-22" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2023-12-22" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018" eff="2023-12-22" path="attachments|law/|5" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.14.060</num>
        <heading>Counterparts</heading>
        <text>This MOU may be executed in multiple counterparts, each of which is deemed an original and all of which together constitute one and the same document.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018"/>
          <annotation app="2023-12-22" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018" eff="2023-12-22" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2023-12-22" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R23-018" eff="2023-12-22" path="attachments|law/|6" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.15</num>
      <heading>Authorizing the San Ildefonso Housing Authority Apply for a 2023 Indian Housing Block Grant on Behalf of the Pueblo</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001"/>
      <annotation app="2024-03-25" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001" eff="2024-03-25" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.15.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "AUTHORIZATION FOR THE SAN ILDEFONSO HOUSING AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR A 2023 INDIAN COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT BLOCK GRANT ON BEHALF OF THE PUEBLO" ("Act").</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001"/>
          <annotation app="2024-03-25" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001" eff="2024-03-25" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-03-25" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001" eff="2024-03-25" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.15.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this resolution is to authorize the San Ildefonso Housing Authority to apply for an Indian Housing Block Grant (IHBG) for construction of new homes on the reservation for IHBG eligible families.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001"/>
          <annotation app="2024-03-25" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001" eff="2024-03-25" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-03-25" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001" eff="2024-03-25" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.15.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The San Ildefonso Council hereby finds that,</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>San Ildefonso Housing Authority ("SIHA") is the Tribally Designated Housing Entity ("TDHE") authorized to develop, rehabilitate and manage affordable housing activities for San Ildefonso and to participate in the design and implementation of comprehensive community and housing development activities and administer its NAHASDA funding.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo and SIHA has determined there is a shortage of new homes for IHBG Eligible families which has created overcrowding and risk for homelessness and other health and safety issues for IHBG eligible families.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo and SIHA has determined new homes are essential to ensure San Ildefonso families are able to live on the reservation, thereby preserving its culture and traditions.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo and SIHA has determined the need for new construction of homes for IHBG eligible families cannot be met with existing sources of funding and therefore the IHBG Competitive Grant is essential to address substandard housing conditions on the reservation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo must meet certain threshold requirements in Section III.D., Threshold Eligibility Requirements. Similarly, there are eligibility requirements under Section III.E., Statutory and Regulatory Requirements Affecting Eligibility in order to be deemed eligible for IHBG funding whether the application is made directly by the Pueblo or on the Pueblo's behalf by its TDHE, the Pueblo and SIHA intends to fully comply with the threshold requirements and of the 2023 IHBG grant.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>SIHA has adopted a code of conduct policy and, in coordination with the Pueblo, prepared and disclosed to the public a statement of conflict of interests, specifically that no conflict of interest exists within the qualified applicants for the IHBG funding project nor the criteria for the selection of the proposed beneficiaries.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>SIHA has adopted and Fiscal Management and Procurement and Contract Management policies that meets 2 CFR 200 requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001"/>
          <annotation app="2024-03-25" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001" eff="2024-03-25" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-03-25" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001" eff="2024-03-25" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.15.040</num>
        <heading>Authorizations</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby,</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>authorizes the Governor and the San Ildefonso Housing Authority to apply for Fiscal Year 2023 IHBG funding on behalf of the Pueblo for new construction of homes for IHBG eligible families; and,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>authorizes the Governor and the San Ildefonso Housing Authority to take any and all actions necessary to effectuate the intent of the project and the 2023 IHBG application and process.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001"/>
          <annotation app="2024-03-25" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001" eff="2024-03-25" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-03-25" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-001" eff="2024-03-25" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.16</num>
      <heading>Authorizing the San Ildefonso Housing Authority to Apply for a 2024 Indian Community Development Block Grant for New Construction on Behalf of the Pueblo, Evidence of Citizen Participation and Commitment of Tribal Funds for the Project</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010"/>
      <annotation app="2024-07-15" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010" eff="2024-07-15" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.16.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "AUTHORIZATION FOR THE SAN ILDEFONSO HOUSING AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR A 2024 INDIAN COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT BLOCK GRANT ON BEHALF OF THE PUEBLO" ("Act").</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010"/>
          <annotation app="2024-07-15" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010" eff="2024-07-15" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-07-15" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010" eff="2024-07-15" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.16.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this resolution is to authorize the San Ildefonso Housing Authority to apply for an Indian Community Development Block Grant for eligible families to be able to remain living on the reservation and to ensure the health, safety and well-being of San Ildefonso Tribal members is critical to the viability of the Pueblo community.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010"/>
          <annotation app="2024-07-15" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010" eff="2024-07-15" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-07-15" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010" eff="2024-07-15" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.16.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The San Ildefonso Council hereby finds that,</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>San Ildefonso Housing Authority ("SIHA") is the Tribally Designated Housing Entity ("TDHE") authorized to develop, rehabilitate and manage affordable housing activities for San Ildefonso and to participate in the design and implementation of comprehensive community and housing development activities.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo and SIHA has determined that the lack of new sustainable homes impedes ICDBG eligible family's ability to remain living on the reservation and risks the health, safety and well-being of San Ildefonso Tribal members and therefore threatens the viability of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Eligible Tribal Organizations are permitted to submit applications under the Community Development Block Grant for Indian Tribes and Alaska Villages regulation 24 CFR 1003.5(b).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>SIHA is recognized by the Bureau of Indian Affairs as an eligible Tribal Organization as defined in Title I of the Indian Self Determination Education and Assistance Act, and as a Tribal Organization, the Pueblo Housing Authority is also therefore an eligible recipient under that Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>SIHA is recognized by the Bureau of Indian Affairs as an eligible Tribal Organization as defined in Title I of the Indian Self Determination Education and Assistance Act, and as a Tribal Organization, the Pueblo Housing Authority is also therefore an eligible recipient under that Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Only Community Based Development Organizations ("CBDO") may apply for ICDBG funding for New Construction and HUD has confirmed SIHA meets the definition of a CBDO under 24 C.F.R. 1003.204.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo must meet certain threshold requirements in order to be deemed eligible for ICDBG funding whether the application is made directly by the Pueblo or on the Pueblo's behalf by an eligible tribal organization and the Pueblo intends to fully comply with the threshold requirements and of the 2024 ICDBG application process, including the citizen participation requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo, through activities carried by SIHA, sought and considered community input and posted the Citizen Participation Statement, Budget and Schedule for the Homeownership Assistance Project in advance of the 2024 Indian Community Development Block Grant Application in compliance with the Notice of Funding Availability governing the contents of the application for 2024 ICDBG funding expressed at 24 C.F.R. § 1003.604(a), and has considered comments received in preparing the application</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>SIHA has adopted a code of ethics policy and, in coordination with the Pueblo, prepared and disclosed to the public a statement of conflict of interests, specifically that no conflict of interest exists within the qualified applicants for the Homeownership Assistance project nor the criteria for the selection of the proposed beneficiaries.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>SIHA has adopted the Fiscal Management and Procurement and Contract Management policies that meets 2 CFR 200 requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010"/>
          <annotation app="2024-07-15" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010" eff="2024-07-15" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-07-15" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010" eff="2024-07-15" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.16.040</num>
        <heading>Authorizations</heading>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso hereby,</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>commits $150,000 in forgivable mortgages to eligible homebuyers to acquire buildable lots.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>certifies the Citizen Participation requirements were followed as expressed in 24 C.F.R. § 1003.604(a) and therefore has met those requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>authorizes San Ildefonso Housing Authority to take any and all actions necessary to effectuate the intent of the Project and the 2024 ICDBG application and process.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010"/>
          <annotation app="2024-07-15" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010" eff="2024-07-15" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-07-15" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-010" eff="2024-07-15" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.17</num>
      <heading>Authorizing a Lease of Land to the San Ildefonso Housing Authority</heading>
      <annotation app="2025-04-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R25-002" eff="2025-04-14" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.17.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "SAN ILDEFONSO HOUSING AUTHORITY LAND LEASE AUTHORIZATION ACT" ("Act").</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2025-04-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R25-002" eff="2025-04-14" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2025-04-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R25-002" eff="2025-04-14" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.17.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this resolution is to authorize the Governor to enter into a land lease with the San Ildefonso Housing Authority for housing purpose.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2025-04-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R25-002" eff="2025-04-14" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2025-04-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R25-002" eff="2025-04-14" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.17.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The San Ildefonso Housing Authority ("SIHA") is the Tribally Designated Housing Entity for the Pueblo and develops and manages housing programs for the Pueblo's tribal members; and,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The SIHA is developing the Deer Tail Phase 2 Subdivision, consisting of forty (40) acres, more or less, which will provide lots for homes managed by SIHA and homes built by individual tribal members pursuant to a home mortgage; and,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The SIHA requires a lease to the Subdivision site to allow the SIHA to plan the subdivision, and to allow SIHA to sublease lots to families that qualify for a mortgage, and to enter into occupancy agreements with eligible tribal members for the lease-purchase or rental of a home.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2025-04-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R25-002" eff="2025-04-14" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2025-04-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R25-002" eff="2025-04-14" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.17.040</num>
        <heading>Authorization</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby authorizes the Governor of the Pueblo to negotiate and execute a Land Lease of forty (40) acres, more or less, of tribal trust lands to SIHA for housing purposes for the Deer Tail Phase 1 Subdivision and to submit the Lease to the Bureau of Indian Affairs for approval and recording.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2025-04-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R25-002" eff="2025-04-14" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2025-04-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R25-002" eff="2025-04-14" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>15.2</num>
    <heading>Home Ownership</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.2.1</num>
      <heading>Home Ownership and Property Transfer Clarification Act</heading>
      <section>
        <num>15.2.1.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as, "HOME OWNERSHIP AND PROPERTY TRANSFER CLARIFICATION ACT" ("Act").</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.2.1.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this Act is to clarify the process for members of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Pueblo") to become home owners, and to authorize the Governor to execute and deliver necessary documents to transfer and certify property interests within the Pueblo.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.2.1.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that the current process for members of the Pueblo to obtain ownership of a home through the Northern Pueblo Housing Authority ("NPHA") includes the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo identifies a vacant parcel of land;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo enters into a lease (the "NPHA Lease") with the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority, a federally recognized Tribally Designated Housing Entity ("NPHA") holding authorization from the Pueblos of Picuris, San Ildefonso and Tesuque tribes to obtain and manage Indian Housing Block Grant Program ("IHBG") funding from HUD covering the parcel of land on the Pueblo's reservation where the house is to be located (the "Subject Parcel"), recognizing that, at times, the NPHA lease may cover several parcels (a "master lease");</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Since the Subject Parcel is on the Pueblo's reservation, which is held in trust for the Pueblo by the US Government, the Subject Parcel is subject to federal law;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>As provided by federal law, the NPHA lease between the Pueblo and the NPHA can only have a maximum term of 50 years (25 year initial term and a second 25 year term); At the end of the 50 year term, title to the Subject Parcel reverts to the Pueblo;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Using IHBG funding or other funds, the NPHA builds a house on the Subject Parcel covered by the NPHA Lease;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Because the NPHA is the lessee under the NPHA Lease, the NPHA, as lessee, owns the house (because the house is attached to the land, if the NPHA Lease did not exist, the house would belong to the Pueblo);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>NPHA enters into an "Occupancy Agreement" with a member of the Pueblo (the "Acquiring Member") whereby the Acquiring Member: (1) obtains immediate right to occupy the house;  and, (2) if the Acquiring Member performs certain obligations over a specific term of time, the Acquiring Member will acquire the rights the NPHA has in the house;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Currently, when the Acquiring Member fully performs under the Occupancy Agreement, the NPHA transfers to the Acquiring Member all of the NPHA's right, title and interest in the house in the form of a quit claim deed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The problem with the current arrangement is that although the NPHA is transferring all of its rights as lessee under the NPHA Lease to the Acquiring Member, the NPHA Lease only gives the NPHA the right to occupy the parcel for a maximum of 50 years;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo wants the Acquiring Member to be able to occupy and treat the house 	as his or hers for a period of time longer than the term of the NPHA Lease;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>In order to correct the situation, the process needs to be changed to provide that, when the Acquiring Member fully performs under the Occupancy Agreement: (1) the NPHA gives up all rights it has in the parcel and the house (this would require a quit claim deed between the NPHA and the Pueblo for the Subject Parcel); and (2) the Pueblo would immediately give the Acquiring Member an assignment covering the house and the land on which it is located;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>There is also an issue as to whether the Pueblo's Governor had the legal authority from the Council to grant the right to occupy specific houses to previous Acquiring Members who had fully and completely performed under the Occupancy Agreement.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.2.1.040</num>
        <heading>Authorization and Ratification of the Governor's Authority to Execute Various Housing Documents</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Upon written notification to the Governor from the NPHA and the Pueblo's Realty Office that an Acquiring Member has fully performed under his or her Occupancy Agreement, the Governor shall take any and all steps to confirm that the Acquiring Member is in good standing with the Pueblo, the NPHA, and the Occupancy Agreement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the Governor determines that the Acquiring Member is in good standing with the Pueblo, the NPHA, and the Occupancy Agreement, the Governor shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Accept a quit claim deed for the house from the NPHA substantially in the form attached hereto, as may be revised from time to time in conjunction with the NPHA; and,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Execute and deliver to the Acquiring Member a Certificate of Land Assignment covering the subject parcel and house substantially in the form attached hereto, as may be revised from time to time in conjunction with the Pueblo's Realty Office and the NPHA.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the Governor does not receive confirmation that the Acquiring Member is in good standing with the Pueblo, the NPHA, and the Occupancy Agreement, the Governor shall so notify the Acquiring Member and the Acquiring Member may obtain review of the matter as provided by the Agreement and laws of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All previous transfers of houses to Acquiring Members (including by quit claim deed or assignment) executed by the current and any previous Governors since 2012 are hereby ratified and confirmed <em>ab initio</em> provided, that the Acquiring Member was in good standing with the Pueblo, the NPHA as confirmed in writing by the NPHA, and the Occupancy Agreement as of the date of transfer.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="" type="History"/>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>15.3</num>
    <heading>Leases, Mortgages, Foreclosures, and Evictions</heading>
    <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.3.1</num>
      <heading>Leasing and Mortgage Act of 2024 – General Provisions</heading>
      <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.1.010</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <text>As used in this Act, the term:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Act" means the Leasing and Mortgage Act of 2024.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Authority" means the San Ildefonso Housing Authority, and may also be</text>
          <text>abbreviated as "SIHA."</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Borrower" or "Mortgagor" means the Pueblo, its Tribally Designated Housing</text>
          <text>Entity (if applicable), or any Member who has the legal right and capacity to execute a Mortgage and who has executed a Mortgage on his or her Leasehold Interest, including any heir(s), successor(s), executor(s), administrator(s), or assign(s) of such Borrower.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>"Cure Period" means the time between an initial event of default and the time at</text>
          <text>which the Lender can commence a Mortgage Foreclosure Proceeding. The use of the term does not limit the Borrower's right to cure the default, which right extends to the date the Lender commences the Mortgage Foreclosure Proceeding.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>"Default" means the occurrence of a violation of any material term or condition of</text>
          <text>the Mortgage. A Borrower will be considered to be in default if a Mortgage payment is five (5) days past due or if he or she has violated any other material term or condition of the Mortgage.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>"Federal Agency" means any agency of the federal government that makes,</text>
          <text>guarantees, or insures mortgage loans, including but not limited to the Veteran's Administration ("VA"), the Department of Housing and Urban Development ("HUD"), the Federal Home Administration ("FHA"), and the Department of Agriculture ("USDA").</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>"Forbearance Relief" means an action that results in the Lender or the federal, state,</text>
          <text>or tribal government refraining from pursuing Mortgage Foreclosure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>"Governor" means the Governor of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>"Lease" means the residential ground lease or other agreement for use of Trust Land or Restricted Land on which a Mortgage has been or may be given. A Lease shall</text>
          <text>include a sublease of a Lease.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>"Leasehold Interest" means the Borrower's right, title, and interest under a Lease from the Pueblo, as Lessor, and may include improvements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>"Leasehold Tax" means any tax that may be assessed by the Pueblo against a Lessee for the use of land subject to a Leasehold Interest.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>"Lender or Mortgagee" means any mortgage lender or any successors or assigns of any such lender, and includes any subsequent holder, whether by assignment, succession, or otherwise, of the original Lender's or Mortgagee's right, title, or interest in and to the Mortgage.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>"Lessee" means a person who has acquired a legal right of possession of tribal Trust or Restricted Lands by a Lease.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>"Lessor" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>"Manufactured Home" means a structure manufactured in compliance with the federal Mobile Home Construction and Safety Standards Act of 1974 [42 U.S.C. Section 5402(b)] and the regulations thereunder [24 CFR Section 3280.2(a)(16], as that statute and that regulation may from time to time be amended.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>"Member" means an enrolled member of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>"Mortgage" means the leasehold mortgage given to secure a mortgage loan or other loan made by a Lender to a Borrower.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text>"Mortgage Foreclosure Proceeding" means a proceeding in the Trial Court to: 1) foreclose on the Leasehold Interest or other interests of the Borrower, and/or 2) assign such interest of the Borrower to the Lender or other person or entity.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(s)</num>
          <text>"Nuisance" means maintenance on the mortgaged property of a condition that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Unreasonably threatens the health or safety of a resident of the community, the mortgaged property, or neighboring land users; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Unreasonably and substantially interferes with the ability of neighboring real property users to enjoy the reasonable use and occupancy of their property.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(t)</num>
          <text>"Order of Repossession" means an order of the Trial Court that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Restores the Lessor or Lender to possession of Trust Land or Restricted Land; and/or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Evicts a Borrower or other occupant from such property.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(u)</num>
          <text>"Pueblo" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(v)</num>
          <text>"Redemption" means the right of the Borrower or other person with an interest in property subject to a Mortgage pursuant to this Act to regain possession of the property from the purchaser after judicial sale resulting from foreclosure upon payment or performance of other conditions prescribed by this Act and the Mortgage documents.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(w)</num>
          <text>"Residential Unit" means a building constructed or used for residential purposes, including a manufactured home (a) which is affixed or to be affixed to a permanent foundation in accordance with lender guidelines for such affixation; and (b) as to which a duly completed Affidavit of Title has been recorded under New Mexico law or the law of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(x)</num>
          <text>"Restricted Land" means any land within the jurisdiction of the Pueblo that is subject to restrictions against alienation imposed by federal treaty, statute, Executive Order, or the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(y)</num>
          <text>"Secretary," unless otherwise indicated, means the Secretary of the United States Department of the Interior or a duly designated representative.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(z)</num>
          <text>"Subordinate Lienholder" means the holder of any lien, including a mortgage perfected subsequent to the recording of a Mortgage under this Act, provided, however, such definition shall not include the Pueblo with respect to a claim for a tribal tax on the Mortgaged property, where applicable.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(aa)</num>
          <text>"Trial Court" means the Trial Court of the San Ildefonso Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(bb)</num>
          <text>"Council" means the Council of the San Ildefonso Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(cc)</num>
          <text>"Trust Land" means any land within the jurisdiction of the Pueblo, title to which is held by the United States for the benefit of the Pueblo or an individual Member of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(dd)</num>
          <text>"Unlawful Detainer Action" means a suit brought before the Trial Court to terminate a Borrower's interest in Trust Land or Restricted Land and/or to evict any person from occupancy of such property.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ee)</num>
          <text>"Waste" means spoliation or destruction of land, buildings, landscaping, trees, or other improvements on the mortgaged property which results in or is likely to result in substantial injury to such property.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.1|15.3.1.010" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.1.020</num>
        <heading>Applicability</heading>
        <text>Except as otherwise specifically stated, this Act shall apply to any and all Mortgages, leasehold Mortgages, and agreements to secure an interest in all Residential Units, housing, dwellings, or accommodations for human occupation or residence, or other buildings on Trust or Restricted Land and supersedes and replaces all other codes and ordinances previously adopted by the Pueblo specifically relating to residential Mortgages. In addition, the section on eviction contained herein may be applied against any person or entity occupying Trust or Restricted lands without right.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.1|15.3.1.020" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.1.30</num>
        <heading>Purpose and Interpretation</heading>
        <text>The Trial Court shall interpret and construe this Act to assist Members, and others with the consent of SIHA, in obtaining Mortgage financing for the construction or purchase of residences, Residential Units, or other buildings on certain Trust Land or Restricted Land within the jurisdiction of the Pueblo, by prescribing procedures for recordation, priority, and foreclosure and evictions in connection with Mortgages given to secure loans made by or through any Lenders.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.1|15.3.1.30" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.1.040</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction</heading>
        <text>The Trial Court shall exercise jurisdiction over all matters arising under this Act and any persons or entities acting pursuant to this Act.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.1|15.3.1.040" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.1.050</num>
        <heading>Conflict with Mortgage Documents</heading>
        <text>If any provision in the Mortgage or other loan documents is determined to conflict with this Act, then this Act shall control.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.1|15.3.1.050" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.1.060</num>
        <heading>Conflict with Other Laws</heading>
        <text>If this Act is determined to be in conflict with any other law of general application adopted by the Pueblo, this Act shall control.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.1|15.3.1.060" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.1.070</num>
        <heading>Mortgage of Leasehold Interests Prohibited Without Lease</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding any provision to the contrary contained in this Act or in any Mortgage document, no Borrower may mortgage a Leasehold Interest without first:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Obtaining a valid Lease for such property in the manner and form prescribed by the Authority; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Obtaining the prior written consent of the Authority to mortgage the Leasehold Interest.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The SIHA's residential lease form may allow a Lessee to mortgage the leasehold for the purchase, construction, rehabilitation, or refinancing for residential purposes without further SIHA consent .</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any Mortgage given in violation of this Section shall be void and of no effect.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.1|15.3.1.070" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.1.080</num>
        <heading>Merger of Estates</heading>
        <text>There shall be no merger of estates by reason of the execution of a Lease or a Mortgage or the assignment or assumption of the same, including an assignment effected by the approval of the Authority or by operation of law, except as such may arise upon satisfaction of the Mortgage.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.1|15.3.1.080" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.1.090</num>
        <heading>Alternative Remedies</heading>
        <text>If the persons or property concerned in an action arising under this Act are subject to the jurisdiction of the courts of the United States, the remedies and procedures enumerated in this Act are in the alternative to the remedies and procedures provided by the United States.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.1|15.3.1.090" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.1.100</num>
        <heading>Recording of Leases and Mortgages</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>As used in this Section:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>"Bureau of Indian Affairs Regional Land, Titles, and Records Office" means that office or any successor agency, office, or instrumentality of the United States performing substantially the same function.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>"Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Office" means that office or any successor agency, office, or instrumentality of the Pueblo performing substantially the same function.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>"Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Officer" means that officer or any successor officer, agent, or employee of the Pueblo performing substantially the same duties and functions.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The appropriate offices for recording Leases and Mortgages are the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Office and the Bureau of Indian Affairs Regional Land, Titles, and Records Office. The Pueblo recognizes that a Lender may additionally require that Leases and Mortgages be recorded in a state and/or county land records office, however, such recording is for notice and convenience purposes only and is not I intended nor shall be deemed to grant jurisdiction over the Lease, Mortgage, or underlying property to the state or county.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The process for recording documents at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Office is as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Officer shall endorse upon any Lease and/or Mortgage or other security instrument received for recording the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>The date and time of receipt of the Lease and/or Mortgage or other security instrument;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>The filing number, to be assigned by the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Officer, which shall be a unique number for each Lease and/or Mortgage or other security instrument received; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>The name of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Officer receiving the Lease and/or Mortgage or other security instrument.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Upon completion of the above endorsements, the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Officer shall make true and correct copies of the Lease and/or Mortgage or other security instrument and shall certify each copy in substantially the following format:</text>
          </para>
          <text>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO ) ss.</text>
          <text>I certify that this is a true and correct copy of a document received for recording this date.</text>
          <text>Given under my hand and seal this day of , 20 .</text>
          <text>(SEAL) ______________________________</text>
          <text>Signature</text>
          <text>______________________________</text>
          <text>Title</text>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Officer shall maintain such copies in the records of the recording system and shall return the original Lease and/or Mortgage or other security instrument to the person or entity that presented the same for recording.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Officer shall also maintain a log of each Lease and/or Mortgage or other security instrument recorded in which log shall be entered the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>The name(s) of the Borrower(s) of each Mortgage or Lessor of each Lease and/or Mortgage, identified as such;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>The name(s) of the Lender(s) of each Mortgage or Lessee of each Lease, identified as such;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>The name(s) of the parties and their designation in any other security instrument;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>The date and time of receipt;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(E)</num>
              <text>The filing number assigned by the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Officer; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(F)</num>
              <text>The name of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Officer receiving any Lease, Mortgage, or other security instrument.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Certified copies of Leases, Mortgages, and other documents and the log maintained by the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Officer shall be made available for public inspection and copying. The Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Office is hereby authorized to impose reasonable fees on the copying and printing of records.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.1|15.3.1.100" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.1.110</num>
        <heading>Priority</heading>
        <text>All Mortgages recorded in accordance with the recording procedures set forth in this Actshall have priority over any lien not perfected at the time of such recording and any subsequent lien or claim except a lien or claim arising from a tribal Leasehold tax assessed after the recording of the Mortgage.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If a Lessee fails to pay a tribal Leasehold tax, the Lessor shall copy Mortgagees of record on any notice of failure to pay and said Mortgagees may pay the tribal Leasehold tax.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.1|15.3.1.110" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.1.120</num>
        <heading>Assignment</heading>
        <text>Unless otherwise prohibited in the mortgage documents or under applicable law, Borrower may assign any mortgaged property at any time prior to commencement of foreclosure proceedings; provided that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The successor Borrower is a Member of the Pueblo, a Pueblo instrumentality or entity, or a Federal Agency; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Borrower receives all required consents in writing from the SIHA, Lender, and/or applicable Federal Agency, if any.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>SIHA's residential lease form may allow the Borrower to assign mortgaged property to persons/entities in (a) above without further SIHA consent. SIHA consent is required where assignment is to any other person or entity not listed in (a) above.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.1|15.3.1.120" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.1.130</num>
        <heading>Limited Waiver of Sovereign Immunity</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo hereby authorizes a limited waiver of sovereign immunity from suit that SIHA may enjoy with respect to any and all controversies or claims arising out of or related to the obligations of SIHA under a Lease or any Mortgage document or instrument to which SIHA may be a party pursuant to a Mortgage assumption.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In connection with such waiver, the Pueblo hereby authorizes SIHA to</text>
          <text>consent to personal jurisdiction exclusively in the courts of the Pueblo with respect to any action to enforce any obligations owed by it to any other party, including a Federal Agency, or to enforce any other party's rights and/or remedies under such Lease(s) or Mortgage documents.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The authority provided herein is not intended nor shall it be construed to waive the immunity of the Pueblo or of SIHA for any other purpose or with respect to any other claim or other matter not specifically mentioned in this Section, and is not intended to, nor shall it, extend to the benefit of any person other than the parties to such agreements or their successors or assigns.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>To the extent necessary, the Office of Governor may delegate its authority under the Grant Authorization Act to grant a limited waiver of the Pueblo's sovereign immunity to SIHA for the limited purpose of applying for and receiving grant funds related to the operations of SIHA.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.1|15.3.1.130" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.3.2</num>
      <heading>Lease and Mortgage Modernization Act of 2024 – Foreclosure</heading>
      <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.2.010</num>
        <heading>Notice of Default Required</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In the event that a Borrower defaults in performance under a Mortgage, the Lender shall provide a written Notice of Default prior to enforcing the terms and conditions of the Mortgage and prior to availing itself of the remedies under this Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All Notices of Default on a Mortgage shall be properly served by Lender on Borrower and all Subordinate Lienholders.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.2|15.3.2.010" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.2.020</num>
        <heading>Actions Upon Default</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A Borrower shall be considered to be in default when they are in violation of any material term or condition of the Mortgage.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When a Borrower is at least five (5) days past due on a payment owed under Mortgage, or the Lender has received actual notice that the Borrower is in violation of any other material term or condition of the Mortgage, and before any foreclosure action or activity is initiated, the Lender shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Provide written notice to the Borrower specifying the default and outlining curative actions that may be taken. The notice must include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>A statement that, if the Mortgage remains past due on monthly installment payments or the Borrower fails to cure any other material default within sixty (60) days from receipt of the notice, the Lender may accelerate the amounts due under the Mortgage, requiring payment of the entire loan;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>A statement of the qualifications for Forbearance Relief from the Lender, if any, and that Forbearance Relief may be available from the federal government, along with the names and addresses of government officials to whom further communication may be addressed for said Forbearance Relief, if applicable;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Make reasonable efforts to arrange a face-to-face interview with the Borrower, including at least one in-person visit to the mortgaged property to meet with the Borrower; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Document that it has made at least one phone call to the Borrower (or to a phone designated by the Borrower as able to receive and relay messages to the Borrower) for the purpose of arranging a face-to-face meeting.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>If an attempt to reach a Borrower by phone is not successful, then Lender shall send a letter via certified mail, return receipt requested, to Borrower's last known address, with a copy to the property, seeking to make arrangements for a face-to-face meeting.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>When a Borrower remains in default for at least sixty (60) days from the receipt of written notice of such default by Borrower and at least ten (10) days before initiating a foreclosure action, the Lender shall, in writing sent by certified mail, return receipt requested, with a copy posted prominently on the Residential Unit or other structure on the mortgaged property, with a copy provided to the SIHA, advise the Borrower:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>If the lender intends to report the information to credit reporting agencies, that information regarding the loan and default and/or delinquency shall be reported to credit reporting agencies;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Of the existence and availability of homeownership counseling opportunities or programs offered by the Lender, if any;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Of any available assistance regarding the Mortgage or default thereon;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Of the Lender's right to seek Foreclosure; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Of the Lessor's Right of First Refusal pursuant to Section 15.3.2.050 of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.2|15.3.2.020" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.2.030</num>
        <heading>Notice to the Pueblo</heading>
        <text>The Lender shall serve notice, by certified mail with return receipt requested, on the Office of the Governor and the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Office contemporaneously with the notice required in Section 15.3.2.020 (c ) above to be served on the Borrower.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.2|15.3.2.030" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.2.040</num>
        <heading>Cure of Default</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Borrower or any Subordinate Lienholder may cure the default(s) at any time before the entry of a judgment of foreclosure by payment of any arrearages up to the date of payment along with any interest and any reasonable and normal late fees.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Under no circumstances shall the amount required to be tendered include any amounts due pursuant to an acceleration clause.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any Subordinate Lienholder who has cured a default may thereafter include in its lien the amount of all payments made by such Subordinate Lienholder to cure such default(s), plus interest on such amounts at the rate stated in the promissory note secured by the subordinate lien.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.2|15.3.2.040" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.2.050</num>
        <heading>Right of First Refusal</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In the event of default by the Borrower on any Mortgage or other loan agreement for which a Lease is pledged as security, the Lessor shall have the Right of First Refusal to acquire the Borrower's interest in the premises, subject to all valid liens and encumbrances, upon:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Payment of all sums then in arrears and either payment of the balance of the loan or assumption of the Mortgage.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Right of First Refusal may be exercised at any time after the Lessor receives notice from the Lender of the Borrower's default in writing, by certified mail with return receipt requested, up to the date the Lender commences a Mortgage Foreclosure Proceeding. The Notice of the Lessor's intent to exercise its Right of First Refusal shall be provided in writing from the Lessor to Lender, with a copy to the Borrower and, all Subordinate Lienholders.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding subsection (b) of this Section, even upon the Lessor's exercising of the Right of First Refusal, the Borrower may cure the default at any time up to the date the Lender commences a Mortgage Foreclosure Proceeding.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The estate acquired by the Lessor through exercise of its Right of First Refusal shall not merge with any other estate or title held by the Lessor as long as the Lease is mortgaged or otherwise pledged as security for any loan.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Under no circumstances shall the Lessor exercise its Right of First Refusal unless the Borrower has first been advised of Forbearance Relief that may be available, if any, and the Lender has found the Borrower to be ineligible.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.2|15.3.2.050" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.2.060</num>
        <heading>Mortgage Foreclosure Proceedings</heading>
        <text>Upon expiration of the cure period for a default under a Mortgage, as identified in the Mortgage documents or otherwise provided in this Act, if there is a failure to cure, and the Lender has complied with the provisions set forth in this Act, the Lender may commence a Mortgage Foreclosure Proceeding in the Trial Court in the following manner:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Lender shall file a verified complaint:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Invoking the jurisdiction of the Trial Court through citation to proper authorities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Naming as defendant(s) the Borrower and each record owner claiming through the Borrower subsequent to the recording of the Mortgage, including each Subordinate Lienholder;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Describing the property subject to the Mortgage;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Stating the facts concerning:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>The execution of any Lease and/or the Mortgage;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>The recording of the Mortgage;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>The alleged default(s) of the Borrower(s); and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>Any other facts necessary to support a cause of action for Mortgage Foreclosure.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Including an allegation that all relevant requirements and conditions prescribed by federal and tribal law, and by the promissory note, security instrument, and the Lease, if any, have been complied with by the Lender;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Appending as exhibits true and correct copies of each promissory note, Lease, if any, Mortgage, and if applicable, assignment thereof relating to such mortgaged property; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Otherwise satisfying the pleading requirements of the Trial Court.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Lender shall obtain and serve upon each defendant a summons, along with a copy of the complaint, in the manner prescribed by law according to the Civil Procedures Code.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Lender shall additionally serve a copy of the summons and complaint upon the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Realty Office and the Office of the Governor by means capable of verification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Except as otherwise provided by Federal Agency loan guarantee requirements, in no event shall Lender file a claim for a deficiency judgment.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.2|15.3.2.060" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.2.070</num>
        <heading>Continuances</heading>
        <text>No continuances shall be granted in cases to which the Lender or a Federal Agency are a party, except for good cause shown and:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>By agreement of all parties with the consent of the Trial Court; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At the sole discretion of the Trial Court.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.2|15.3.2.070" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.2.080</num>
        <heading>Power of the Trial Court</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Trial Court shall enter judgment in favor of a Lender if all of the following requirements are met:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A Notice of Default has been properly provided to all persons or entities as required by this Act;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The Lessor's Right of First Refusal has not been exercised;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The default has not been cured within the allowable period as provided in the Mortgage documents or in this Act; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The Trial Court finds that the Lender has proven its claim by a preponderance of the evidence.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A judgment for the Lender in a Mortgage Foreclosure Proceeding shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Foreclose the Borrower's interest in the mortgaged property, and each other defendant named in the complaint upon whom proper and timely service was made, including each Subordinate Lienholder; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Assign the Leasehold Interest in the mortgaged property to the Lender or any purchaser of the Leasehold Interest at a foreclosure sale, subject to the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>The Borrower's right of redemption, if applicable;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>Limitations as to who may become an assignee of a Leasehold Interest as stated in the Lease or as determined according to the regulations of the Authority adopted pursuant to 15.1.8.070(b)(22); and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>The right, under HUD Section 248 guarantees, to convey the Leasehold Interest to the HUD Secretary without providing the Pueblo the Right of First Refusal.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Order the proceeds of such foreclosure sale to be applied in the following order:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>First, toward the satisfaction of any lien resulting from the assessment of any Leasehold Tax;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>Next, toward any lien having a priority date prior to that of the Mortgage documents;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>Next, as provided in the Mortgage documents; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>Finally, toward any liens having a priority date subsequent to the Mortgage documents.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Trial Court shall have the authority to enter against the Borrower a judgment for any or all of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Past due payments, unpaid utilities, and any charges due the Pueblo or Lessor under any Lease or occupancy agreement;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Any and all amounts secured by the Mortgage that are due the Lender; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Damages caused by the Borrower to the property other than ordinary wear and tear.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Trial Court shall have the authority to award the prevailing party its costs and reasonable attorneys' fees in bringing suit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Trial Court shall not have the authority to enter a deficiency judgment except as may be required pursuant to a federal loan guarantee program.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.2|15.3.2.080" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.2.090</num>
        <heading>Redemption</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>There shall be a Right of Redemption available to a defendant-Borrower in a Mortgage Foreclosure Proceeding. The Redemption period shall extend</text>
          <text>for sixty (60) days from the date that a judgment of foreclosure is entered against a Borrower.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>During the Redemption period, a defendant-Borrower of a mortgaged property, or their heirs, personal representatives, or assigns, may exercise the Right of Redemption by paying to the purchaser, or the purchaser's heirs, personal representatives, or assigns the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The amount paid by the purchaser;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Interest from the date of purchase at the rate of ten percent (10%) per year;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>All taxes, interest, and penalties thereon; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>All payments made to satisfy, in whole or in part, any prior lien or mortgage not foreclosed, paid by the purchaser, with interest on such taxes, interest, penalties and payments made on liens or mortgages at the rate of ten percent (10%) per year from the date of payment.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the Lender is assigned the Borrower's Leasehold Interest, the Lender may subsequently sell or assign such Leasehold Interest without the approval of the Secretary, but only with the written approval of the Lessor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If HUD acquires the Leasehold Interest, it may transfer the same subject to the terms and conditions of the Lease and pursuant to applicable law.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.2|15.3.2.090" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.2.100</num>
        <heading>Intervention</heading>
        <text>The Authority may petition the Trial Court to intervene in any Lease or Leasehold Mortgage Foreclosure Proceeding under this Act. Neither the filing of a motion to intervene by the Authority, nor the grant of such motion by the Trial Court, shall operate as a waiver of the sovereign immunity of the Pueblo or of the Authority, except as expressly authorized by the Pueblo.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.2|15.3.2.100" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.3.2.110</num>
        <heading>Subleases</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In the event that a Federal Agency or the Lender is assigned the leasehold Mortgage as a result of an action brought pursuant to this Act, and a subsequent purchaser cannot be found as provided in this Act, the Federal Agency or Lender may sublease the leased premises to a Member of the Pueblo or a Pueblo entity.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a Pueblo member or entity cannot be found to sublease the leased premises within thirty (30) days of making diligent efforts, the Federal Agency or Lender may sublease the lease to a non-member, provided that the SIHA gives its prior written consent.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="attachments|law|15.3|15.3.2|15.3.2.110" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.3.3</num>
      <heading>Mortgage and Lease Modernization Act of 2024 – Eviction</heading>
      <annotation app="2024-12-16" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R24-015" eff="2024-12-16" path="" type="History"/>
    </container>
  </container>
</container>
