<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" containing-doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>15</num>
  <heading>HOUSING</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>15.1</num>
    <heading>Housing</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.1</num>
      <heading>Housing Authority ICDBG Funding Act of 2016</heading>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes">This law was originally enacted pursuant to Council Resolution No. SI-R16-007, dated May 25, 2016.</annotation>
      </annotations>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.1.010</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Northern Pueblos Housing Authority ("NPHA") is the Tribally Designated Housing Authority ("TDHE") for the Pueblos of San Ildefonso, Picuris, and Tesuque, established by such Pueblos pursuant to § 4(18) and (21) of the Native American Housing and Self Determination Act of 1996, 25 U.S.C. §§ 4401 <em>et seq.</em> ("NAHASDA") for developing, operating, and managing housing units assisted by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development ("HUD");</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo has identified rehabilitation of low-income resident homes as an urgent, high priority housing need in its 2016 Indian Housing Plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Council wishes to authorize NPHA to apply for 2016 Indian Community Development Block Grant (ICDBG) funds on behalf of the Pueblo to finance the rehabilitation of homes of low-income Pueblo residents.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.1.020</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "Housing Authority ICDBG Funding Act of 2016."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.1.030</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Pueblo" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Act" means the Housing Authority ICDBG Funding Act of 2016.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.1.040</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this Act is authorize the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority to apply for and receive funds HUD ICDBG funds to rehabilitate fourteen low income residents' homes.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.1.050</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On April 12, 2000, the Council adopted Ordinance No. SI-R00-001, establishing the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>NPHA is the Tribally Designated Housing Authority ("TDHE") for the Pueblos of San Ildefonso, Picuris, and Tesuque, established by such Pueblos pursuant to §4(18) and (21) of the Native American Housing and Self Determination Act of 1996, 25 U.S.C. §§ 4401 <em>et seq.</em> ("NAHASDA") for developing, operating, and managing housing units assisted by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo has directed NPHA to maintain a waiting list of local residents requesting and eligible to receive home rehabilitation services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Home inspections of residents requesting services have confirmed numerous serious health, safety, energy efficiency, and code compliance issues that could be resolved by an Indian Community Development Block Grant (ICDBG) funded rehabilitation project;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The number of local residents requesting and eligible to receive home rehabilitation services exceeds all funds the Pueblo is eligible to obtain to provide the needed services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo has identified rehabilitation of low-income resident homes as an urgent, high priority housing need in its 2016 Indian Housing Plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Council wishes NPHA to apply for $605,000 in 2016 Indian Community Development Block Grant (ICDBG) on behalf of the Pueblo to finance the rehabilitation of fourteen homes of low-income Pueblo residents; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Pursuant to the Notice of Funding Availability for the ICDBG program, NPHA, acting on behalf of the tribe, must meet certain threshold requirements in order to be deemed eligible for funding; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Acting through NPHA, the Council intends to fully comply with the programmatic and project-related threshold requirements of the ICDBG program.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.1.060</num>
        <heading>Authorization</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby certifies that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A Community Development Statement pertaining to the authorized 2016 ICDBG application for housing rehabilitation, a record of the posting of the Statement, and public meeting record provided to the Council and to be included by NPHA in the ICDBG application documents that all requirements of citizen participation found at 24 C.F.R. 1003.604 have been met;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The 2016 ICDBG application for housing rehabilitation has been made available to residents;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>No public comments affecting the content of the ICDBG proposal were received pursuant to the opportunity provided for citizen participation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The methodology and information provided by NPHA for purposes of meeting ICDBG threshold and service standards, notably in respect to the certification of the income-eligibility of the intended beneficiaries of the project, were systematically collected, are reliable, and are independently verifiable, and are approved by the Council;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Council accepts the ICDBG funding condition that rehabilitation not be provided to any Current Assisted Stock (CAS) homeowner that is not current in their payments;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of ICDBG funding and program delivery, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the applicable provisions contained in the in the Building and Construction Codes as codified in Title 14 of the New Mexico Administrative Code as may be amended from time to time, or the International Building Codes, whichever is more stringent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of ICDBG funding and program delivery, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The NPHA Code of Conduct Policy Statement adopted on February 7, 2011 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 11-6;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The applicable provisions contained in the Ninth Amended and Restated NPHA Procurement, Inventory, Disposition, and Housing Standards Policy, adopted on February 7, 2011 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 11-6;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The Fifth Amended and Restated NPHA Management Policy, adopted on March 19, 2014 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2014-01;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The Fourteenth Amended and Restated Personnel Policy adopted on November 21, 2012 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2012-10;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The Fourth Amended and Restated NPHA Financial Management and Internal Controls Policy, adopted on February 7, 2011 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 11-6 in relation to administration of ICDBG funds;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>The Fourth Amended and Restated NPHA Housing Rehabilitation Standards and Policy adopted on January 19, 2011 by Board Resolution Number 11-1;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The Council affirms that $56,250 in funds set-aside for substantial housing rehabilitation in the Pueblo's 2016 Indian Housing Plan are intended for use as leverage funding in support of the authorized application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Council hereby specifically authorizes NPHA to apply 	for $605,000 in 2016 ICDBG funds on behalf of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The Council hereby approves and adopts this resolution in accordance with the requirements of the Agreement, according to published Council procedures, and authorizes and directs the Governor, or his designee, to take such actions as deemed necessary to carry out 	the intent of this Resolution and law.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-007"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.2</num>
      <heading>Confirming Delegation of Authority to the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority to Apply for 2017 ICDBG Funding for Rehabilitation of Existing Homes for Low-Income Pueblo Members</heading>
      <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.2.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as "CONFIRMING DELEGATION OF AUTHORITY TO THE NORTHERN PUEBLOS HOUSING AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR 2017 ICDBG FUNDING FOR REHABILITATION OF EXISTING HOMES FOR LOW- INCOME PUEBLO MEMBERS," or in the abbreviated form, the "2017 ICDBG GRANT APPLICATION."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.2.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this enactment is to provide the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA) with the authority to apply for 2017 funding under the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) Indian Community Development Block Grant (ICDBG) Program for rehabilitation of existing homes of low-income San Ildefonso Pueblo members.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.2.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On April 12, 2000, the Tribal Council adopted Ordinance No. SI-R00-001, establishing the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Northern Pueblos Housing Authority  is the Tribally Designated Housing Authority ("TDHE") for the Pueblos of San Ildefonso, Picuris, and Tesuque, established by such Pueblos pursuant to § 4(18) and (21) of the Native American Housing and Self Determination Act of 1996, 25 U.S.C. §§ 4401 <em>et seq.</em> ("NAHASDA") for developing, operating, and managing housing units assisted by the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A community meeting was held on April 19, 2017, and Rehabilitation of Existing Homes for Low-Income Pueblo Members was identified as a project priority for the ICDBG Program application and that Citizen (community) participation was adhered to.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.2.040</num>
        <heading>Certifications</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby certifies that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All requirements of citizen participation found at 24 C.F.R. 1003.604 have been met; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Council has considered all comments and views made by residents of the Pueblo; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Council has had the application modified, as necessary; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The ICDBG application has been made available to residents; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The methodology and information provided by NPHA for purposes of meeting ICDBG threshold and service standards, notably in respect to the certification of the income-eligibility of the intended beneficiaries of the project, were systematically collected, are statistically reliable, and to the greatest extent feasible, are independently verifiable, and are approved by the Council; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of ICDBG funding and program delivery, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the applicable provisions contained in the in the Building and Construction Codes as codified in Title 14 of the New Mexico Administrative Code as may be amended from time to time, or the International Building Codes, whichever is more stringent.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.2.050</num>
        <heading>Compliance and Provisions</heading>
        <text>For the purpose of ICDBG funding and program delivery, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with these provisions which collectively enumerate all essential ethics in contracting and conflicts of interest requirements, in relation to the administration and management of ICDBG funds and the delivery of services there under:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The NPHA Code of Conduct Policy Statement Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The applicable provisions contained in the Tenth Amended and Restated NPHA Procurement, Inventory, Disposition, and Housing Standards Policy, Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Seventh Amended and Restated NPHA Management Policy, Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Fifteenth Amended and Restated NPHA Personnel Policy Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>That for the purpose of administering ICDBG funding, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the Fifth Amended and Restated NPHA Financial Management and Internal Controls Policy, Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09 in relation to administration of ICDBG funds;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>That for the purpose of provision of rehabilitation services, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the Fourth Amended and Restated NPHA Housing Rehabilitation Standards and Policy adopted on January 19, 2011 by Board Resolution Number 11-1;</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="attachments|law|1.5" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.2.060</num>
        <heading>Grant Authorization</heading>
        <text>The Governor or his designee is hereby authorized to take such actions as deemed necessary to carry out the intent and purpose of this Resolution.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-05-11" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-009" eff="2017-05-11" path="attachments|law|1.6" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.3</num>
      <heading>Confirming Delegation of Authority to the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority to Apply for 2018 ICDBG Funding for Rehabilitation of Existing Homes for Low Income Pueblo Members</heading>
      <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.3.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as "CONFIRMING DELEGATION OF AUTHORITY TO THE NORTHERN PUEBLOS HOUSING AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR 2018 ICDBG FUNDING FOR REHABILITATION OF EXISTING HOMES FOR LOW- INCOME PUEBLO MEMBERS," or in the abbreviated form, the "2018 ICDBG GRANT APPLICATION."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.3.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this enactment is to provide the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA) with the authority to apply for 2018 funding under the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) Indian Community Development Block Grant (ICDBG) Program for rehabilitation of existing homes of low-income San Ildefonso Pueblo members.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.3.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On April 12, 2000, the Tribal Council adopted Ordinance No. SI-R00-001, establishing the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority (NPHA); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Northern Pueblos Housing Authority  is the Tribally Designated Housing Authority ("TDHE") for the Pueblos of San Ildefonso, Picuris, and Tesuque, established by such Pueblos pursuant to § 4(18) and (21) of the Native American Housing and Self Determination Act of 1996, 25 U.S.C. §§ 4401 <em>et seq.</em> ("NAHASDA") for developing, operating, and managing housing units assisted by the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A community meeting was held on April 19, 2017, and Rehabilitation of Existing Homes for Low-Income Pueblo Members was identified as a project priority for the ICDBG Program application and that Citizen (community) participation was adhered to.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.3.040</num>
        <heading>Certifications</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby certifies that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All requirements of citizen participation found at 24 C.F.R. 1003.604 have been met; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Council has considered all comments and views made by residents of the Pueblo; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Council has had the application modified, as necessary; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The ICDBG application has been made available to residents; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The methodology and information provided by NPHA for purposes of meeting ICDBG threshold and service standards, notably in respect to the certification of the income-eligibility of the intended beneficiaries of the project, were systematically collected, are statistically reliable, and to the greatest extent feasible, are independently verifiable, and are approved by the Council; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of ICDBG funding and program delivery, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the applicable provisions contained in the in the Building and Construction Codes as codified in Title 14 of the New Mexico Administrative Code as may be amended from time to time, or the International Building Codes, whichever is more stringent.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.3.050</num>
        <heading>Compliance and Provisions</heading>
        <text>For the purpose of ICDBG funding and program delivery, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with these provisions which collectively enumerate all essential ethics in contracting and conflicts of interest requirements, in relation to the administration and management of ICDBG funds and the delivery of services there under:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The NPHA Code of Conduct Policy Statement Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The applicable provisions contained in the Tenth Amended and Restated NPHA Procurement, Inventory, Disposition, and Housing Standards Policy, Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Seventh Amended and Restated NPHA Management Policy, Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Fifteenth Amended and Restated NPHA Personnel Policy Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>That for the purpose of administering ICDBG funding, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the Fifth Amended and Restated NPHA Financial Management and Internal Controls Policy, Amended and Restated on October 24, 2016 by NPHA Board Resolution Number 2016-09 in relation to administration of ICDBG funds;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>That for the purpose of provision of rehabilitation services, the Council hereby directs NPHA to comply with the Fourth Amended and Restated NPHA Housing Rehabilitation Standards and Policy adopted on January 19, 2011 by Board Resolution Number 11-1;</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="attachments|law|1.5" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.3.060</num>
        <heading>Grant Authorization</heading>
        <text>The Governor or his designee is hereby authorized to take such actions as deemed necessary to carry out the intent and purpose of this Resolution.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2018-12-17" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R18-030" eff="2018-12-17" path="attachments|law|1.6" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.4</num>
      <heading>Confirming Delegation of Authority to the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority to Apply for Bureau of Indian Affairs, Department of Interior Office of Indian Energy and Economic Development, Energy and Mineral Development Grant to Conduct a Solar Energy Feasibility Assessment</heading>
      <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.4.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as "CONFIRMING DELEGATION OF AUTHORITY TO APPLY FOR BUREAU OF INDIAN AFFAIRS, DEPARTMENT OF INTERIOR OFFICE OF INDIAN ENERGY AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT, ENERGY AND MINERAL DEVELOPMENT GRANT TO CONDUCT A SOLAR ENERGY FEASIBILITY ASSESSMENT" ("Act").</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.4.020</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Agreement" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Governing Agreement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Council" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Pueblo" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.4.030</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this Act is to provide the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority, in coordination with the Pueblo, with authority to apply for grant funding to conduct a feasibility assessment for utilization in developing solar photovoltaic (PV) opportunities at the Pueblo.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.4.040</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Northern Pueblos Housing Authority ("NPHA") is the Tribally Designated Housing Authority ("TDHE") for the Pueblos of Tesuque, Picuris, and San Ildefonso, established by such Pueblos pursuant to § 4(18) and (21) of the Native American Housing and Self Determination Act of 1996, 25 U.S.C. §§ 4401 <em>et seq</em>. ("NAHASDA") for developing, operating, and managing housing units assisted by the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In addition to the environmental benefits, the Pueblo de San Ildefonso is interested in developing solar photovoltaic (PV) opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso to reduce electric utility costs and/or generate additional revenue to support Tribal programs; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Tribal Leadership understands that the appropriate step towards developing solar PV opportunities is to hire a qualified consultant to conduct a feasibility assessment to identify and evaluate possible projects; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Bureau of Indian Affairs (BIA), Department of the Interior Office of Indian Energy and Economic Development, Division of Energy and Mineral Development (DEMD), Energy and Mineral Development Program (EMDP) is</text>
          <text>soliciting proposals for the Grant Program ("Funding Program") to Assess, Evaluate, and Promote Development of Tribal Energy and Mineral Resources (BIA-000-0009-TEDC); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso is committed devoting appropriate resources and coordinating with NPHA and the consultant to facilitate successful completion of the feasibility assessment of solar PV project opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso is willing to consider developing viable solar PV projects, as determined by the completed feasibility assessment.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.4.050</num>
        <heading>Authorizations</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Council hereby authorizes NPHA to coordinate with the Pueblo de San Ildefonso staff to prepare and submit the application to the BIA DEMD in response to the Funding Program solicitation (BIA-000-0009-TEDC) on behalf of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For the purposes of the Funding Program, the Tribal Council hereby designates the NPHA Executive Director, Jon Paul Romero, as the Tribal Project Lead to oversee the project work, make authorized decisions during the course of the project, and be responsible for submitting quarterly and final progress reports, plus financial status reports, as required by the Funding Program; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Council hereby directs NPHA to hire a consultant to complete the feasibility assessment of solar PV opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso, in compliance with all applicable procurement requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso is committed devoting appropriate resources and coordinating with NPHA and the consultant to facilitate successful completion of the feasibility assessment of solar PV project opportunities at the Pueblo de San Ildefonso; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Council hereby authorizes and directs the Governor or his designee to take such actions as deemed necessary to carry out the intent and purpose of this Resolution.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2019-02-13" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R19-005" eff="2019-02-13" path="attachments|law|1.5" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.5</num>
      <heading>Northern Pueblo Housing Authority Evaluation Act of 2021</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004"/>
      <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.5.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "NORTHERN PUEBLOS HOUSING AUTHORITY EVALUATION ACT OF 2021".</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.5.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of the NPHA Evaluation Act is to authorize and direct the completion of a comprehensive study, evaluation, and analysis of the current funding and management of the Northern Pueblo Housing Authority ("NPHA") including options for improving the operation and delivery of housing programs and services.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.5.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo currently contracts with the NPHA to operate, manage, and administer housing programs and services for the Pueblo, including receiving and expending federal grant funds on behalf of the Pueblo as a third-party contractor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>NPHA has experienced a number of detrimental events in the last several years including a high turnover rate in senior management positions and inadequate financial practices; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>NPHA has previously consisted of multiple northern Pueblos; however, NPHA currently</text>
          <text>consists of only two member Pueblos; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The administrative efficiencies of having multiple Pueblos sharing the costs of administrative functions has largely been lost by the departure of other member Pueblos from NPHA; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Council desires to study and evaluate the current funding and operations of the NPHA to determine the best method to provide housing programs and services to the citizens of the Pueblo, including whether to make any modifications to the structure, scope, and delivery of housing programs and services.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.5.040</num>
        <heading>NPHA Report of 2021</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Council hereby authorizes and directs the Governor, the Administrator, the Housing Committee or a designee, to conduct a written, comprehensive review, evaluation, and analysis of the current programs and services provided by NPHA and related issues ("NPHA Report of 2021").</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The NPHA Report of 2021 shall include the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The evaluation of the operation and delivery of housing programs and services provided to the Pueblo by NPHA;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>An evaluation of the management and staffing of NPHA including the status of the Board of Directors;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The types and amounts of funding received by NPHA on behalf of the Pueblo for housing services to the Pueblo;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The financial status of NPHA including current financial statements and practices, and the status of required financial audits;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The process to modify the current arrangement with NPHA or for dissolution of the corporation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>An evaluation of the funding requirements for the Pueblo to operate a minimum housing program including likely available grant funding and any unmet financial obligations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Any other observations and recommendations to assist the Council in evaluating the delivery of housing services by NPHA including methods to improve the delivery, type, and scope of services.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The NPHA Report of 2021 shall be completed and delivered to the Council within sixty (60) days of the effective date of the NPHA Evaluation Act.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-05-03" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-004" eff="2021-05-03" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.1.6</num>
      <heading>Housing Utility Infrastructure Authorization Act</heading>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
      <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "HOUSING UTILITY INFRASTRUCTURE AUTHORIZATION ACT."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this Act is to: (1) Establish a process for members of the Pueblo to apply for home utility infrastructure services or to initiate a Utility Infrastructure Project; (2) ) Establish the standards, process, and requirements for approval of applications for home and homesite utility services; (3) Require public notice of any pending Utility Infrastructure Project with an opportunity for public comments prior to approval; and (4) Authorize the Governor to make final decisions on land use matters pursuant to this Act including applications for home and homesite utility infrastructure services and/or a Utility Infrastructure Project.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.030</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Act" means the Housing Utility Infrastructure Authorization Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Application" means a mandatory, written application completed by a member of the Pueblo to request or initiate a Utility Infrastructure Project.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"DNR" means the Department of Natural Resources of the Pueblo or a designee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>"IHS" means the U.S. Indian Health Service.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>"Project" means any and all home or homesite Utility Infrastructure Projects located on the Pueblo that is funded in whole or in part by or through a member of the Pueblo, a resident of the Pueblo, a private party, the Pueblo, and/or IHS or other governmental agency, as requested in a written Application and subject to the approval of the Governor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>"Pueblo" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso. "Pueblo" also means the lands over which the Pueblo has jurisdiction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>"Utility Infrastructure Project" means any and all projects to develop, repair, or improve water, wastewater, electric, gas, or internet services to a home or homesite.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.040</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The population of the Pueblo is increasing putting pressure on existing housing supplies and creating a need for new housing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Many members of the Pueblo have expressed the need for new housing and improvements to existing homes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo has some land parcels available that could be utilized for new housing purposes; however, these parcels often lack adequate utilities, ingress and egress, and other infrastructure needs; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo has issued land assignments to members of the Pueblo, in some cases decades ago, initially for farming purposes, and some members and their descendants have utilized or desire to utilize land assignments to develop or improve housing including manufactured and new construction homes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo desires to make land available for housing for members of the Pueblo in a fair and equal manner while taking into account the impacts new housing will likely have on neighboring land assignments, land use, the natural environment, culturally-sensitive areas, aesthetics, infrastructure, utilities, and overall policies established by the Pueblo; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The IHS has, from time to time, provided utility line construction and installation services to deliver certain utilities such as water and wastewater systems to members of the Pueblo, including to both existing homes and new homes, at a significant cost savings to the Pueblo and its members; however, the process to apply for IHS-funded services, and the process for the Pueblo to authorize IHS-funded construction services, has been haphazard and unclear, due in part to federal funding limitations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>As part of the <u>Aamodt</u> water rights litigation and settlement, the Pueblo is in the process of constructing a major water infrastructure project that will result in the availability of additional water resources to the Pueblo and its members including water for housing, farming, economic development, conservation, and other purposes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The amount of land available for housing purposes is limited, and any decisions regarding the development of new housing projects must be made in a thoughtful, systematic, and culturally-appropriate manner to protect against waste, duplication of services including utility infrastructure, and to reduce conflicts, while, at the same time, establishing fair and transparent rules and procedures for all members of the Pueblo to address their housing needs; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Council has determined that it is in the best interests of the Pueblo and its members to authorize and direct the Governor to address housing utility issues including the authority to approve and enter into agreements with the IHS to provide utility infrastructure services or to initiate a Utility Infrastructure Project to homes and homesites of members of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.050</num>
        <heading>Mandatory Approval Process for All Utility Infrastructure Projects</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All Utility Infrastructure Projects shall comply with the requirements of this Act. Any person or entity seeking approval of a Utility Infrastructure Project shall fila an Application with DNR. This Act shall not apply to minor repairs or normal; maintenance to home utility services.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.5" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.060</num>
        <heading>Process for Members to Apply for Approval of a Utility Infrastructure Project</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any member of the Pueblo shall be eligible to apply for approval of a Project by filing a written Application with the DNR, which shall be in addition to any application or process required by any other government. DNR may request additional information from an applicant which DNR determines is necessary for consideration and approval of the Project.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>It shall be the responsibility of the applicant to provide adequate information requested in the Application and to cooperate with reasonable requests from DNR for additional information that will assist in the consideration and approval of the Project.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.6" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.070</num>
        <heading>Responsibilities of the Department of Natural Resources</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><u>Application</u>. DNR shall develop a written Application for any member of the Pueblo to apply for approval of a Project.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><u>New Applications</u>. DNR shall keep a chronological list of all Applications for a Project received by the DNR. If an Application seeks assistance and funding from IHS for a Project, DNR shall cooperate with IHS to fulfill the requests for services contained in the Applications in the order the Application was received depending on the nature of the request and the availability of funding; Provided, that the Governor may alter the order of Projects in urgent or emergency situations to protect the health and safety of the citizens of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><u>Pending Applications and/or Requests for Assistance</u>. DNR shall keep a separate list of any known applications or requests for assistance previously filed with IHS and/or pending with IHS at the time of the approval of this Act. DNR shall apply this Act to the extent reasonably possible to all applications or requests for assistance pending at the time of the approval of this Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The DNR shall be authorized to promulgate a rule to establish design criteria for all Projects pursuant to notice and comment rule-making.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The DNR shall review each Application and shall consider the following factors:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The Applicant's land assignment or other indication of the Applicant's property</text>
            <text>interest in the home or homesite; Provided, that the burden of proof demonstrating a property interest shall be on the Applicant, and if DNR and/or the Governor cannot determine that a cognizable property interest exists, then DNR and/or Governor may decline to process the Application by providing a written explanation to the Applicant.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Whether the project is designated in an appropriate location including:</text>
            <para>
              <num>i.</num>
              <text>the nature of the surrounding area including the location of any nearby homes, buildings, and roads;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>ii.</num>
              <text>the amount of available land for the Project;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>iii.</num>
              <text>the length and duration of any disruption to the land;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>iv.</num>
              <text>the availability of all utilities including water, sewer, electricity, gas, and other necessary services, or an explanation of how all basic needs will be met;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>v.</num>
              <text>the impact of the Project on any surrounding or nearby land assignments and homes;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>vi.</num>
              <text>the impact of the Project on the natural environment and whether the least disruptive alternatives have been considered;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>vii.</num>
              <text>whether the project will change or alter the current use of the land;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>viii.</num>
              <text>whether the project will have an impact on future development in the area;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>ix.</num>
              <text>the availability of reasonable ingress and egress to the homesite;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>x.</num>
              <text>the type and condition of the structure to which the utilities will be provided, and whether the Project will improve existing utility service or provide new access to utility services;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Whether IHS has offered any comments or recommendations regarding the design, scope, and cost of the Project;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Whether the project will have any impact on any culturally significant site or have an impact on any religious practice;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Whether the Project will comply with the Pueblo's Tribal Historic Preservation Office requirements and laws including avoiding any disturbance to a culturally significant site;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Whether the Project complies with other applicable laws of the Pueblo.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text><u>Preliminary Review of the Application</u>. DNR shall consider the Project Application and the factors listed above, and any other factors that the DNR may reasonably consider to protect the health and safety of the Pueblo and its citizens. DNR shall recommend approval of the Project unless significant factors listed above exist to deny the Project, which DNR shall identify in writing to the Applicant. DNR shall provide the Applicant with an opportunity to address the factors identified that may be cause to deny the Project.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text><u>Public Notice and Comment</u>. Upon submission of a final Application for a Project, DNR shall provide General Public Notice of the Project for at least thirty (30) days, including Notice in at least one official monthly Pueblo bulletin or newsletter, in the Rio Grande Sun or similar newspaper of general circulation, and in at least two public locations on the Pueblo, and shall include DNR's preliminary recommendation regarding the Project. DNR shall provide Specific Notice of the Project to all known adjacent landowners or anyone with an adjacent property interest. DNR shall also provide the public and any adjacent interested party with at least thirty (30) days to provide comments and recommendations to DNR regarding the Project.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text><u>DNR Recommendation to the Governor</u>. After thorough consideration of the Application and public comments received regarding a Project, DNR shall make a final recommendation to the Governor regarding the approval or rejection of the Project and the reasons therefor. DNR shall provide a final recommendation on a Project within sixty (60) days of the close of the public comment period; provided that DNR may take up to an additional sixty (60) days as necessary by providing written notice of the need for additional time to the Applicant.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.7" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.080</num>
        <heading>Decision by the Governor</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Governor shall make a written decision on all Applications for a Project in a timely manner. A decision made by the Governor pursuant to this Act shall take precedence over any initial decision by IHS regarding a Project. The Governor may take any of the following actions regarding a Project:</text>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>if DNR recommends approval of the Project, the Governor may grant final approval of the Project;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ii.</num>
            <text>if DNR recommends approval of the Project, the Governor may deny the recommendation from DNR, and make a final decision to reject the Project;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iii.</num>
            <text>if DNR recommends denial of the Project, the Governor may make a final decision to reject the Project;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iv.</num>
            <text>if DNR recommends denial of the Project, the Governor may deny the recommendation from DNR and grant final approval of the Project; or,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>v.</num>
            <text>remand the Application to DNR with instructions for further investigation and study, which may include DNR requesting additional information from the Applicant or suggesting modifications to the Application and Project; Provided, that if the Applicant modifies the proposed Project, then DNR shall treat the modified Project as a new Application and shall begin the process anew.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upon approval of a Project by the Governor, the Governor shall be authorized to negotiate and execute agreements with the IHS as may be necessary to provide utility infrastructure services to homes and homesites.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>No Utility Infrastructure Project shall be constructed without the prior approval of the Governor in writing.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.8" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.1.6.090</num>
        <heading>Enforcement</heading>
        <text>The Governor or his designee shall be authorized to enforce this Act including by filing suit in the Courts of the Pueblo against any party who fails or refuses to comply with the requirements of this Act. The Court may award the costs of the enforcement of this Act against any party who has been found to have violated this Act.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2021-08-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R21-018" eff="2021-08-30" path="attachments|law|1.9" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>15.2</num>
    <heading>Home Ownership</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>15.2.1</num>
      <heading>Home Ownership and Property Transfer Clarification Act</heading>
      <section>
        <num>15.2.1.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as, "HOME OWNERSHIP AND PROPERTY TRANSFER CLARIFICATION ACT" ("Act").</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.2.1.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this Act is to clarify the process for members of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Pueblo") to become home owners, and to authorize the Governor to execute and deliver necessary documents to transfer and certify property interests within the Pueblo.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.2.1.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that the current process for members of the Pueblo to obtain ownership of a home through the Northern Pueblo Housing Authority ("NPHA") includes the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo identifies a vacant parcel of land;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo enters into a lease (the "NPHA Lease") with the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority, a federally recognized Tribally Designated Housing Entity ("NPHA") holding authorization from the Pueblos of Picuris, San Ildefonso and Tesuque tribes to obtain and manage Indian Housing Block Grant Program ("IHBG") funding from HUD covering the parcel of land on the Pueblo's reservation where the house is to be located (the "Subject Parcel"), recognizing that, at times, the NPHA lease may cover several parcels (a "master lease");</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Since the Subject Parcel is on the Pueblo's reservation, which is held in trust for the Pueblo by the US Government, the Subject Parcel is subject to federal law;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>As provided by federal law, the NPHA lease between the Pueblo and the NPHA can only have a maximum term of 50 years (25 year initial term and a second 25 year term); At the end of the 50 year term, title to the Subject Parcel reverts to the Pueblo;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Using IHBG funding or other funds, the NPHA builds a house on the Subject Parcel covered by the NPHA Lease;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Because the NPHA is the lessee under the NPHA Lease, the NPHA, as lessee, owns the house (because the house is attached to the land, if the NPHA Lease did not exist, the house would belong to the Pueblo);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>NPHA enters into an "Occupancy Agreement" with a member of the Pueblo (the "Acquiring Member") whereby the Acquiring Member: (1) obtains immediate right to occupy the house;  and, (2) if the Acquiring Member performs certain obligations over a specific term of time, the Acquiring Member will acquire the rights the NPHA has in the house;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Currently, when the Acquiring Member fully performs under the Occupancy Agreement, the NPHA transfers to the Acquiring Member all of the NPHA's right, title and interest in the house in the form of a quit claim deed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The problem with the current arrangement is that although the NPHA is transferring all of its rights as lessee under the NPHA Lease to the Acquiring Member, the NPHA Lease only gives the NPHA the right to occupy the parcel for a maximum of 50 years;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo wants the Acquiring Member to be able to occupy and treat the house 	as his or hers for a period of time longer than the term of the NPHA Lease;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>In order to correct the situation, the process needs to be changed to provide that, when the Acquiring Member fully performs under the Occupancy Agreement: (1) the NPHA gives up all rights it has in the parcel and the house (this would require a quit claim deed between the NPHA and the Pueblo for the Subject Parcel); and (2) the Pueblo would immediately give the Acquiring Member an assignment covering the house and the land on which it is located;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>There is also an issue as to whether the Pueblo's Governor had the legal authority from the Council to grant the right to occupy specific houses to previous Acquiring Members who had fully and completely performed under the Occupancy Agreement.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15.2.1.040</num>
        <heading>Authorization and Ratification of the Governor's Authority to Execute Various Housing Documents</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Upon written notification to the Governor from the NPHA and the Pueblo's Realty Office that an Acquiring Member has fully performed under his or her Occupancy Agreement, the Governor shall take any and all steps to confirm that the Acquiring Member is in good standing with the Pueblo, the NPHA, and the Occupancy Agreement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the Governor determines that the Acquiring Member is in good standing with the Pueblo, the NPHA, and the Occupancy Agreement, the Governor shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Accept a quit claim deed for the house from the NPHA substantially in the form attached hereto, as may be revised from time to time in conjunction with the NPHA; and,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Execute and deliver to the Acquiring Member a Certificate of Land Assignment covering the subject parcel and house substantially in the form attached hereto, as may be revised from time to time in conjunction with the Pueblo's Realty Office and the NPHA.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the Governor does not receive confirmation that the Acquiring Member is in good standing with the Pueblo, the NPHA, and the Occupancy Agreement, the Governor shall so notify the Acquiring Member and the Acquiring Member may obtain review of the matter as provided by the Agreement and laws of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All previous transfers of houses to Acquiring Members (including by quit claim deed or assignment) executed by the current and any previous Governors since 2012 are hereby ratified and confirmed <em>ab initio</em> provided, that the Acquiring Member was in good standing with the Pueblo, the NPHA as confirmed in writing by the NPHA, and the Occupancy Agreement as of the date of transfer.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <annotation app="2017-06-06" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-014" eff="2017-06-06" path="" type="History"/>
  </container>
</container>
