<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" containing-doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Code">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>19</num>
  <heading>COMMUNITY</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>19.1</num>
    <heading>Department of Tribal Services</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>19.1.1</num>
      <heading>Department of Tribal Services Enabling Act</heading>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes">This law was originally enacted pursuant to Council Resolution No. SI-R12-026, dated June 18, 2012.</annotation>
      </annotations>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-026"/>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.1.010</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Annual budget items may only be included if they have first been authorized by law as required by Section 5(a)(ii)(A) of the Agreement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Council finds that reorganizing the structure of governmental departments and programs will promote efficiency within the Tribe;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Council finds that establishing a Department of Tribal Services will assist the Tribe in efficiently administering services provided by Human Resources, Facilities, Aid to Tribal Government; Information Technology, and Tourism.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-026"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.1.020</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the Department of Tribal Services Act ("Act").</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-026"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.1.030</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Agreement" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso governing Agreement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Council" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Pueblo" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-026"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.1.040</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The Purpose of the Act is to establish the Department of Tribal Services.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-026"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.1.050</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>reorganizing the structure of governmental departments and programs will promote efficiency within the Tribe; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>establishing a Department of Tribal Services will assist the Tribe in achieving efficient administration of services provided by Human Resources, Facilities, Aid to Tribal Government; Information Technology, and Tourism.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-026"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.1.060</num>
        <heading>General Policy</heading>
        <text>Department of Tribal Services.  This act shall establish the Department of Tribal Services to efficiently administer services provided by Human Resources, Facilities, Aid to Tribal Government; Information Technology, and Tourism.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-026"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.1.070</num>
        <heading>Organization of the Department of Tribal Services</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>There shall be a Director of the Department of Tribal Services who shall oversee the general supervision of the department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In order to promote efficiency within the Department of Tribal Services, program offices will be established as necessary.  A program director shall oversee the general supervision of the each program office and shall report to the Director of the Department of Tribal Services.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Department of Tribal Services includes the following program offices:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Human Resources</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Facilities</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Aid to Tribal Government</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Information Technology</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Tourism</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-026"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.1.080</num>
        <heading>Department of Tribal Services Goals and Objectives</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>Department of Tribal Services.</heading>
          <text>The overall mission of the Department of Tribal Services is to efficiently administer services provided by Human Resources, Facilities, Aid to Tribal Government; Information Technology, and Tourism.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <heading>Human Resources ("HR").</heading>
          <text>The HR program office shall efficiently manage the Pueblo's human resources, ensure compliance with applicable regulations, provide assistance in personnel management, coordinate recruitment, selection, and hiring, and address employee relations issues.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>Facilities.</heading>
          <text>The Facilities program office shall manage and maintain the Tribe's facilities, buildings and assets, including water, sanitation and sewage systems and utility systems.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <heading>Aid to Tribal Government ("ATTG").</heading>
          <text>The ATTG program office shall administer the Tribal membership enrollment process, issue Certificates of Indian Blood ("CIB") to eligible members, and maintain the Pueblo enrollment system.  The ATTG program office responsibilities include data collection and management, accurate record and documentation management and ensuring compliance with applicable guidelines and laws.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <heading>Information Technology("IT").</heading>
          <text>The IT program office shall manage and maintain the computer network system of the administration of the Pueblo, provide advanced technical assistance, and ensure quality of systems operation in all areas of the organization.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <heading>Tourism.</heading>
          <text>The Tourism program office is responsible for management of the Pueblo's Visitor Center which provides information on local events and activities, culture, local arts and artists, shops, information regarding local guidelines and restrictions or restricted areasto the general public.  The Tourism program office shall gather and utilizes tourist and visitor information including visitor demographics and numbers, visitor trends, and related information.  The Tourism program office is responsible for sales of merchandise, issuing visitor permits and collecting photo permits and other fees, tracking revenues generated, and analyzing marketing trends for use in planning.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-026"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.1.090</num>
        <heading>Amendment</heading>
        <text>The Council may amend this enabling act or reorganize the Department of Tribal Services at any time upon majority vote of the Council.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-026"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.1.100</num>
        <heading>Sovereign Immunity</heading>
        <text>Nothing in this Act waives the sovereign immunity of the Pueblo or any of its representatives, officers, or employees.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-026"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.1.110</num>
        <heading>Severability</heading>
        <text>If a court of competent jurisdiction finds any provision of this Act to be invalid or illegal under applicable tribal and/or federal law, such provision shall be severed from this Act and the remainder of this Act shall remain in full force and effect.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-026"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>19.1.2</num>
      <heading>Public Use Requirements for Tunyo Po Sidewalk and School Crossing Improvement Project Act of 2016</heading>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes">This law was originally enacted pursuant to Council Resolution No. SI-R16-008, dated May 25, 2016.</annotation>
      </annotations>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-008"/>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.2.010</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo received Federal Funds from the New Mexico Transportation Alternative Program Funds (TAP) under the New Mexico Department of Transportation for the Tunyo Po Sidewalk and School Crossing Improvement Project, Control No. 5100973;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Receipt of the TAP Funds requires that the project must be dedicated and open for public use; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Council finds the need to affirmatively state that the entire sidewalk facility that is constructed and improved through the use of the TAP funds shall be dedicated for public use.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Council hereby enacts the attached law entitled, "Public Use Requirements for Tunyo Po Sidewalk and School Crossing Improvement Project Act of 2016."</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-008"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.2.020</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "Public Use Requirements for Tunyo Po Sidewalk and School Crossing Improvement Project Act of 2016."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-008"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.2.030</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Pueblo" means the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Tunyo Po Sidewalk and School Crossing Improvement Project" means the project funded through federal Transportation Alternative Program (TAP) funds administered by the State of New Mexico Department of Transportation.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-008"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.2.040</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this Act is to affirmatively dedicate that the entire sidewalk facility that is constructed and improved through the use of the TAP funds shall be for public use.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-008"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.2.050</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On October 4, 2013, the Council approved Council Resolution No. SI-R13-039: "Support Resolution for the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Transportation Division to Submit an Application to the New Mexico Department of Transportation for Federal Fiscal Year 2014/2015 Transportation Alternative Program Funds;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo received Federal funds from the New Mexico Transportation Alternative Program in the amount of $22,890.00 for the design and $130,381.00 for the construction of the Tunyo Po Sidewalk and School Crossing Improvements Project, Control No. 5100973;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo is providing a matching contribution of $22,218.00 for the construction for a total project cost of $175,489.00; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Receipt of the TAP Funds requires that the project must be dedicated and open for public use; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A portion of the area for the sidewalk facilities lies outside of the existing Tunyo Po right-of-way and there is the need to confirm that entire sidewalk constructed under this project will be open for use by the public regardless of the location.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-008"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.1.2.060</num>
        <heading>Tunyo Po Sidewalk and School Crossing Dedicated for Public Use</heading>
        <text>The Pueblo property upon which the entire sidewalk facility that is constructed and improved through the Tunyo Po Sidewalk and School Crossing Improvement Project shall be dedicated for public use.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-008"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>19.2</num>
    <heading>Animal Control</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>19.2.1</num>
      <heading>Animal Control Act</heading>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes">This law was originally enacted pursuant to Council Resolution No. SI-R16-025, dated November 6, 2016.</annotation>
      </annotations>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.010</num>
        <heading>FINDINGS, PURPOSE AND APPLICABILITY.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>Short Title:</heading>
          <text>This law shall be known as the "Animal Control Act" or "Act."</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <heading>Findings:</heading>
          <text>Untreated animals and uncontrolled roaming of animals on Pueblo Lands pose a threat to the public.  Preventing the spread of disease transmitted by animals, controlling the animal population, and preventing neglect or abuse of animals are proper concerns of the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>Purpose:</heading>
          <text>The purpose of this Act is to preserve the public's health, peace, and safety by preventing the abuse and neglect of animals, preventing the over-population and roaming of animals, preventing and controlling the spread of diseases transmittable from animals to humans, and fostering a culture that promotes the proper care of the animals on Pueblo Lands.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <heading>Applicability.</heading>
          <text>It is a violation of this Act to own an animal except as provided for in this Act.  This Act applies to all animals within the exterior boundaries of Pueblo Lands.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.020</num>
        <heading>EFFECTIVE DATE.</heading>
        <text>The provisions of this Act shall supersede any or all other rules, regulations, or customs that conflict with this Act, and shall be effective six months after enactment.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.030</num>
        <heading>DEFINITIONS.</heading>
        <text>Subject to additional definitions contained in subsequent parts of this Act or unless otherwise specified, the following definitions apply, unless the context otherwise requires:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Abandon" means to desert or give up an animal without having secured another owner for the animal or by failing to provide the elements of basic care for a period of five (5) consecutive days.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Animal" means any mammal, bird, reptile, amphibian, or fish.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Animal Control Officer" means any person employed, contracted, or appointed by the Governor to enforce this Act.  The Animal Control Officer may include a local law enforcement official, a ranger, or any other Person that may be designated by the Governor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>"Horse" includes a horse, pony, mule, burro, ass, or donkey.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>"Impound" means taking or receiving an animal into custody to confine it.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>"Own" means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>To have a property right in an animal;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>To keep, harbor, or maintain an animal;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>To have an animal in one's care;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>To be or act as a custodian of an animal; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>To knowingly allow an animal to stay on any premises occupied by the Owner.</text>
          </para>
          <aftertext>If there is evidence that a person feeds an animal for five (5) or more consecutive days, it will be assumed that the animal is owned by the person unless the person proves otherwise or reports the animal to the Animal Control Officer as a stray.</aftertext>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>"Owner" means any person who owns an animal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>"Person" includes, but is not limited to, any individual, firm, group, association, partnership, corporation, or any other entity whatsoever.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>"Pound" means any establishment authorized by the Council for the confinement, maintenance, safekeeping, and control of animals that are impounded.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>"Provocation" or "provoked" includes intentional or unintentional acts that could reasonably be expected to cause, incite, or encourage an animal to immediately bite the person.  The animal's reaction to the act of provocation cannot be grossly out of proportion to the provocative act itself.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>"Pueblo Lands" means all lands owned by, or within the jurisdiction of, the Pueblo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>"Public Health Official" means an official from the United States Public Health Service.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>"Quarantine" means restriction of the activities of an animal that has been exposed, or is suspected of being exposed, to a communicable disease during a period of communicability or incubation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>"Rabies" means a rhabdovirus of the genus <em>Lyssavirus</em>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>"Rabies Quarantine Area" means any area in which a state of emergency has been declared to exist due to the occurrence or potential occurrence of rabies in animals in or adjacent to this area.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.040</num>
        <heading>SCHEDULE AND USE OF FEES AND FINES.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The amount of fees and/or range of fines to be levied and collected under this Act shall be determined, from time to time, by the Governor or his designee pursuant to notice and comment rule-making.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Nothing in this Act shall prevent the Animal Control Officer from imposing administration fees and fines in addition to any fees and fines imposed by the Court pursuant to Section 10.20(D) of this Act.  All fees and fines collected under this Act will be used to defray the expense of administrating the provisions of this Act including providing access to medical treatment, vaccines, sterilization programs, feed, or the cleaning, repair, maintenance, or construction of facilities used for animals, as appropriated by the Council by law.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.050</num>
        <heading>ANIMAL CONTROL OFFICER.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>Authority.</heading>
          <text>The Animal Control Officer is responsible for the execution and enforcement of this Act, under the direction of the Governor.  The Governor shall be authorized to obtain and provide appropriate training and equipment for Animal Control Officers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <heading>Powers and Responsibilities.</heading>
          <text>In addition to powers and responsibilities authorized elsewhere in this Act, the Animal Control Officer has the following powers and responsibilities:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>To investigate violations or suspected violations of this Act, including entering private property, but only with probable cause, to investigate a violation or possible violation of this Act;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>To enter onto private property without probable cause to apprehend an animal that is at-large.  Such entrance upon private property shall be in reasonable pursuit of the animal and shall not include a right of entry into a domicile or enclosure unless it is at the invitation of a resident or occupant;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>To issue civil citations based on probable cause that a violation of this Act has been committed or to issue orders, warnings, or recommendations directing owners to take certain preventative or corrective measures;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>To prosecute citations in the Pueblo Courts and to testify in such prosecutions;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>To supervise the operation of the community Pound, or the contracting of such services to another entity;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>To institute, as necessary, educational programs to acquaint residents of the Pueblo with the provisions of this Act;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>To administer rabies vaccinations to animals and to issue rabies certificates for such animals but only after the development of a sustainable and professional vaccination program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>To provide reasonable medical resources to Owners when available, on a fee-basis or without charge, depending on the circumstances of each case; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>To perform such other appropriate activities related to the enforcement of this Act or other duties as are assigned to the Animal Control Officer by this Act, by his or her supervisor, or by the Governor.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>Records.</heading>
          <text>The Animal Control Officer must keep complete, correct, and legible records of appropriate matters for five (5) years after the date to which the records relate.  The records to be kept shall include, but are not limited to, the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Investigative records of every violation or possible violation investigated;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Civil citations issued, including the date of the violation, name and address of the Owner of the animal, and any written orders issued or actions taken;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Animals impounded, including the disposition of the animals;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Animal bite cases;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Reports of positive diagnosis of rabies related to animals;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>The destruction of all animals pursuant to this Act; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>All other records deemed necessary by the Animal Control Officer.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <heading>General Liability of Animal Control Officers.</heading>
          <text>No Animal Control Officer will be held liable for the death or injury to any animal that occurs during an attempt to capture, incapacitate, or euthanize the animal, while responding to an emergency situation, or while attempting to ensure his or her own safety or the safety of others.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.060</num>
        <heading>CARE OF ANIMALS.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>Minimum Level of Care.</heading>
          <text>Owners must provide the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Enough food of sufficient nutritional value to maintain the animal in good health.  The food provided must be free from harmful contamination, including free from dirt, sand, or other contamination caused by not storing or feeding in an appropriate container;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Drinkable water accessible to the animal at all times in a clean receptacle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Reasonable medical treatment, which may include traditional methods of treatment; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>When confined, the animal must be confined in an adequate enclosure that provides reasonable access to natural or artificial shelter protecting the animal from temperature extremes.  The enclosure must provide adequate ventilation and must be of a size that minimizes the risk of the animal contracting a disease, being injured, or becoming infested with parasites.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.070</num>
        <heading>LIMITATIONS ON THE NUMBER OF ANIMALS.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>Dogs and Cats.</heading>
          <text>A household may not have more than two dogs over the age of four (4) months nor may it have more than two cats over the age of four (4) months; provided, that any person who owns more than two dogs or two cats on the date of the enactment of this Act may keep such dogs or cats for their natural lives as long as the Owner is in compliance with all other provisions of this Act.  A household that exceeds these limits must turn any animal over the household limit over to the Animal Control Officer for adoption or destruction within ten (10) days of written notice from the Animal Control Officer to any member of the household eighteen years of age or older.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.080</num>
        <heading>ANIMALS AT LARGE.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>No Roaming Permitted.</heading>
          <text>No animal shall be permitted to roam at large, with or without a license or rabies vaccination, on Pueblo Lands.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <heading>Definition.</heading>
          <text>An animal is roaming when it is not:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Securely tied or fenced-in so that the animal is confined entirely to the owner's property; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Physically restrained on a leash, halter, or other secure device and under the direct control of a person fourteen (14) years of age or older; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Temporarily enclosed in a humane manner within a vehicle, a cage, or similar enclosure.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>Exception.</heading>
          <text>Animals properly vaccinated and licensed shall not be considered to be roaming if they are under the direct, in-person control or supervision of an adult Person or Owner.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.090</num>
        <heading>LICENSING.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>False or Misleading Statement or Information.</heading>
          <text>An Owner shall not make false or misleading statements or provide false or misleading information during any stage of the licensing process.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <heading>License Required.</heading>
          <text>All Animals, including dogs and cats, four (4) months of age or older must be licensed.  Licenses shall be issued by the Animal Control Officer.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any animal subject to licensing under this Section must be licensed within fourteen (14) days of the date the animal is acquired by the Owner or brought onto Pueblo Lands.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>An animal subject to licensing under this Section and that is on Pueblo Lands for fourteen (14) days or less is exempt from the licensing requirement of this Section, but the Owner must present a current rabies vaccination before the animal may enter Pueblo Lands.  Any Owner who is not able to present this documentation will be ordered to immediately remove the animal from Pueblo Lands.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>Requirements for License.</heading>
          <text>Before a license may be issued, the Owner must:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Pay any applicable license fees; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Present a rabies vaccination certificate or current tag to the Animal Control Officer proving that the animal has been vaccinated with a vaccine licensed by the United States Department of Agriculture as recommended in the then current Compendium of Animal Rabies Control prepared by the National Association of State Public Health Veterinarians.  The certificate must be signed by a veterinarian or, after the development of a sustainable vaccination program, by the Animal Control Officer.  The certificate must state the Owner's name and address, the animal's description, the date of vaccination, the vaccine type, the vaccine manufacturer and lot number and/or serial number, and the date that revaccination is due.  If the vaccination was administered by a veterinarian, the form shall also state the veterinarian's name and address.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <heading>Form of License.</heading>
          <text>Each license issued shall consist of a license receipt and a suitable tag.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The license receipt shall state the license fee paid, the name, address and telephone number of the Owner, the date of payment, the date the license was issued and expires, the serial number, a general description including color, sex, name, and breed of the animal, and whether the animal has been neutered or spayed.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The tag shall have inscribed on it "San Ildefonso", the number of the license, and the date on which it expires.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <heading>Presentation of License; Failure to Present.</heading>
          <text>Upon request by the Animal Control Officer, an Owner must promptly present its animal's license receipt.  In addition to any other penalties or remedies under this Act, the Animal Control Officer may also order impoundment and the proper disposition of the animal if the Owner fails to produce such a license receipt.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <heading>Wearing of Tag by Animal.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Every dog or cat must wear its tag on a securely attached collar, halter, or similar device whenever the animal is off the Owner's premises.  An animal found without a tag while off its Owner's premises may be considered unlicensed.  The burden of proof that the animal is licensed or not required to wear a tag is on the Owner.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Temporary Removal of Tag.  An animal does not have to wear its tag if wearing a collar, halter, or similar device will worsen a skin condition.  In order to avoid citation, the skin condition must be reasonably observable by the Animal Control Officer.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <heading>Expiration; Renewal.</heading>
          <text>All licenses issued under this Act will expire two years from the date of issuance.  A renewal will be issued upon completion of any required forms and payment of any required renewal fee. Extensions for renewal of an expired license may be given in the sole discretion of the Animal Control Officer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <heading>Replacement License.</heading>
          <text>An Owner may get a license receipt or tag replaced after the Owner submits an application and pays any applicable replacement fee.  The expiration date for the replacement shall be the same date as for the item being replaced.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <heading>Failure to Pay Fee.</heading>
          <text>Payment of any applicable fee in this Section must be made when due.  Payment of an applicable fee after a citation is issued but before a summons to appear is issued does not relieve the Owner from paying any fine ordered by the Courts for failure to pay the fee in a timely manner.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <heading>Pay Over of Fees.</heading>
          <text>All licensing fees collected pursuant to this Act must be held over and paid to an account designated by the Governor in accordance with the Pueblo's accounting policies.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.100</num>
        <heading>VICIOUS ANIMALS; PUBLIC NUISANCE.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>Definition of Vicious.</heading>
          <text>Hunting dogs are exempt from the provisions of this Section when engaged in any legal hunt or training procedure.  Dogs that have been classified as vicious may not be used for hunting purposes.  An animal is vicious if, without provocation, it is an animal that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Has attacked, bitten, seriously injured, or killed a person or other animal; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Has, on two or more separate occasions in a six (6) month period,  engaged in behavior that required a person or another animal to take defensive action in order to avoid serious injury; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Continues to exhibit behavior that previously resulted in the animal being found vicious by the Court; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Demonstrates a tendency to continually expose humans or other animals to the potential of rabies, as recorded through the Rabies Quarantine Program administered by the Animal Control Officer.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <heading>Definition of Public Nuisance.</heading>
          <text>An animal is a public nuisance if it:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Harasses any passing person or animal or chases any passing vehicle; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Attacks other animals; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Barks, howls, or creates other animal noises so as to repeatedly and incessantly disturb the peace and quiet of any person; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Roams repeatedly at-large, or roams at-large during any ceremonial or traditional activity; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Overturns or spreads garbage or other property about; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Runs through, tears up, or eats lawns, gardens, crops, or landscaping; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Creates a substantial and continuous disturbance or annoyance to a person, property, or animals.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>Confinement Before Judgment.</heading>
          <text>Any animal cited as vicious or as a public nuisance may be ordered confined or impounded by the Animal Control Officer until the Court enters its judgment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <heading>Disposition of Animal.</heading>
          <text>The Court may order that the animal be released without conditions, released under conditions ordered by the Court, or euthanized; provided, that any animal that, without provocation, bites so as to cause a severe abrasion of the skin of a person requiring professional medical treatment may only be euthanized pursuant to Section 10.11(C) after the Court makes specific findings as to the severity of the injury and the Court finds no special circumstances or mitigating factors to justify the animal's release with or without conditions.  Any order of the Court requiring the destruction of any animal shall be stayed pending the exhaustion of any appeal and final disposition by the Supreme Court.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <heading>Sign.</heading>
          <text>The Owner of an animal deemed vicious by the Court shall, in addition to any other conditions ordered by the Court, post a sign in a prominent place on the Owner's premises, easily readable by the public, using the words "Vicious Dog."  The posting of a sign does not relieve an owner from liability for a citation under Section 10.11(B) or from civil liability.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.110</num>
        <heading>WHEN AN ANIMAL BITES.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>Notice.</heading>
          <text>Whenever an animal bites any person or other animal, the incident must be reported to the Animal Control Officer immediately by any person having direct knowledge of the incident, including, but not limited to, members of the public, employees or staff of school(s) or medical facilities, and law enforcement officers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <heading>Citation.</heading>
          <text>The Animal Control Officer may cite the Owner of the biting animal, irrespective of whether the animal was known to be vicious prior to the attack.  Proof that the person bitten provoked the attack is a defense.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>Destruction of an Animal That Has Bitten.</heading>
          <text>No person except the Animal Control Officer shall euthanize any animal that has bitten a person or another animal, except that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any person who destroys any animal while the animal is attacking a person or another animal in an effort to stop said attack shall not be civilly or criminally liable for destroying the animal; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A wild animal that bites any person shall be killed and submitted to the Animal Control Officer.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <heading>Quarantine; Impoundment.</heading>
          <text>The Animal Control Officer shall order any animal that bites so as to cause abrasion of the skin to be (1) confined and quarantined at the property of the Owner or at some other appropriate location on the Pueblo, including a veterinary hospital should one be established, or (2) impounded for a period of time as determined by the Animal Control Officer.  If quarantined at the property of the Owner or at a veterinary hospital, the Owner shall make the animal available for inspection upon request by the Animal Control Officer.  If an animal becomes sick and/or dies while being confined or quarantined, the Owner shall immediately contact the Animal Control Officer to determine the proper disposition of the body.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <heading>Liability for an Animal Bite.</heading>
          <text>The Owner of an animal that bites without provocation while the person is on public property, or lawfully on private property, including the property of the Owner of the animal, shall be liable for any damages suffered by the person bitten, regardless of the former viciousness of the animal or the Owner's knowledge of such viciousness.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.120</num>
        <heading>DESTRUCTION OF ANIMALS.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>Humane Method.</heading>
          <text>Any animal euthanized under the provisions of this Act must be euthanized as humanely as possible.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <heading>Injured or Diseased Animals.</heading>
          <text>An animal that is clearly suffering from serious injury, is in great pain and not likely to survive, or an animal that has evidence of any infectious or contagious disease that is a danger to other animals or humans may be euthanized by the Animal Control Officer or by another person under order by the Animal Control Officer, after reasonable efforts to notify the Owner have been made.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.130</num>
        <heading>ABANDONMENT; DUMPING.</heading>
        <text>It is unlawful to release, dump, or abandon live animals anywhere on Pueblo Lands.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.140</num>
        <heading>[RESERVED]</heading>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.150</num>
        <heading>RESPONSIBILITY FOR REMOVAL OF CARCASS.</heading>
        <text>An Owner is responsible for removing and appropriately disposing of all animal carcasses, no matter where the carcass is located, and all expenses associated with the removal and disposal.  Burial of horses must be at a depth of no less than six (6) feet and only at a sight approved by the Solid Waste Department and that does not interfere with ground water.  Other animals need only be buried at a depth of no less than three (3) feet.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.160</num>
        <heading>DISEASED ANIMALS.</heading>
        <text>Any animal afflicted with a contagious or infectious disease must be confined by a fence or pen at all times and may not be removed from its enclosure, even when held by a leash, halter, or other secure device, except for the purpose of being transported to and from a licensed veterinarian.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.170</num>
        <heading>ANIMALS NOT PERMITTED.</heading>
        <text>Animals not permitted on the Pueblo will be ordered off the Pueblo or seized and disposed of; provided, that an owner of such animal(s) may apply for a waiver of subsection (A) and (B) below from the Animal Control Officer who shall grant a waiver if the owner can demonstrate that the animal(s) is properly cared for and maintained so as not to create a public safety issue.  The following animals are not permitted on Pueblo Lands unless a waiver is obtained from the Animal Control Officer:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>Cats and/or Dogs not Spayed/Neutered.</heading>
          <text>Cats or dogs six (6) months of age or older that have not been spayed or neutered.  Proof of the animal's status as spayed or neutered must be provided to the Animal Control Officer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <heading>Certain Breeds of Dog.</heading>
          <text>Dogs of the Rottweiler, Cattle Dog, or Pit Bull breed.  Sterilized dogs of these breeds already on Pueblo Lands as of the effective date of this Act and that do not exceed the household limit under Section 10.7 are permitted to live out their natural lives, but only after the Owner receives a special permit issued by the Animal Control Officer.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>"Cattle Dog" means any Australian Cattle Dog, including, but not limited to, any Australian Heeler, Hall's Heeler, Queensland Heeler, Blue Heeler, Australian Cattledog, Australischer Treibhund, or any American Cattle Dog or American version thereof.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>"Pit Bull" means any pit bull terrier, including, but not limited to, any American pit bull terrier, Staffordshire bull terrier, American bulldog or American Staffordshire terrier breed of dog or any mixed breed of dog which contains as an element of its breeding the breed of American pit bull terrier, Staffordshire bull terrier, American bulldog or American Staffordshire terrier so as to be identifiable as partially of the breed American pit bull terrier, Staffordshire bull terrier, American bulldog or American Staffordshire terrier.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Any person found to have such breed of dog acquired after the effective date of this Act shall immediately surrender the dog to the Animal Control Officer and pay any costs associated with the handling, impounding, and/or the disposition of the animal, including, but not limited to, the off-Pueblo adoption of or the destruction of the animal.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Any person disputing the classification of the dog as one of the breeds banned by this Section by the Animal Control Officer may file a petition for a hearing before the Court.  The animal shall remain impounded during the pendency of the hearing and notice of decision.  At the hearing, the Owner bears the burden of proving that the dog is not one of the breeds prohibited by this Section.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The provisions of this Sub-section 10.17(B) shall take effect ninety (90) days after the effective date of this Act.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>Dangerous Animals.</heading>
          <text>A dangerous animal includes an animal not naturally tamed or gentle, an animal which is of a wild nature or disposition, or an animal that is capable of killing or inflicting serious injury upon human beings and having known tendencies, individually or as a species, to do so.  A dangerous animal also includes, but is not limited to, pythons, anacondas, boa constrictors, poisonous snakes and spiders, bears, wolves, lions, tigers, panthers, alligators, crocodiles, and piranhas.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <heading>Non-Resident Animals.</heading>
          <text>Tourists and other visitors to the Pueblo are not permitted to bring animals onto Pueblo Lands, unless such persons obtain prior approval from the Animal Control Officer after paying any applicable fee and after presenting a current rabies vaccination for the animal.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.180</num>
        <heading>COMMUNITY POUND; IMPOUNDMENT.</heading>
        <text>The Governor may establish a community Pound or enter into a cooperative agreement with another jurisdiction or a veterinarian for the establishment of a community Pound.  At such time as a community Pound is established, the following provisions shall apply:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>Animals That May be Impounded.</heading>
          <text>The following animals, licensed or unlicensed, shall be impounded and the Owner cited:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any animal found abused or neglected under Section 10.6;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Any animal required to be vaccinated under Section 10.9 or 10.19 that is not so vaccinated;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Any animal found at large under Section 10.8;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Any animal found abandoned or dumped under Section 10.13;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Any diseased animal not confined in accordance with Section 10.16;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>An animal that bites a person under Section 10.11;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>An animal that is vicious or a public nuisance under Section 10.10;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Any animal that appears to be infected with rabies pursuant to Section 10.19; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>Any animal not properly confined during rabies quarantine pursuant to Section 10.19.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <heading>Notification.</heading>
          <text>The Animal Control Officer shall immediately upon impoundment make reasonable efforts to notify the Owner, if known, and shall inform the Owner of the conditions whereby the Owner may regain custody of the animal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>Impound fees.</heading>
          <text>An impoundment fee shall be charged for each day that an animal is impounded.  An animal will not be released to its Owner until any impound fees have been paid and proof of current license has been provided.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <heading>Length of Impoundment.</heading>
          <text>Unless an Owner gets a written extension from the Animal Control Officer, an animal not claimed within three (3) days may be sold at a public sale, placed up for adoption, or euthanized.  A person who buys or adopts an animal may not take possession of the animal until the fees associated with its sale or adoption are paid and the person obtains a license for the animal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <heading>Care During Impoundment.</heading>
          <text>All impounded animals shall be given proper care and maintenance.  Any sick or injured animals that are impounded may be euthanized, after reasonable efforts to notify the Owner have been made, to prevent the animal from suffering or to prevent the spread of disease.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.190</num>
        <heading>RABIES AND OTHER DISEASE CONTROL.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>Rabies vaccination.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>It shall be unlawful for any person to own any animal over the age of four (4) months unless such animal is appropriately vaccinated with a vaccine licensed by the U.S. Department of Agriculture as recommended in the current "Compendium of Animal Rabies Control," prepared by the National Association of State Public Health Veterinarians, Inc.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The Owner of an animal shall furnish the current certificate of vaccination upon request by the Animal Control Officer.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Upon being found guilty of three or more violations of this Section related to the same animal, the Court may also order the confiscation and the proper disposition of the animal.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <heading>Certificate and collar tag.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A suitable and distinctive collar tag and certificate of rabies vaccination certifying that the animal in question has been vaccinated shall be issued to the Owner at the time of vaccination.  The collar tag shall be securely affixed to the animal's collar, as appropriate, and shall be worn at all times when the animal is not confined within the Owner's or custodian's dwelling unit.  An Owner of a horse may keep a horse's tag in the Owner's residence.  The Owner must present the tag to the Animal Control Officer upon request.  Proof of rabies inoculation or vaccination in the form of a written certificate must be produced when requested.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A certificate of rabies vaccination issued under this Section shall comply with Section 10.9(C)(2) of this Act.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>All veterinarians doing business on Pueblo Lands shall provide a copy of any issued certificate of rabies vaccination to the Animal Control Officer.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>Declaration of Rabies Emergency.</heading>
          <text>When sufficient evidence exists to believe that a rabid or potentially rabid animal is at-large within Pueblo Lands, the Animal Control Officer may undertake any actions necessary to immediately contain and prevent the spread of rabies.  This will require the immediate cooperation of other Pueblo officials to abate the emergency situation.  The Animal Control Office may issue an emergency rule (which shall become effective upon passage) which may require owners and custodians of animals to keep their animals confined upon their premises unless under leash and under the control of the Owner or custodian so as not to subject their animals to contact with the rabid animal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <heading>Duty to Report, Investigate Rabies Exposure.</heading>
          <text>It shall be the duty of any person who has knowledge of the existence of a rabid or suspected rabid animal or of a person exposed to such animal to immediately report the existence and whereabouts of such animal to the Animal Control Officer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <heading>Notice to Owner; Duty to Respond; Access to Animal.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <heading>Notice to Owner.</heading>
            <text>The Animal Control Officer shall notify the Owner of the rabid or suspected rabid animal, or of an animal suspected of having itself been exposed to a suspected rabid animal, of the report.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <heading>Adequacy of Notice.</heading>
            <text>Notice to the Owner shall be deemed made if executed in any of the following manners:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>By direct verbal notice to the Owner or any other resident of the Owner's home or a family member over the age of sixteen (16) years;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>By delivering a written notice to the Owner or to any other resident of the Owner's home or a family member over the age of sixteen (16) years;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>By posting a written notice at the Owner's last known address; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>By posting a written notice at the location of the exposure (when no address or telephone number can be obtained).</text>
              <text>Testimony of the Animal Control Officer as to the manner of service of the notice shall constitute <em>prima facie</em> evidence that service was made.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>If notice is made in writing, the Owner shall immediately and in no event in more than twenty-four (24) hours, contact the Animal Control Officer about the notice.  Each subsequent day's failure to make the required contact with the Animal Control Officer after written notice is made shall be considered a separate offense by the Owner.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The Owner of any animal reported to have exposed a person or other animal to a rabid or suspected rabid animal shall give the Animal Control Officer or Public Health Official prompt access to the animal at any time as may be necessary for verification of quarantine or as may be required to prevent the spread of rabies and thereby safeguard human life.  Upon order by the Animal Control Officer, the Owner shall immediately relinquish such animal to the Officer.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>It shall be unlawful for any person to evade or elude the Animal Control Officer or to dispose of, conceal, harbor, or remove from Pueblo Lands any animal to keep the animal from being quarantined, euthanized, or confined in accordance with this Act.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <heading>Quarantine.</heading>
          <text>Any animal determined by the Animal Control Officer to be a threat to the spread of rabies may be ordered quarantined.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Quarantine means restriction of the activities of an animal which has been exposed or is suspected of being exposed to a communicable disease during a period of communicability or incubation to prevent further disease transmission.  Such quarantines shall meet the criteria set forth by the Animal Control Officer in accordance with the current guidelines in the "Compendium of Animal Rabies Control."</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Strict Isolation or absolute quarantine means the restriction of contact between exposed subjects and other animals and/or humans for a period of time not longer than the longest usual incubation of the disease.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Modified quarantine means a selective, partial limitation of freedom of movement and contact between exposed and nonexposed humans and/or animals as deemed appropriate to prevent transmission of the disease.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <heading>Quarantine Under Owner's Control.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any animal so quarantined shall be kept so as to be available for inspection by the Animal Control Officer and such quarantined animal shall not be removed, released, or euthanized without the express consent of the Animal Control Officer.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>In the event an animal in such quarantine needs to be relocated, the Owner or person undertaking the relocation shall notify the Animal Control Officer prior to the relocation occurring.  Upon order by the Animal Control Officer, the owner shall immediately hand over such animal.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Such animal shall be confined for a period of no less than one (1) day and not to exceed six (6) months.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <heading>Quarantine Under Veterinary Control or Impoundment.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>If the Animal Control Officer determines that such animal cannot be safely and appropriately confined under the Owner's control, the animal may, at the discretion of the Animal Control Officer, be quarantined by containment at a veterinary facility or by impoundment at the community Pound.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>If the animal is ordered impounded or to be contained at a veterinary facility, the Owner shall be responsible for all impoundment or containment fees, whether or not the animal is determined to be rabid.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>Such animal shall be confined for a period of no less than one (1) day and not to exceed six (6) months.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <heading>Destruction of Rabid Animal.</heading>
          <text>Any animal quarantined or impounded under the previous provisions may be euthanized prior to the termination of the confinement period upon the order of the Animal Control Officer for laboratory examination for rabies if such animal shows clear clinical signs of rabies or the Owner consents to its destruction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <heading>Animal Dying During Quarantine.</heading>
          <text>If an animal dies while being quarantined pursuant to this Section and the animal is known to have exposed another animal or person to rabies at any time during a period of two (2) weeks before the beginning of the quarantine period through the time of death, it shall be the duty of the person with such knowledge to immediately contact the Animal Control Officer who will contact the Public Health Official and obtain instructions for the testing and/or disposal of the body.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <heading>Rabies Clinics.</heading>
          <text>The Animal Control Officer is hereby authorized to review, from time to time, the need for rabies clinics to encourage residents to comply with provisions of this Act requiring the vaccination of animals against rabies.  The Animal Control Officer shall be responsible for working with the Public Health Official and others to schedule and coordinate such clinics based on the availability of veterinarian services.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.200</num>
        <heading>CITATION; COMMENCEMENT OF ACTION; FINES.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <heading>Service.</heading>
          <text>A citation issued pursuant to this Act must be provided to the person cited and may be served by personally delivering a copy to the person or by any other means authorized by the civil rules of the Pueblo for serving a civil complaint.  The citation shall command the person to appear before the Court at a time and place to be ordered by the Court and to answer the violation alleged.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <heading>Number of Incidents.</heading>
          <text>Once a person has been cited, each day that the person fails to comply with the provisions of this Act will constitute a separate offense.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>Proceedings.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <heading>Jurisdiction.</heading>
            <text>The Pueblo Courts have jurisdiction over civil complaints filed by the Animal Control Officer pursuant to this Act.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <heading>Hearing Date Set.</heading>
            <text>Upon filing of the citation by the Animal Control Officer with the Clerk of the Court, a hearing will be set for the Court's next available hearing date.  If the next hearing date is less than seven (7) days after the filing of the complaint, the hearing will be set for the following hearing date.  A copy of the civil citation may serve as the civil complaint.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <heading>Summons to Appear.</heading>
            <text>The Clerk of the Court must issue a Summons to Appear to the person cited no less than seven (7) days prior to the hearing date.  The Summons to Appear shall state the date, time, and location of the hearing.  The Summons to Appear shall contain a statement that failure to appear will be deemed an admission of guilt to the allegation(s).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <heading>Hearing.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>A person served with a Summons to Appear must appear before the Court at the designated time and place.  The person must enter a plea of (i) admit, (ii) admit with explanation, or (iii) deny.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>If the person admits or admits with explanation, the Court shall enter judgment for the Pueblo and impose a civil fine and the time in which the fine must be paid.  In determining the fine, the Court may consider any explanation submitted by the person cited.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>If the person fails to appear, the Court shall enter judgment for the Pueblo and shall impose a civil fine and the time in which the fine must be paid.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>If the person denies the allegation, the Court shall set a trial date.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <heading>Trial.</heading>
            <text>The trial shall be informal and without a jury.  The Animal Control Officer is required to prove that the violation occurred by a preponderance of evidence.  Technical rules of evidence shall not apply.  The failure of the Animal Control Officer to perform the Officer's duties or responsibilities under this Act shall not be cause for the Court to set aside the citation.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>If the Court finds in favor of the cited person, it shall enter an order dismissing the allegation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>If the Court finds in favor of the Pueblo, it shall enter judgment for the Pueblo, impose a civil fine on the person, and set the date by which the fine must be paid.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>The decision of the Court shall be final and shall be appealable to the Supreme Court.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <heading>Penalty.</heading>
          <text>In addition to any other fees assessed under this Act, a person found responsible by the Court shall be subject to the following civil penalties:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>For a minor violation, a fine no less than twenty-five dollars ($25.00) and not to exceed one-hundred dollars ($100.00).  Minor violations include, but are not limited to, licensing violations, roaming violations, failure to spay or neuter violations, or failing to dispose of a carcass.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>For a medium violation, a fine no less than one-hundred dollars ($100.00) and not to exceed five-hundred dollars ($500.00).  Medium violations include, but are not limited to, vaccination violations, household limitation violations, failure to post a vicious animal sign, harboring a vicious or nuisance animal, or harboring a dangerous animal or an animal not permitted on Pueblo Lands.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>For a major violation, a fine of no less than five-hundred dollars ($500.00) and not to exceed one-thousand dollars ($1,000.00).  Serious violations include, but are not limited to, care and neglect violations, confinement violations, and violations of Section 10.19 Rabies and Other Disease Control.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>In addition to any fine imposed under this sub-Section, the Court may also enter an order removing an animal from the Owner, prohibiting an Owner from owning an animal or any kind of animal, requiring certain conditions for an Owner to have or keep an animal, or any other order that the Court finds, in its discretion, achieves the purposes of this Act.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <heading>Community Service in Lieu of Payment of Fine.</heading>
          <text>If the person is not able to pay any fines ordered for any reason, the Court may order the person to complete one (1) hour of community service at the national minimal wage rate until the monies due would have been paid off.  Such work shall be performed under the supervision of the Animal Control Officer and must consist of activities that pertain to the care, treatment, or control of animals and/or the cleaning, repair, maintenance, or construction of facilities used for animals.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <heading>Pay Over of Fines.</heading>
          <text>All fines must be paid to the Clerk of the Court.  The Clerk of the Court shall hold and pay over to an account designated by the Governor on a monthly basis all the fines collected pursuant to this Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <heading>Judgment of Civil Liability for Damages or Injury.</heading>
          <text>When judgment is entered against a person, the person shall also be liable in any civil action brought for damages or injury.  When the action arises from an attack, the owner shall be civilly liable whether the person attacked was in a public place or lawfully upon private premises and regardless of whether or not the animal was known to be vicious prior to the attack.  Proof that the plaintiff provoked the attack is a defense.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.2.1.210</num>
        <heading>LEGISLATIVE HISTORY.</heading>
        <text>This Animal Control Act was enacted and codified by the Council through Resolution No. SI-R16-025, effective November 5, 2016.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R16-025"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>19.3</num>
    <heading>Personnel Policies</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>19.3.1</num>
      <heading>Reaffirmation of the Tribal Personnel Manual</heading>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes">This law was originally enacted pursuant to Council Resolution No. SI-R12-015, dated March 1, 2012.</annotation>
      </annotations>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-015"/>
      <section>
        <num>19.3.1.010</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Council has previously adopted personnel policies for the Tribal Administration employees as provided for in the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Personnel Policy Manual;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Council has determined it to be in the best interest of the Pueblo to reaffirm the Pueblo de San Ildefonso Personnel Policy Manual.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-015"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.3.1.020</num>
        <heading>Personnel Policy Manual</heading>
        <include>
          <text>
            <center>Pueblo de San Ildefonso</center>
          </text>
          <text>
            <center>Human Resources Office</center>
          </text>
          <text>Personnel Policy Receipt Form</text>
          <text>I, ___________________________________ (employee), acknowledge receipt of this manual and that I have thoroughly read and understand its contents.  I also understand that this manual is Pueblo de San Ildefonso's property that must be returned to the Human Resources Coordinator on or before my last day of work.</text>
          <text>I further understand that this manual does not create a contract with the Council for any purpose and that the provisions of this manual may be modified or eliminated at any time as approved by the Tribal Council.</text>
          <text>Issued to: _________________________________________________</text>
          <text>Signed:    _________________________________________________</text>
          <text>Date Received:    ________________________</text>
          <text>
            <center>
              <strong>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO</strong>
            </center>
          </text>
          <text>
            <center>
              <strong>PERSONNEL POLICY</strong>
            </center>
          </text>
          <text>
            <center>TABLE OF CONTENTS</center>
          </text>
          <text>PAGE</text>
          <text>INTRODUCTION	1</text>
          <text>DEFINITIONS	2</text>
          <text>GENERAL EMPLOYMENT POLICIES</text>
          <text>101.	Nature of Employment	3</text>
          <text>102.	Equal Employment Opportunity 	4</text>
          <text>103.	Business Ethics and Conduct 	5</text>
          <text>104.	Conflicts of Interest	6</text>
          <text>105.	Outside Employment 	7</text>
          <text>106.	Dress Code	8</text>
          <text>107.	Confidentiality	9</text>
          <text>RECRUITMENT</text>
          <text>201.	Personnel Selection Committee 	10</text>
          <text>202.	Job Vacancies and Employee Transfers	11</text>
          <text>203.	Employment Applications	12</text>
          <text>204.	Employment Reference Checks and Background Investigations	13-15</text>
          <text>205.	Hiring of Relatives 	16</text>
          <text>EMPLOYMENT STATUS &amp; RECORDS</text>
          <text>301.	Employment Categories 	17-18</text>
          <text>302.	Job Descriptions 	19</text>
          <text>303.	Probationary Period	20</text>
          <text>304.	Performance Evaluation	21</text>
          <text>305.	Personal Data Changes	22</text>
          <text>306.	Access to Personnel Files 	23</text>
          <text>EMPLOYEE BENEFITS</text>
          <text>401.	Annual Leave	24</text>
          <text>402.	Sick Leave 	25</text>
          <text>403.	Bereavement Leave 	26</text>
          <text>404.	Family and Medical Leave Of Absence	27-29</text>
          <text>405.	Other Unpaid Personal Leave Of Absence 	30</text>
          <text>406.	Holidays 	31</text>
          <text>407.	Military Leave 	32</text>
          <text>408.	Time Off To Vote	33</text>
          <text>409.	Jury Duty 	34</text>
          <text>410.	Overtime and Compensatory Time 	35</text>
          <text>411.	Administrative Leave of Absence	36</text>
          <text>412.	Donation of Sick Leave	37</text>
          <text>ATTENDANCE</text>
          <text>501.	Definitions	38</text>
          <text>502.	Timekeeping and Documenting 	39</text>
          <text>503.	Work Schedules 	40</text>
          <text>504.	Separation from Employment 	41-42</text>
          <text>505.	Return of Property	43</text>
          <text>SPECIAL WORK PLACE POLICIES</text>
          <text>601.	Use of Phone and Mail Systems 	44</text>
          <text>602.	No Smoking Policy 	45</text>
          <text>603.	Use of Equipment and Vehicles 	46</text>
          <text>604.	Visitors in the Workplace	47</text>
          <text>605.	Use of Information Systems and Networks 	48-49</text>
          <text>606.	Workplace Safety	50-51</text>
          <text>EMPLOYEE CONDUCT &amp; DISCIPLINARY ACTION</text>
          <text>701.	Employee Conduct and Work Rules 	52-53</text>
          <text>702.	Drug and Alcohol Policy	54-65</text>
          <text>703.	Harassment Policy 	66</text>
          <text>704.	Progressive Discipline 	67-69</text>
          <text>705. -Grievances and Appeals 	70-71</text>
          <text>
            <strong>INTRODUCTION</strong>
          </text>
          <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso is a sovereign self-governing Nation and recognized as such by the United States of America.  The Pueblo Tribal Council is the governing body and has legislative and other responsibilities for the Pueblo in its exercise of its inherent sovereign powers.  A primary objective of the Tribal Council is to provide a work environment that is conducive to both personal and professional growth.</text>
          <text>This Policy is designed to acquaint you with the Pueblo and provide you with information about working conditions, employee benefits, and some of the policies affecting your employment.  It describes many of your responsibilities as an employee and outlines the programs developed by the Pueblo to benefit employees.  It is your responsibility to read, understand, and comply with all provisions of the Policy.</text>
          <text>One of our objectives is to provide a work environment that is conducive to both personal and professional growth.</text>
          <text>No Personnel Policy can anticipate every circumstance or question.  Over time, the need may arise and the Pueblo reserves the right to revise, supplement, or rescind any policies as the Tribal Council deems appropriate, in its sole and absolute discretion. Employees will be notified appropriately of such changes.</text>
          <text>These policies and procedures shall apply to all employees of the Pueblo.</text>
          <text>
            <strong>DEFINITIONS</strong>
          </text>
          <text>The following terms are used throughout this Manual:</text>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Council"</strong> means the governing body for the Pueblo.  This Personnel Policy has been approved and adopted by the Pueblo Tribal Council.  In case of conflict between this Personnel Policy and Tribal Ordinances and By-Laws, the Tribal Council will evaluate the conflict and make decision regarding which provision shall prevail.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text><strong>"Governor" </strong>means the elected official of the Pueblo in charge of all programs, employees, and operations, and the direct supervisor of the Tribal Administrator.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>3.</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Administrator" </strong>means the individual who administers the day-to-day operations, business and fiscal affairs, and other management function associated with the administration of the Pueblo and who supervises all Directors.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>4.</num>
            <text><strong>"Director" </strong>means the person charged with the management and budget functions of individual departments and/or programs of the Pueblo.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>5.</num>
            <text><strong>"Supervisor"</strong> means the individual to whom any employee directly reports and receives directions.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>6.</num>
            <text><strong>"Coordinator" </strong>means an individual responsible for the overall function of the program and provides administrative direction/support and technical assistance to all staff.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>7.</num>
            <text><strong>"Employee" </strong>means an individual hired to carry out the objectives of the Pueblo, as identified in their job description.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>8.</num>
            <text><strong>"Pueblo de San Ildefonso" </strong>means a sovereign self-governing Indian Nation recognized by the United States of America Federal Government.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>9.</num>
            <text><strong>"At-Will" </strong>means an employee is free to resign at any time; and the Pueblo is free to terminate employment at any time, with or without cause.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>GENERAL EMPLOYMENT POLICIES</strong>
            </text>
            <text>
              <strong>101. Nature of Employment</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Employment with the Pueblo is "at-will" so that employment is voluntarily entered into by the employee and the employee is free to resign at any time, with or without cause. Similarly, the Pueblo is free to terminate the employment at any time, with or without cause.  Employees may be given the right to pursue grievance procedures.</text>
            <text>This Policy is not a contract. The policies set forth are not intended to create a contract, nor are they to be construed to constitute contractual obligations, express or implied, to remain employed by the Pueblo. Nor does it guarantee any fixed terms or conditions of employment. Nothing in any policy or work rule of the Pueblo shall alter the at-will employment relationship between the Pueblo and its employees.</text>
            <text>This Policy is intended to provide employees with a general understanding of employment with the Pueblo. However, this Policy cannot anticipate every situation or answer every question about employment. Therefore, in order to retain necessary flexibility in the administration of policies and procedures, the Pueblo reserves the right to alter, delete, or add to any of the provisions of the Policy and to change, modify, suspend, cancel or interpret any of the personnel policies and practices or employee benefits which are described herein without notice to employees whenever the Tribal Council determines, in its sole discretion, that such action is warranted and without having to give cause or justification or consideration to any employee.</text>
            <text>These provisions supersede all existing policies and practices and may not be amended or added to without the express written approval of the Pueblo Tribal Council. It is the responsibility of the Tribal Administrator to notify all employees of changes made to the content of the Policy in a timely fashion.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>102. Equal Employment Opportunity</strong>
            </text>
            <text>In order to provide equal employment and advancement opportunities to all individuals, employment decisions at the Pueblo will be based on performance, job qualifications, and experience. The Pueblo does not discriminate in employment opportunities or practices on the basis of race, color, religion, sex, sexual orientation, national origin, age, ancestry, disability, or any other characteristic protected by law. However, the Pueblo will give preference in employment to qualified American Indians and Pueblo Tribal members as described by the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act and other applicable laws.</text>
            <text>This policy applies to all employment practices, including recruiting, hiring, evaluation, promotion, transfer, discipline and termination, as well as all forms of employee compensation. All of the Pueblo's policies will be interpreted to permit and promote reasonable accommodation of the disabilities and religious beliefs and practices of otherwise qualified employees and applicants, except where such accommodation causes undue hardship to the Pueblo. The extent of an obligation is determined by the Pueblo of San Ildefonso's needs, financial costs and expense, in conformity with applicable law.</text>
            <text>Every employee is expected to conform to this policy, to accomplish work in a professional and businesslike manner, and to be courteous to all other employees, contractors, business associates, customers, guests, and visitors at all times. Discrimination against or harassment of any employee or other person because of race, color, religion, creed, sex, sexual orientation, marital status, age, national origin, ancestry or disability is strictly prohibited.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>103. Business Ethics and Conduct</strong>
            </text>
            <text>The successful operation and reputation of the Pueblo is built upon the principles of fair dealing and ethical conduct of our employees. Employees owe a duty to the Pueblo, its community members and the Tribal Council to act in a way that will merit the continued trust and confidence of the public. Employees are expected to conduct themselves in a positive and professional manner so as to promote the best interests of the Pueblo.</text>
            <text>The Pueblo will comply with all applicable laws and regulations and expects its employees to conduct business in accordance with the letter, spirit, and intent of all applicable laws and regulations and to refrain from any illegal, dishonest, or unethical conduct.</text>
            <text>In general, the use of good judgment, based on high ethical principles, will guide employees with respect to lines of acceptable conduct. If a situation arises where it is difficult to determine the proper course of action, the matter will be referred to the Tribal Administrator who will make a final determination on the issue. Conduct that interferes with operations, discredits, or is offensive the Pueblo, the public, or fellow employees will not be tolerated.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>104. Conflicts of Interest</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Employees have an obligation to conduct business within guidelines that prohibit actual or potential conflicts of interest. Employees are expected, at all times, to act in the best interest of the Pueblo.</text>
            <text>Transactions with outside firms<sup>-</sup> must be conducted within a framework established and controlled by the Governor of the Pueblo. Business dealings with outside firms should not result in unusual gains for those firms or employees. Unusual gain refers to bribes, product bonuses, special fringe benefits, unusual price breaks, and other windfalls designed to ultimately benefit the employer, the employee, or both. Plans that could be interpreted to involve unusual gain require specific approval from the Tribal Council.</text>
            <text>An actual or potential conflict of interest occurs when an employee is in a position to influence a decision that may result in a personal gain for that employee or for a relative as a result of the Pueblo's business dealings.</text>
            <text>However, if employees have any influence on transactions involving purchases, contracts, or leases, it is imperative that they disclose to the Tribal Administrator the existence of any actual or potential conflict of interest so that safeguards can be established to protect all parties.</text>
            <text>Personal gain may occur not only in cases where an employee or relative has a significant ownership in a firm with which the Pueblo does business, but also when an employee or relative receives special consideration or unusual gain as a result of any transaction or business dealing.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>105. Outside Employment</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Unless a conflict of interest is created, an employee may hold a job with another organization as long as that employee, first, obtains the written acknowledgment from their Director and, second, continues to satisfactorily perform their job responsibilities with the Pueblo. The second job cannot interfere with the position held with the Pueblo of San Ildefonso.   All employees will be judged by the same performance standards and will be subject to the Pueblo's scheduling demands, regardless of any existing outside work requirements.</text>
            <text>If the Pueblo determines that an employee's outside work interferes with performance or the ability to meet the requirements of the Pueblo, the employee may be asked to terminate the outside employment as a condition of remaining employed by the Pueblo.</text>
            <text>Outside employment will present a conflict of interest if it has an adverse impact on the Pueblo or otherwise is inconsistent with the provisions of Section 104 Conflicts of Interest.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>106. Dress Code</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Dress, grooming, and personal cleanliness standards contribute to the morale of all employees and affect the business image the Pueblo presents to community members and visitors. Attire should be clean, tasteful, non-offensive and non-revealing.</text>
            <text>During business hours, employees are expected to present a clean and neat appearance and to dress according to the requirements of their positions. Employees who appear for work inappropriately dressed will be sent home and directed to return to work in proper attire. Under such circumstances, employees will not be compensated for the time away from work.</text>
            <text>Consult your Director or supervisor if you have questions as to what constitutes appropriate attire.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>107. Confidentiality</strong>
            </text>
            <text>The protection of confidential business information, trade secrets and Tribal information is vital to the interests and the success of the Pueblo. Such confidential information includes, but is not limited to, the following:</text>
            <text>
              <ul>
                <li>Personnel Records</li>
                <li>Enrollment Files and Data</li>
                <li>Case Files</li>
                <li>Compensation Information and Data</li>
                <li>Computer Passwords</li>
                <li>Legal opinions of counsel</li>
                <li>Investigation Background Check</li>
                <li>Financial Information</li>
                <li>Business Information and Data</li>
                <li>Pending Projects and Proposals</li>
                <li>Research, Development, Marketing Strategies</li>
                <li>Tribal Council Minutes</li>
                <li>Pueblo Customs, Rites and Traditions</li>
              </ul>
            </text>
            <text>In addition, certain files and documents kept by a federally funded program may be considered as part of the federal recordkeeping system and may be subject to the Privacy Act.</text>
            <text>All employees are required to sign a non-disclosure agreement as a condition of employment. Employees who improperly use or disclose trade secrets or confidential business information will be subject to disciplinary action, including termination of employment and legal action, even if they do not benefit from the disclosed information.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>RECRUITMENT</strong>
            </text>
            <text>
              <strong>201. Personnel Selection Committee</strong>
            </text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>a.</num>
            <text>) For each vacancy the Tribal Administrator, in consultation with the Governor, shall appoint an Ad Hoc Personnel Selection Committee. The selection committee may be composed of two or more individuals including the Human Resources Director, the Department Director, and at least one Councilman knowledgeable in the field. The role of the Personnel Selection Committee shall be to review applications, evaluate applicants for employment based on job qualifications and experience, and recommend final selection of applicants to the Tribal Administrator and/or Governor. Immediate family members may not serve on the same personnel selection committee, nor may immediate family members of an interviewee serve on the Personnel Selection Committee evaluating that interviewee.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>b.</num>
            <text>) The Committee must display fairness, honesty and integrity in the execution of its duties as Personnel Selection Committee members in screening and selecting employees for the Pueblo. If the Personnel Selection Committee or an individual member sees a conflict of interest arise, that person will remove themselves or be asked to remove themselves.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>c.</num>
            <text>) The Tribal Council reserves the right to make the final decision or approve the final decision on the hiring of high level management positions.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>202. Job Vacancies and Employee Transfers</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Job vacancies will first be posted on the employee bulletin board and within the community of the Pueblo. Announcements may be sent to other recruiting sources and publications as applicable. It is within the sole discretion of the Pueblo to fill a vacancy with an existing employee or hire a new employee from outside of the Pueblo. Each job posting notice will include the job title, department, location, job summary, essential duties, qualifications, and the closing date for receipt of applications.</text>
            <text>To be eligible to apply for a posted job, employees must have performed competently for at least ninety (90) calendar days in their current position. Employees who have not completed any corrective action issued in connection with a written warning, or who are on probation or suspension, are not eligible to apply for posted jobs. When an applicant is considered for a position, the hiring supervisor or Director will contact the applicant's Director to verify performance, skills, and attendance.</text>
            <text>Upon transfer to another program, an employee, at the discretion of the Pueblo, may be compensated for 50% of any accrued annual leave to be paid by the program from which the employee is transferring. The remaining accrued annual leave and all sick leaves shall be carried over to the new program. This policy is meant to prevent the new program from bearing the burden of carrying and covering the full amount of accrued annual leave for a transferred employee.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>203. Employment Applications</strong>
            </text>
            <text>All applicants shall complete a Pueblo Employment Application Form. The Pueblo relies upon the accuracy of information contained in the employment application, as well as the accuracy of other data presented throughout the hiring process and employment. Any misrepresentations, falsifications, or material omissions in any of this data may result in the Pueblo's exclusion of the individual from further consideration for employment or, if the person has been hired, termination of employment.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>204. Employment Reference Checks and Background Investigation</strong>
            </text>
            <text>It is the policy of the Pueblo to check the employment references of all applicants.  Background investigations will be conducted on business managers for businesses operated by the Pueblo and not its corporation, financial managers, controller and assistant controller.  These financial positions do not require an FBI Criminal History Records Search.</text>
            <text>It is the policy of the Pueblo that background investigations, and reinvestigations every five years, shall be conducted on those individuals in positions covered by Public Law 101-630, Indian Child Protection and Family Violence Prevention Act for the protection of children and of the elderly.  A favorable background investigation meeting the minimum standards of inquiries identified in federal regulations is a condition of employment for individuals working with, having regular contact with or having control over children and the elderly.</text>
            <text>Covered programs include but are not limited to the following:   (1) All Health and Human Services programs including Community Health Representative Program, Diabetes Program;, Health Coalition,  Senior Citizens Center, and the Indian Child Welfare Act Program; and (2) all Education programs including the Language Program, Recreation and Youth, the Parks and Wildlife Program and (3) the Tribal Courts.  Each of the individuals must meet the minimum standards of character prescribed by federal laws and regulations to work in such programs or positions.</text>
            <text>The Background Investigations Program is designed to meet the minimum standards of investigative inquiries identified by federal laws and regulations.  The Background investigation process requires investigation of individuals applying for or working in a paid or voluntary capacity, whether short term or long term, and includes:</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>FBI Criminal History Records Search via fingerprint checks.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text>State Repository Check - Criminal history checks within each state that the individual identifies as a former residence and each place of work for the last 5 years.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>3.</num>
            <text>Local Law Enforcement Check - Law enforcement agency check (including tribal entities) within each state or jurisdiction that the individual identifies as a former residence and each place of work for the last 5 years.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>4.</num>
            <text>Record/Reference Check from Former Employer - Record check for former employer(s) for the last 5 years.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>5.</num>
            <text>Personal Reference Checks - At least three (3) reference contacts.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>6.</num>
            <text>Record Check of Former School - Verification of last degree.</text>
            <text>The minimum standards of character prescribed by federal law and this Policy shall ensure that none of the individuals appointed to positions in the programs described above have been found guilty of, or entered a plea of nolo contendere or guilty to, (1) any felonious offense, or any of two or more misdemeanor offenses, under Federal or  State law involving crimes of violence;, sexual assault, molestation, exploitation, contact or prostitution; (2) crimes against persons; or (3) offenses committed against children or elderly under Federal or State law. Any conviction in tribal court is not considered a felony.</text>
            <text>
              <u>Suitability Determinations</u>
            </text>
            <text>The Human Resources Director is the designated Suitability Official who determines suitability of prospective employees for employment and efficiency of service. The Pueblo may appoint one additional Suitability Official. The Suitability determination process protects the interests of the Pueblo and the rights of applicants and employees. The Suitability Determination Process requires uniform evaluation to ensure fair and consistent judgment.</text>
            <text>The Suitability Official is the designated representative for the Pueblo who directs proper background investigations and suitability determinations.  The Suitability Official must be qualified for the position and the responsibilities of his/her office and must have a favorable background investigation and suitability determination. The Suitability Official receives and is responsible for the results of the fingerprint checks and all other background investigations.  All precautions shall be taken to guarantee confidentiality.</text>
            <text>The Suitability Official should have a balanced, unbiased approach in the review of all investigations.  Potential conflicts of interest shall be avoided.  There are potential problems if the Suitability Official personally knows the subject of the investigation. Where a conflict of interest exists, the Tribal Administrator shall act as a temporary Suitability Official to conduct the background Investigation. A subordinate should not make a suitability determination for his/her immediate supervisor.</text>
            <text>The suitability determination process involves an assessment of past and present conduct that may indicate probable future actions with adverse impact on the efficiency of the interests of the Pueblo and which may violate Public Law 101-630, Indian Child Protection and Family Violence Prevention Act.</text>
            <text>
              <u>Criteria for Suitability Standards</u>
            </text>
            <text>The assessment of suitability is made to establish a reasonable expectation that the employment or continued employment of a person either would or would not promote the interests and the efficiency of the Pueblo. This determination is based on considerations of whether the conduct of the person indicates a potential for behavior which would interfere with, prevent, or otherwise impact adversely on (1) the performance of the person in the position applied for or employed in; (2) the accomplishment of the duties and responsibilities of others in the Pueblo; or (3) the ability of the Pueblo to fully and effectively carry out its mandated responsibilities.</text>
            <text>
              <u>Determination Factors for Suitability Standards</u>
            </text>
            <text>In determining potential impact on the efficiency of the service, two issues are considered:</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Whether the conduct in question indicates a potential for inadequate or reduced accomplishment of specific duties; and (2) whether the conduct indicates any immediate or long-term risk for abuse of trust in carrying out the responsibilities of the position. Conduct paralleling any of the following factors may be considered as a basis for disqualification:</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>a.</num>
            <text>Delinquency or misconduct in prior employment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>b.</num>
            <text>Criminal, dishonest, infamous or notoriously disgraceful conduct;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>c.</num>
            <text>Intentional false statement or deception or fraud in examination or appointment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>d.</num>
            <text>Habitual use of intoxicating beverages to excess; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>e.</num>
            <text>Abuse of narcotics, drugs, or other controlled substances.</text>
            <text>The Suitability Official shall consider the following additional factors to the extent that these factors are deemed pertinent to the individual case:</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>a.</num>
            <text>The kind of position for which the person is applying or in which the person is employed, including its trust risks;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>b.</num>
            <text>The nature and seriousness of the conduct;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>c.</num>
            <text>The circumstances surrounding the conduct;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>d.</num>
            <text>The recency of the conduct;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>e.</num>
            <text>The age of the applicant or employee at the time of the conduct;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>f.</num>
            <text>Contributing social or environmental conditions; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>g.</num>
            <text>The absence or presence of rehabilitation or efforts toward rehabilitation.</text>
            <text>The Suitability Official shall determine suitability and complete a Certificate of Investigation form identifying the written investigation reports and verbal references received and favorable determination of suitability.  The Suitability Official must obtain concurrence on a suitability decision from the Governor or Lt. Governor.  The Certificate of Investigation is signed and dated by the Suitability Official and the Governor or Lt. Governor and placed in the employee's personnel file.  The supporting documentation to the favorable determination can then be destroyed.  The appropriate personnel will be notified that the employee has been cleared.</text>
            <text>In cases in which the Suitability Official with the concurrence of the Governor or Lt. Governor determines that the individual does not meet the character requirements and is unacceptable for employment, appropriate personnel will be notified and all documents supporting this unacceptable determination will be kept in a secure locked file.</text>
            <text>In cases in which a former employee of the Pueblo requires a reference regarding new employment, such reference request must be submitted in writing to the Human Resources Department.  The response of the Human Resources Department shall be in writing and, except as otherwise required by law, will be limited to confirming only dates of employment, wage rates, and position(s) held. If a former employee would like the prospective employer to be provided with more information, that former employee must provide a written and signed authorization and release to their prior direct supervisor.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>205. Hiring of Relatives</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Although the Pueblo has no prohibition against hiring relatives of existing employees, we are committed to monitoring situations in which relatives work in the same area. The employment of relatives in the same area of an organization may cause serious conflicts and problems with favoritism and employee morale. In addition to claims of partiality in treatment at work, personal conflicts from outside the work environment can be carried into day-to-day working relationships.</text>
            <text>In case of actual or potential problems between or among relatives who work in the same area, the Pueblo may monitor the problem and may take prompt action to attempt to resolve the problem. This may include reassignment or, if necessary because no resolution is possible, one or both employees may be required to resign or be terminated.</text>
            <text>A "relative" as used in this Policy is any person who is related by blood or marriage in the immediate family or whose relationship with the employee is similar to that of persons who are related by blood or marriage. The term includes employees who become related after employment.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>EMPLOYMENT STATUS &amp; RECORDS</strong>
            </text>
            <text>
              <strong>301. Employment Categories</strong>
            </text>
            <text><strong>Regular Full-Time: </strong>Employees who are not in a Temporary or Probationary status and who are regularly scheduled to work the Pueblo's full-time schedule which, in general, is thirty-two (32) or more hours per week. Generally, regular full-time employees are eligible for the Pueblo de San Ildefonso's benefits.</text>
            <text><strong>Part-Time: </strong>Employees who are not assigned in a Temporary or Probationary status and who are regularly scheduled to work less than thirty-two (32) hours per week. Part-Time employees are generally ineligible for the Pueblo's benefits, unless otherwise expressly provided, in writing.</text>
            <text><strong>Contract: </strong>A contract employee is an individual who provides services as stipulated in a contract/subcontract agreement and is not eligible for the rights and benefits of Pueblo. All employee contracts shall be reviewed and approved by the Governor and Tribal Administrator.  All proper documentation shall be submitted to the Tribal Administrator including the contract and budget justification.</text>
            <text><strong>Probationary: </strong>Employees whose performance is being evaluated to determine whether further employment in a specific position with the Pueblo is appropriate. Employees who satisfactorily complete the probationary period of ninety (90) calendar days will be notified of their new employment classification. The probationary period may be extended to continue assessment of the employee's performance. The probationary period will be extended by the same amount of days that have been authorized and taken as leave during the probationary period as described in Section 303. The employee shall be terminated if job performance during the probationary period is not satisfactory. Probationary employees accrue annual and sick leave from the date of hire, however, use of such leave by probationary employees during the probationary period is not authorized except in extraordinary circumstances as determined by the immediate supervisor and the Tribal Administrator.</text>
            <text><strong>Temporary: </strong>Employees who are hired as interim replacements to temporarily supplement the work force, or to assist in the completion of a specific project or as an emergency hire. Employment assignments in this category are of a limited duration (90-Day or unless a waiver granted for the Governor for an extension). Employment beyond any initially stated period does not in any way imply a change in employment status. Temporary employees retain that status unless and until notified of a change. Temporary employees are ineligible for the Pueblo's benefits, unless otherwise expressly provided.</text>
            <text><strong>Exempt Employees</strong>:  Employees in positions classified in accordance with the Fair Labor Standards Act (FLSA is the acronym for Federal Labor Standards Act of 1938 as amended), are exempt and shall not be eligible for overtime pay because of supervisory, managerial, professional, or otherwise exercise independent judgment and discretion in the performance of their job duties.   Exempt employees will be compensated on the basis of an annual salary.  Overtime and Compensatory Time refer to Section 411.</text>
            <text><strong>Non-Exempt Employees: </strong>Employees in positions classified in accordance with the FLSA which are eligible for overtime pay at a rate of one and one-half times (1 1/2 ) their regular rate of pay for hours worked in excess of forty (40) hours per week. Nonexempt employees will be compensated on an hourly basis. For Overtime and Compensatory Time refer to Section 411.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>302. Job Descriptions</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Job descriptions shall be developed for each employee of the Pueblo. The employee shall be required to read their job description and shall acknowledge complete agreement with the stated responsibilities by signing the description.</text>
            <text>The job description shall be a part of the employee's personnel file.</text>
            <text><strong>303</strong>. <strong>Probationary Period</strong></text>
            <text>The probationary period is intended to give new employees the opportunity to demonstrate their ability to achieve a satisfactory level of performance and to determine whether the new position meets their expectations. The Pueblo de San Ildefonso uses this period to evaluate employees' capabilities, work habits, and overall performance. All new, transferred and rehired employees work on a probationary basis for the first ninety (90) calendar days after their date of hire or transfer.</text>
            <text>A probationary employee may be terminated or transferred at will during the probationary period when his or her abilities or performance are judged insufficient by the immediate supervisor. Transferred employees may be reinstated to their former positions, or an equivalent position they are qualified for, provided such a position is available.</text>
            <text>New employees are not eligible to receive benefits within the probationary period. New employees will accrue annual and sick leave from the date of hire but are generally not eligible to use or be paid for such leave during the probationary period except in extraordinary circumstances as determined by the immediate supervisor and Tribal Administrator.</text>
            <text>Upon satisfactory completion of the probationary period, the probationary employee shall become either a Regular Full-Time or Regular Part-Time employee. However, successful completion of the probationary period does not modify or change the employee's "at-will" status and does not entitle an employee to an automatic increase in pay for the change to a "regular employee" status.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>304. Performance Evaluation</strong>
            </text>
            <text>A formal written performance evaluation will be conducted at the end of an employee's initial period of hire, known as the probationary period. Additional formal performance evaluations are conducted to provide both Directors and employees the opportunity to discuss job tasks, identify and correct weaknesses, encourage and recognize strengths, and discuss positive, purposeful approaches for meeting goals. This clause applies to new hires, rehires and transferred employees.</text>
            <text>The Tribal Administrator and Governor will evaluate the Directors. The Governor and Tribal Council will evaluate the Tribal Administrator.</text>
            <text>Directors and supervisors will conduct performance evaluations of all their employees on a 12-month cycle, beginning at the employee's date of hire.</text>
            <text>At the discretion of the Director or Tribal Administrator, evaluations may be conducted on a more frequent basis.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>305. Personal Data Changes</strong>
            </text>
            <text>It is the responsibility of each employee to promptly notify the Pueblo of any changes in personal data. Names, personal mailing addresses, telephone numbers, number and names of dependents, individuals to be contacted in the event of emergency, educational accomplishments, and other such status reports should be accurate and current at all times. If any personal data has changed, notify the Human Resources Department.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>306. Access to Personnel Files</strong>
            </text>
            <text>The Pueblo maintains a personnel file on each employee. The personnel file includes the employee's job application, resume, job description, records of training, documentation of performance appraisals and salary increases, disciplinary action and other employment records.</text>
            <text>Personnel files are the property of the Pueblo, and access to the information they contain is restricted to the employee, the employee's Director and/or Supervisor, and Administrative Management personnel of the Pueblo with a legitimate reason to review information in an employee's file.</text>
            <text>Employees may review their own personnel files, with advance notice, in the presence of the Human Resources Director.   Employees will be notified of any request by an outside agency to view their personnel file.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>EMPLOYEE BENEFITS</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Eligible employees are provided benefits by the Pueblo for the welfare of employees and these benefits are not to be abused. Employees with questions about any of the benefits provided by the Pueblo should ask their Director or the Human Resources Director.</text>
            <text>In case of a conflict between any benefit described in this Policy or in a specific plan, summary plan description, or other legal document, the language of the specific plan, shall prevail, unless otherwise expressly stated in writing.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>401. Annual Leave</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Annual leave with pay is available to eligible employees to provide opportunities for rest, relaxation, and personal pursuits. Annual Leave is <strong>scheduled </strong>leave that is provided to Regular Full-Time Employees upon successful completion of the probationary period.</text>
            <text>Employees who have worked for the Pueblo for less than three (3) years shall receive fourteen days Annual Leave per year. Employees who have worked for the Pueblo for between three (3) to seven (7) years shall receive sixteen (16) days annual leave per year. Employees who have worked for the Pueblo for more than seven (7) years shall receive eighteen (18) days annual leave per year. Employees may take their Annual Leave at any time during the year with prior approval from their Director.</text>
            <text>Accrual of Annual Leave shall end on December 31, 2008 and shall not be carried over from year to year beginning January 1, 2009. Annual leave accrued through 2008 will be paid out if not used by February 28, 2009. For the year 2009, Annual Leave will be budgeted for Employees in the full annual amount stated above starting on March 1, 2009. Starting in 2010, Annual Leave will be budgeted in the full annual amounted stated above to eligible employees on January 1, 2010 and on January 1<sup>st</sup> of each year thereafter. Employees hired after January 1 in any year will have Annual Leave budgeted in an amount pro-rated to the nearest month of employment remaining for that year and whole day of leave, as determined by the Tribal Administrator.</text>
            <text>For Annual Leave which requires more than five (5) consecutive days of leave, the employee should submit an Annual Leave request no later than one week prior to the scheduled dates and obtain prior approval from their Director. A request for annual leave will be granted at the discretion of the supervisor and/or Director.</text>
            <text>Any Annual Leave unused at the end of employment will not be paid.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>402. Sick Leave</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Sick Leave can be <strong>scheduled </strong>or <strong>unscheduled </strong>leave that is provided to Regular Full-Time employees. Sick Leave is provided to employees after successful completion of the probationary period.</text>
            <text>As of March 1, 2009 for 2009, and on January 1 of each year starting with 2010, each employee is entitled to twelve (12) days of sick leave each year. Sick Leave may be authorized when an employee is incapacitated by sickness or injury; for medical, dental, or optical diagnosis or treatment; when the Employee's attendance jeopardizes the health of others; or for the care of immediate family members in the event of serious illness. Employees hired after January 1 in any year will have Sick Leave in an amount pro-rated to the nearest month of employment remaining for that year and whole day of leave, as determined by the Tribal Administrator.</text>
            <text>Employees must notify their director as soon as possible if they will miss work due to sickness, but no later than the beginning of the scheduled work day. Requests for sick leave can be made in advance if known (scheduled), but must be submitted within one day after returning to work after sick leave has been used (unscheduled). A physician's verification may be required at any time a director feels that sick leave is being abused.</text>
            <text>Upon separation of employment with the Pueblo, any unused Sick Leave will not be paid.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>403. Bereavement Leave</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Employees who must take time off due to the death of an immediate family member must notify their Director immediately. A Regular Full-Time employee will be paid for up to four (4) days of Bereavement Leave per year.</text>
            <text>Annual or Sick Leave may be used for time off work for bereavement in all other instances. Administrative leave may be granted at the sole discretion of the Governor.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>404. Family and Medical Leave Of Absence</strong>
            </text>
            <text>In accordance with the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993, the Pueblo provides family leave of absence, without pay, to eligible employees for birth or adoption or foster placement of a child, serious health conditions of a child, the serious health condition of a parent or spouse, or the employee's own serious health condition.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>General Guidelines</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>Employees may be eligible to take an unpaid family or medical leave of up to a total of 12 workweeks in any 12-month period for the following reasons, as defined by the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993:</text>
            <text>The birth of a child of an employee or the placement of a child with the 	employee for adoption or foster care. Entitlement to leave for the birth or placement 	of a child for adoption or foster care expires 12 months from the date of birth or 	placement of the child.</text>
            <text>To care for a spouse, child or parent who has a serious health condition.</text>
            <text>Because of a serious health condition of the employee.</text>
            <text>In cases where both spouses are employed by the Pueblo, the combined period of their family and medical leave will be limited to 12 workweeks in any 12-month period, for birth or adoption of a child. In all other instances, including covered health conditions of the employee or the employee's spouse, parent or child, each spouse is entitled to his or her own full 12 weeks of family leave.</text>
            <text>The amount of leave that an employee is entitled to at any given time will be determined on a rolling 12-month period, measured backward from the date an employee uses any leave, as defined under the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993.</text>
            <text>All employees are required to designate brief absences as FMLA leave within two (2) days following their return from leave if the Pueblo has not previously designated this absence as FMLA leave. If an employee fails to designate the leave at that time, they may not be able to qualify that absence as FMLA leave at a later date.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Employee Eligibility</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>To be eligible for unpaid family and medical leave, an employee must be qualified under the terms of the Family and Medical Leave Act, meaning, the employee must:</text>
            <text>
              <ul>
                <li>Have worked for the Pueblo at least 12 months.</li>
                <li>Have at least 1250 hours of service during the 12-month period prior to the leave.</li>
              </ul>
            </text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Benefits While On Leave</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>During an approved family and medical leave, an employee is entitled to receive health benefits at the same level and terms of coverage as if they had been working throughout the leave.</text>
            <text>An employee is not entitled to the accrual of any seniority or leave benefits that would have accrued if not for the taking of leave. Annual leave and sick leave will be suspended during the leave period and will resume upon return to active employment. An employee who takes family or medical leave will not lose any seniority or leave benefits that accrued before the date leave began.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Restoration Of Employment After Leave</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>The Pueblo will reinstate an employee returning from family and medical leave to the same or to an equivalent position with equivalent pay, benefits, and other terms and conditions of employment. However, an employee on leave does not have a greater right to reinstatement or to other benefits and conditions of employment than if the employee had been continuously employed during the leave period. An employee may be requested to submit a physician's release to return to work if leave was for his or her own health condition.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Status Reports While On Leave</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>Employees on family leave may be required, on a periodic basis, to report their status and intent to return, to designated Pueblo representatives.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Substitution of Accrued/Earned Time Off</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>The Pueblo requires employees to first substitute all accrued/earned Annual Leave and Sick Leave as part or all of the 12 work week period. After all paid leave has been exhausted; any time remaining in the 12 work week period must be taken without pay.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Care for a Child After Childbirth or Adoption or Foster Care Placement</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>Scheduling/Notice: Family leaves taken for childbirth or adoption or foster care placement must be taken within 12 months of the birth or the adoption or foster care placement.</text>
            <text>Employees must notify Pueblo thirty (30) days in advance or give as much advance notice as is practical depending upon conditions.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Care for Spouse, Child_ or Parent or Employee's Own Serious Health Condition</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>Scheduling/Notice: An employee requesting family leave due to their own serious health condition or for the serious health condition of their spouse, child, or parent, must notify both their Director and the Tribal Administrator thirty (30) days in advance or give as much advance notice as is practical depending on conditions.</text>
            <text>Certification: The Pueblo requires a written explanation from the covered family member's physician or the employee's physician of the need for family leave, in both the case of an employee's own serious health condition and that of a covered family member. The Pueblo of San Ildefonso will require written approval from the employee's treating physician of fitness to return to work for an employee's own serious health condition.</text>
            <text>The Pueblo reserves the right to review all information about medical certifications in accordance with the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Full Time versus Intermittent Leave</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>Employees may request intermittent or reduced leave schedules. If the necessity for the leave is foreseeable based on planned medical treatment, employees must make a reasonable effort to schedule the treatment so as not to disrupt the operations of the Pueblo. In addition, the employee shall provide as much notice of the request to take such leave as practicably possible.</text>
            <text>The Pueblo requires employees to provide a written explanation from the employee's physician of the dates and duration of the expected treatment, as well as the medical necessity for intermittent or reduced leave schedule.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Temporary Transfers</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>An employee who requests such an intermittent or reduced leave schedule may be temporarily transferred to an alternative position, if such a position is available, having equivalent pay and benefits that the employee is qualified for and that better accommodates recurring periods of leave, as determined by Pueblo.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>405. Other Unpaid Personal Leave Of Absence</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Unpaid personal leaves of absence may be granted for reasons other than those specified in this Policy. Any employee who wants a personal leave of absence must place such request in writing, including the reason and duration of such leave, and submit that request to the Director/Tribal Administrator. The Tribal Administrator and the Governor, within their sole discretion, will make a determination on the request jointly. In making that decision, the needs and concern of the employee are balanced with the demands of the Pueblo. In some cases, the Pueblo may grant a leave for a lesser period of time than that requested by the employee. All accrued/earned leave must be exhausted before a personal leave of absence will be granted.</text>
            <text>At the time such leave is granted, the Pueblo will inform the employee whether they are to be reinstated to their regular position. If during such a leave of absence, it is necessary to fill the position of the employee on leave, that employee will be so informed and will have the option of immediately returning to work in the position held prior to the leave, or in a different capacity as determined by the Pueblo.</text>
            <text>Benefit accruals such as annual leave and sick leave will be suspended during the leave period and will resume upon return to active employment.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>406. Holidays</strong>
            </text>
            <text>The Pueblo will grant paid time off to all employees on the holidays listed below:</text>
            <text>
              <ul>
                <li>New Year's Day (January 1)</li>
                <li>King's Day (January 6)</li>
                <li>Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.'s Birthday</li>
                <li>Pueblo de San Ildefonso Feast Eve (January 22)</li>
                <li>Pueblo de San Ildefonso Feast Day (January 23)</li>
                <li>President's Day (February)</li>
                <li>Good Friday (Friday before Easter)</li>
                <li>Memorial Day (last Monday in May)</li>
                <li>Independence Day (4<sup>a</sup>' of July)</li>
                <li>Pop Day (August 10)</li>
                <li>Labor Day (first Monday in September)</li>
                <li>Veteran's Day (November 11)</li>
                <li>Thanksgiving Day (fourth Thursday in November)</li>
                <li>Day after Thanksgiving</li>
                <li>Christmas Eve (December 24)</li>
                <li>Christmas Day (December 25)</li>
                <li>New Year's Eve (December 31)</li>
              </ul>
            </text>
            <text>If a recognized holiday falls during an eligible employee's paid absence (such as when the employee is on Annual Leave or Sick Leave), holiday pay will be provided instead of the paid time off benefit that would otherwise have applied. If holiday falls on an employee's mandatory workday, employee will take the holiday the next working day.</text>
            <text>A holiday which falls on a Saturday will be observed on the preceding Friday. A holiday which falls on a Sunday will be observed on the following Monday.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>407. Military Leave</strong>
            </text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Annual Military Reserve Leave</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>Employees who have a military, service obligation requiring participation of up to two weeks of reserve camp annually will be granted a leave of absence from the Pueblo. Such an employee may elect to charge such absence against his or her accrued Annual Leave or other paid time off provided that advance notice is given to the employee's Director and to the Tribal Administrator. If the employee does not choose to use such Annual Leave or other paid time off, the Pueblo will pay the employee the amount of his or her salary, from which shall be deducted all amounts received from the military service (i.e. base pay plus bonus for flying time, demolition service, etc., but not including allowances for travel, clothing, rent, subsistence, etc.).</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Service in the Uniformed Services</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>Employees who serve in the uniformed services shall be provided leave and benefits in accordance with Vietnam Era Veterans' Readjustment Assistance Act ("VEVRA").</text>
            <text>
              <strong>408. Time Off To Vote</strong>
            </text>
            <text>The Pueblo encourages employees to fulfill their civic responsibilities by participating in elections. Generally, employees are expected to find time to vote either before or after their regular work schedule. If employees are unable to vote in an election during their non-working hours, the Pueblo will grant up to two (2) hours of paid time off to vote.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>409. Jury Duty</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Any time served by an employee in connection with jury duty will be considered time worked and the Pueblo will pay the employee his or her regular salary during the time of such service. Any amount received by the employee for jury duty, exclusive of mileage, will be turned over to the Accounting Department. As an alternative, the employee may request Annual Leave for these days and keep jury duty pay. Proof of service will be required.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>410. Overtime and Compensatory Time</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Non-exempt employees may be required to work overtime. Such overtime will be assigned as needed and at the discretion of their Director. To the extent possible, the Director will give notice of overtime work. Exempt employees are not eligible for overtime compensation. Non-exempt and Exempt employees are defined as such in Section 301.</text>
            <text>A non-exempt employee will be paid at a rate of one and one-half times their regular hourly rate of pay for all actual time worked in excess of forty (40) hours in any one workweek with their Director's approval. At the Director's discretion, an employee may earn compensatory time at the rate of 1  hours per hour worked in lieu of overtime pay. Compensatory time must be used within 10 working days of the date compensatory time occurred.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>411. Administrative Leave of Absence</strong>
            </text>
            <text>In appropriate circumstances, as determined within the sole discretion of the Governor, paid Administrative Leave of absence may be granted to employees. Examples of administrative leave granted to all employees include instances of inclement weather, or traditional activities. Other situations not specifically identified in this section may also qualify for administrative leave.</text>
            <text>Individual employees may also request administrative leave for traditional, religious or cultural activities. Upon receipt of a written request for administrative leave for traditional, religious or cultural activities, the Governor, in his sole discretion, may grant paid administrative leave for a total of up to ten (10) days annually. Additional time may be granted at the Governor's discretion. Administrative leave for traditional, religious or cultural activities cannot be accumulated and carried over from year to year.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>412. Donation of Sick Leave</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Employees may donate sick leave to other tribal employees funding program when unique circumstances exist. Any employee wishing to ask for donations of leave from other employees must place such a request in writing to the Governor for approval, including the reason for the donation request. Donated leave shall be considered as Sick Leave for the recipient employee and shall only be used for medical or health reasons and is subject to the same restrictions as all other sick leave. All other forms of leave must be exhausted or nearly exhausted before a request for donation of sick leave will be granted.</text>
            <text>Donated sick leave will first be donated within the department then within funds (General, Federal and Enterprise Funds), sick leave will then be calculated at the donors hours and rate converted to the users rate to calculate the hours.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>ATTENDANCE</strong>
            </text>
            <text>In order to fulfill its obligations to the community and to be fair to one another, the Pueblo must rely on a staff of dependable employees. Employees are expected to work as scheduled and to minimize unscheduled absences and lateness. While it is recognized that absences will occur for any number of valid reasons, it is the expectation of the Pueblo that employees be responsible about their jobs and that they maintain an excellent attendance record.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>501. Definitions</strong>
            </text>
            <text><strong>"Absence" - </strong>Any <strong>unapproved absence </strong>time lost from work regardless of reason, including Sick Leave. Excluding annual leave, holidays, medical leave, jury duty and other absences, which have been approved in advance. Absences are measured daily from the first occurrence and continuously thereafter. Days or parts of days of absence, whether successive or scattered in occurrence, are counted separately, e.g., three (3) successive days of absence are equal to three absences.</text>
            <text><strong>"Lateness"</strong> - The late arrival or early departure from the workstation at any time during an employee's regularly assigned schedule. Lateness is measured from the first occurrence and continuously thereafter. EXCEPTION: If lateness is due to problems with transportation, weather emergencies and the like, and at the discretion of the employee's supervisor, the employee may make up the lost time during the day. In such cases, the lateness will be deleted from the employee's record.</text>
            <text><strong>"Excessive Lost Time" - </strong>An emerging pattern of absenteeism and/or lateness. An employee may be terminated for excessive episodes of absence or lateness.</text>
            <text><strong>"Scheduled Time Off" - </strong>Leave or time off that is approved in advance, including:</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>Annual Leave</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text>Jury Duty</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>3.</num>
            <text>Bereavement Leave</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>4.</num>
            <text>Medical Leave/FMLA</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>5.</num>
            <text>Military, Reserve and National Guard Training Leave</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>6.</num>
            <text>Administrative Leave</text>
            <text>
              <strong>502. Timekeeping and Documenting</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Accurately recording time worked is the responsibility of every employee. Federal laws require the Pueblo to keep an accurate record of time worked in order to calculate employee pay and benefits. Time worked is the time actually spent on the job performing assigned duties.</text>
            <text>Altering, falsifying, tampering with timesheets, or recording time on another employee's timesheet may result in disciplinary action including termination of employment.</text>
            <text>It is the employees' responsibility to sign their timesheets to certify the accuracy of all time recorded. The Director will review and sign the timesheet before submitting it for payroll processing.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>503. Work Schedules</strong>
            </text>
            <text>The normal work schedule for all Regular Full-Time employees is eight (8) hours a day, five (5) days a week. Monday through Friday, 8 A.M. to 5 P.M. with a one (1) hour lunch break. Staffing needs and operational demands may necessitate variations in starting and ending times, as well as variations in the total hours that may be scheduled each day and week. Scheduling is at the discretion of the Governor and may be changed at any time to suit the requirements of the Pueblo.</text>
            <text>Employees shall have the privilege of two breaks per day with a one-hour lunch break, except where the press of business makes such breaks inappropriate. One fifteen (15) minute break shall be taken in the morning and one fifteen (15) minute break in the afternoon.</text>
            <text>Flexible scheduling, or flextime, is available in some cases to allow employees to vary their starting and ending times each day within established limits. Flextime may be possible if a mutually workable schedule can be negotiated with the Director involved. However, such issues as staffing needs, the employee's performance, and the nature of the job will be considered before approval of flextime.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>504. Separation from Employment</strong>
            </text>
            <text>The Pueblo will implement the separation of employees from employment as appropriate and necessary. All those concerned will treat any separation from employment in a professional and confidential manner.</text>
            <text>Separation from employment is normally implemented by one of the following actions and shall be done in accordance with the stated policies and procedures:</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Voluntary Separation</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text><u>Resignation:</u> This is a voluntary separation of employment initiated by the employee. An employee wishing to terminate employment in good standing is expected to give as much advance notice as possible. Two (2) weeks or ten (10) working days is generally considered sufficient notice time. A voluntary resignation should be done in writing by the employee and confirmed in writing by the supervisor/director. A confirmed resignation may be withdrawn by written request of the employee and at the sole discretion and written approval of the Governor.</text>
            <text>An employee absent from work without authorization or without notifying their supervisor for three (3) consecutive days, may be deemed to have effected a voluntary "no call/no show" resignation.</text>
            <text>An employee, who voluntarily resigns from employment, shall be entitled to receive all earned wages subject to deductions for any indebtedness or unreturned property. Payment for earned hours shall be processed as quickly as possible within two weeks after the date of resignation but is subject to the following time constraints: verification of time worked, return of equipment, calculation of any costs owed to the Pueblo by the employee, and other indebtedness.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Involuntary Separation</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text><u>Discharge:</u> This is defined as an involuntary termination of employment from the Pueblo for substandard performance, or misconduct, or at any time during the probationary period. Employees may be terminated in accordance with their at-will employment status. An employee may be discharged when in the judgment of the administration the seriousness of the matter is such that the employee cannot be permitted to remain on the workforce.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>a.</num>
            <heading>Substandard Performance:</heading>
            <text>An employee may be discharged from employment if their 	performance is unacceptable. It is important for Directors and supervisors to identify 	potential performance deficiencies or problems as early as possible and take prompt 	measures in an attempt to correct the situation in consultation with the Tribal 	Administrator to avoid termination. However, this process may not apply for a 	discharge of an employee during the probationary period. Before discharging any 	employee, a supervisor must consult with the Tribal Administrator and Governor 	who must concur in advance of notifying the employee of discharge action.</text>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <heading>Misconduct:</heading>
              <text>The Pueblo reserves the right to either 1) suspend or terminate an 	employee immediately upon the occurrence of misconduct or 2) subject the</text>
              <text>employee to	its progressive discipline policy to be engaged in activities such as, 	but not limited to, theft of the Pueblo tribal property or the property of another 	employee, insubordination, assault, harassment (see Section 606) or any other 	activities showing willful disregard of the Pueblo interests or policies. It is 	important for Directors and supervisors to identify potential performance 	deficiencies or problems as early as possible and take prompt measures in an 	attempt to correct the situation in consultation with the Tribal Administrator.</text>
              <text>If a possibility of continuing misconduct requires that action be taken before consultation 	with the Tribal Administrator and Governor can take place or if the misconduct is so 	serious, a Director may suspend the employee temporarily. Pending the results of further 	review and investigation by the Tribal Administrator and Governor, the suspension may 	be with or without pay. Refer to Section 704 (3)</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>c.</num>
              <heading>Discharge during the Probationary Period:</heading>
              <text>The probationary period is a period of 	service during which Pueblo assesses the performance of an employee to determine 	whether the employee satisfactorily meets the requirements of the position. The 	termination of a probationary employee during the probationary period may be 	without cause but requires the approval of the appropriate Director, Tribal 	Administrator</text>
              <text>or the Governor.</text>
              <text>A probationary employee who is discharged during the probationary period shall only be entitled to pay for any hours worked.</text>
              <text>An employee who is involuntarily separated from employment shall be entitled to receive all earned pay subject to deductions for any indebtedness or unreturned property. Payment for earned hours shall be processed as quickly as possible after the date of termination but is subject to the following time constraints: verification of time worked, return of equipment, calculation of any costs owed to the Pueblo by the employee, other indebtedness, completion of specific projects, etc.</text>
              <text>
                <strong>505. Return of Property</strong>
              </text>
              <text>Employees are responsible for items issued to them by the Pueblo or in their possession or control, including but not limited to the following:</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>1.</num>
              <text>Credit cards</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>2.</num>
              <text>Equipment</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>3.</num>
              <text>Identification badges</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>4.</num>
              <text>Keys</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>5.</num>
              <text>Manuals</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>6.</num>
              <text>Cellular Telephones</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>7.</num>
              <text>Pagers</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>8.</num>
              <text>Tools</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>9.</num>
              <text>Uniforms</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>10.</num>
              <text>Vehicles</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>11.</num>
              <text>PC/Lap Top Computer</text>
              <text>Employees must return all Pueblo property on or before their last day of work to their supervisor or the Human Resources Department. The Pueblo may withhold from the employee's check or final paycheck the cost of any items that are not returned when required. The Pueblo may also take all action deemed appropriate to recover or protect its property.</text>
              <text>
                <strong>SPECIAL WORK PLACE POLICIES</strong>
              </text>
              <text>
                <strong>601. Use of Phone and Mail Systems</strong>
              </text>
              <text>Employees may be required to reimburse the Pueblo for any charges resulting from their personal use of any Pueblo-owned telephones, including cellular phones.</text>
              <text>The use of the Pueblo paid postage for personal correspondence is not permitted.</text>
              <text>
                <strong>602. No Smoking Policy</strong>
              </text>
              <text>In keeping with the Pueblo intent to provide a safe and healthy work environment, smoking in the workplace is prohibited and permitted only in designated areas. This policy applies equally to all employees, community members, and visitors.</text>
              <text>
                <strong>603. Use of Equipment and Vehicles</strong>
              </text>
              <text>Equipment and vehicles essential in accomplishing job duties are expensive and may be difficult to replace. When using Pueblo property, employees are expected to exercise care, perform required maintenance, and follow all operating instructions, safety standards, and guidelines. Only authorized personnel may use equipment and vehicles. Employees' must be insurable and may require certification or training.</text>
              <text>The Director should be notified if any equipment, machines, tools, or vehicles appear to be damaged, defective, or in need of repair. Prompt reporting of damages, defects, and the need for repairs could prevent deterioration of equipment and possible injury to employees or others.</text>
              <text>The improper, careless, negligent, destructive, or unsafe use or operation of equipment or vehicles, as well as excessive or avoidable traffic and parking violations, can result in disciplinary action, up to and including termination of employment. Employees are required to notify their supervisor if their driver's license becomes invalid for any reason if the operation of a motor vehicle is an integral or required part of the employee's job duties.</text>
              <text>For specific information and detailed guidelines, please refer to the Tribal Vehicle Use Policy.</text>
              <text>
                <strong>604. Visitors in the Workplace</strong>
              </text>
              <text>To provide for the safety and security of employees and the facilities at the Pueblo, only authorized visitors are allowed in the workplace. Restricting unauthorized visitors helps maintain safety standards, protects against theft, ensures security of equipment, protects confidential information, safeguards employee welfare, and avoids potential distractions and disturbances.</text>
              <text>Employees are responsible for the conduct and safety of their visitors.  If an unauthorized individual is observed on the Pueblo's premises, employees should immediately notify the Administrative Receptionist or, if necessary, direct the individual to the reception area.</text>
              <text>
                <strong>605. Use of Information Systems and Networks</strong>
              </text>
              <text>The Pueblo's information systems (IS) - networks, software, and computers - are valuable company assets, provided to employees as tools to function competitively in our business. Limited non-business use of them is permissible when it does not interfere with business use of the systems and is consistent with job responsibilities, other Pueblo policies, ethical considerations and all applicable laws. Employees must understand that such non-business use creates no privacy right for any data stored on Pueblo information systems or any data sent over Pueblo networks.</text>
              <text>The Pueblo reserves the right to access, review, and exclude material transmitted over or stored in these systems and networks and may terminate any activity related to its systems and networks which is believed to be inappropriate or in violation of policies. Failure to adhere to these requirements may result in the employee's restriction or prohibition from use of Pueblo information systems and networks.</text>
              <text>Any employee determined by the Pueblo to have misused the technology, and supervisors who have failed to control the use of these resources appropriately, may be subject to appropriate disciplinary action, up to and including termination.</text>
              <text>As used in this Policy, "systems" includes the use of all Pueblo owned or controlled resources to access both internal and external networks and systems. Systems may be any combination of computers, software, accessories, utilities and storage devices and media. Networks refer to any system for the transport of data, video, or voice.</text>
              <text>Following are examples of inappropriate uses of Pueblo information systems and networks:</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>Any use violating law or government regulation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text>Forwarding or permitting unauthorized access to proprietary or confidential Pueblo information;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>3.</num>
            <text>Use promoting disrespect for an individual, discrimination, or constituting a personal attack, including ethnic jokes or slurs;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>4.</num>
            <text>Viewing, copying, or transmitting material with sexual content, harassing or soliciting messages or chain letters, including "charitable" chain letters;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>5.</num>
            <text>Defamatory, inflammatory or derogatory statements about individuals, companies or their products;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>6.</num>
            <text>Disclosing private facts about an individual;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>7.</num>
            <text>Posting third-party proprietary information in a non-restricted environment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>8.</num>
            <text>Using copyrighted material without legal right;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>9.</num>
            <text>Permitting or obtaining unauthorized access to any systems or networks;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>10.</num>
            <text>Use for personal financial gain or in a manner creating a potential conflict of interest for Pueblo of San Ildefonso;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>11.</num>
            <text>Forwarding communications of a third party without permission or without the original header.</text>
            <text>Employees are accountable for use of Pueblo information systems and networks in accordance with these policies, and should request clarification from Directors or systems managers to ensure their understanding of any possible improper use, and should report all potential misuse to their Directors.</text>
            <text>Directors are responsible for the correct use of Pueblo assets, and must take steps to ensure that systems they manage are operated in support of Pueblo business. Directors are expected to communicate policies in a manner that ensures employees understand proper and improper use, should hold employees accountable, and should periodically monitor resources under their control for use in accordance with this policy.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>606. Workplace Safety</strong>
            </text>
            <text>Directors are responsible for maintaining a safe and healthy work environment for their staff. Given the increasing violence in society in general, the Pueblo has adopted the following guidelines to deal with intimidation, harassment, threats of, or actual, violence that may occur during business hours or on its premises.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Zero-Tolerance</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>The Pueblo maintains a zero-tolerance policy regarding all workplace violence. Violence will result in immediate discharge.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Definition of Workplace Safety</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <text>The word "violence" in this policy shall mean an act or behavior that:</text>
            <para>
              <num>1.</num>
              <text>is an actual physical assault;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>2.</num>
              <text>A reasonable person would perceive as obsessively directed, e.g., intensely focused on a 	grudge, grievance, or romantic interest in another person, and reasonably likely to 	result in harm or threats of harm to persons or property;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>3.</num>
              <text>Consists of a communicated or reasonably perceived threat to harm another individual 	or in any way endanger the safety of an individual;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>4.</num>
              <text>Would be interpreted by a reasonable person as carrying potential for physical harm 	to the individual;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>5.</num>
              <text>Is a behavior, or action, that a reasonable person would perceive as menacing;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>6.</num>
              <text>Involves carrying or displaying weapons, destroying property, or throwing objects in a 	manner reasonably perceived to be threatening; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>7.</num>
              <text>Consists of a communicated or reasonably perceived threat to destroy property.</text>
              <text>Violent actions on Pueblo property or facilities, or while on Pueblo business, will not be tolerated or ignored; the Pueblo intends to use reasonable legal, managerial, administrative, and disciplinary procedures to secure the workplace from violence and to reasonably protect employees and members of the public.</text>
              <text>All employees, and everyone on Pueblo property, should be treated with courtesy and respect at all times. Employees are expected to refrain from fighting, "horseplay," or other conduct that may be dangerous to others. Firearms, weapons, and other dangerous or hazardous devices or substances are prohibited from the premises of the Pueblo without proper authorization.</text>
              <text>Conduct that threatens, intimidates, or coerces another employee, a client, or a member of the public at any time, including off-duty periods, will not be tolerated. This prohibition includes all acts of harassment, including harassment that is based on an individual's sex, race, age, or any characteristic protected by federal law.</text>
              <text>All threats of, or actual, violence, both direct and indirect, must be reported as soon as possible to your immediate Director or any other member of management. This includes threats by employees, as well as threats by community members, vendors, solicitors, or other members of the public. When reporting a threat of violence, you should be as specific and detailed as possible.</text>
              <text>The Pueblo will promptly and thoroughly investigate all reports of threats and/or actual violence and suspicious individuals or activities. The identity of the individual making a report will be protected as much as is practical. In order to maintain workplace safety and the integrity of its investigation, the Pueblo may suspend employees, either with or without pay, pending investigation.</text>
              <text>Anyone determined to be responsible for threats of, or actual violence or other conduct that is in violation of these guidelines will be subject to prompt disciplinary action, including termination of employment.</text>
              <text>The Pueblo encourages employees to bring their disputes or differences with other employees to the attention of their Directors or the Human Resources Department. If the matter cannot be resolved, then the Director and employee together should bring the matter to the attention of the Tribal Administrator. Thereafter, within the discretion of the Tribal Administrator, the matter may be brought to the attention of the Governor. The Pueblo is eager to assist in the resolution of employee disputes, and will not discipline employees for raising such concerns.</text>
              <text>
                <strong>EMPLOYEE CONDUCT &amp; DISCIPLINARY ACTION</strong>
              </text>
              <text>
                <strong>701. Employee Conduct and Work Rules</strong>
              </text>
              <text>To ensure orderly operations and provide the best possible work environment, the Pueblo of San Ildefonso expects employees to follow rules of conduct that will protect the interests and safety of all employees and the organization.</text>
              <text>It is not possible to list all the forms of behavior that are considered unacceptable in the workplace. The following is a representative list of infractions of rules of conduct that may result in disciplinary action, including immediate termination of employment:</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>Theft or inappropriate removal or possession of property.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text>Falsification of timekeeping records or any other administrative form.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>3.</num>
            <text>No employee shall have the right to speak for, or on behalf of the Pueblo without the express prior approval of the Governor. If and when an employee is properly delegated to speak for, or on behalf of the Pueblo, they are required to be accurate and exercise restraint.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>4.</num>
            <text>Working under the influence of alcohol or illegal drugs.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>5.</num>
            <text>Possession, distribution, sale, transfer, or use of alcohol or illegal drugs in the workplace, while on duty, or while operating employer-owned vehicles or equipment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>6.</num>
            <text>Fighting or threatening violence in the workplace.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>7.</num>
            <text>Boisterous or disruptive activity in the workplace.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>8.</num>
            <text>Negligence or improper conduct leading to damage of property.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>9.</num>
            <text>Insubordination, intentional refusal to follow an authorized supervisor's reasonable orders, or other disrespectful conduct.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>10.</num>
            <text>Violation of safety or health rules.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>11.</num>
            <text>Sexual or other unlawful or unwelcome harassment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>12.</num>
            <text>Possession of dangerous or unauthorized materials, such as explosives or firearms, in the workplace.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>13.</num>
            <text>Excessive absenteeism or any absence without notice.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>14.</num>
            <text>Excessive tardiness.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>15.</num>
            <text>Unauthorized absence from workstation during workday.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>16.</num>
            <text>Unauthorized use of information systems, telephones, the mail system, or other employer-owned equipment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>17.</num>
            <text>Unauthorized disclosure of confidential information.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>18.</num>
            <text>Violation of personnel policies.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>19.</num>
            <text>Unsatisfactory work performance or conduct.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>702. Drug and Alcohol Policy</strong>
            </text>
            <text>The Pueblo views drug and alcohol abuse with grave concern. The Pueblo's position in its community and its service to and reputation with the public cannot be compromised by the adverse effect of drug and alcohol abuse on the performance and judgment of its personnel.  The Pueblo also recognizes the significant human and business costs arising from the damaging effects of drug and alcohol use.</text>
            <text><u>COMPREHENSIVE SUBSTANCE ABUSE PROGRAM</u> (five steps)</text>
            <text>Dealing with Substance Abuse</text>
            <text>San IIdefonso Pueblo is a business. We are in the business of providing educational, employment and social services to Native Americans. The Pueblo must send a clear signal to present and future employees that we are committed to maintaining a drug and alcohol free workplace.</text>
            <text>The Pueblo's comprehensive Workplace Substance Abuse Program entails a five step process which includes the following components:</text>
            <para>
              <num>1.</num>
              <text>A written substance abuse policy</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>2.</num>
              <text>An employee education and awareness program</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>3.</num>
              <text>A supervisory training program</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>4.</num>
              <text>Access to an employee assistance program  (EAP)</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>5.</num>
              <text>A drug testing program</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <text>
            <u>POLICY ON SUBSTANCE ABUSE</u>
            <strong> (step 1)</strong>
          </text>
          <text>Statement of  Need</text>
          <text>The Pueblo has a strong commitment to the health, safety, and welfare of its employees, their families, and its constituents. Widely available statistics and  information establish that the incidence of drug and alcohol abuse is increasing and that the effect is devastating to lives, business, and the community at large. The Pueblo is concerned that due to the potential for</text>
          <text>abuse among some of our employees, the safety of our employees and the general public could be endangered. Our commitment to maintaining a safe and secure workplace requires a clear policy and supportive programs relating to the detection, treatment, and prevention of substance</text>
          <text>abuse by employees.</text>
          <text>Goal</text>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>It is the goal of the Pueblo to comply with federal regulations and guidelines established to reduce the use and abuse of controlled substances and drugs in the workplace.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text>To provide a safe workplace by eliminating the hazards to health and job safety created by alcohol and other drug abuse.</text>
          </para>
          <text>Scope</text>
          <text>This policy applies to all applicants seeking employment and employees of the Pueblo</text>
          <text>while on the job and to situations when an employee's off-the-job or off-premises conduct impairs work performance, or harms the reputation of the Pueblo. It is also intended to apply to employees of firms doing business with the Pueblo while on our premises or on tribal lands.</text>
          <text>Although the Pueblo has no intention of intruding into the private lives of its employees, we</text>
          <text>recognize that involvement with alcohol or other drugs off the job eventually takes its toll on job performance. Our concern is to assure those employees report to work in condition to perform  their duties safely and efficiently in the interest of their fellow workers and constituents as well</text>
          <text>as themselves.</text>
          <text>Pueblo Policy Statements on Substance Abuse</text>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>The Pueblo will not tolerate or condone substance abuse.   It is the policy of the Pueblo to maintain a workplace free from alcohol and other drug abuse and its effects.  The Pueblo therefore will enforce a comprehensive substance  abuse program committing to the safety and well being of its entire employee.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text>It is the policy of the Pueblo that employees who engage in the sale, use, possession, or transfer of illegal drugs or controlled substances, or buy or sell such substances, or use alcohol during work hours, or abuse prescribed drugs, will be subject to disciplinary action up to and including termination. (However, nothing in this policy precludes the appropriate use of legally prescribed medications).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>3.</num>
            <text>It is the policy of the Pueblo to commit the resources necessary to achieve and  maintain a drug-and alcohol-free environment. It may conduct alcohol and other drug screening tests both prospective to and during employment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>4.</num>
            <text>The Pueblo expects the full support of this policy by all employees and all persons doing business with the Pueblo. It will cooperate with Tribal and outside law enforcement agencies.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>5.</num>
            <text>As a condition of employment, employees must abide by the terms of this policy and must notify the Pueblo in writing of any indictment or conviction of a violation of a criminal drug statute occurring in the workplace no later than five calendar days after such conviction.</text>
          </para>
          <text>Policy Prohibitions</text>
          <text>The Pueblo's policy prohibits the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>Use, possession, manufacture, distribution, dispensation, or sale of illegal drugs</text>
          </para>
          <text>on Pueblo premises during working hours or non-working hours.</text>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text>Controlled substance abuse on Pueblo premises during working hours or</text>
          </para>
          <text>nonworking hours.</text>
          <para>
            <num>3.</num>
            <text>Storing any illegal drug or alcohol in a locker, desk, or other repository on Pueblo premises.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>4.</num>
            <text>Being under the influence of an illegal drug or engaging in controlled substance abuse on Pueblo premises, or while engaged in Pueblo business, or in Pueblo-supplied vehicles, during working hours or non-working hours.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>5.</num>
            <text>Testing positive for illegal drugs or controlled substances without a legal basis for use.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>6.</num>
            <text>Switching or adulterating any urine sample submitted for testing, or submitting a false sample for testing.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>7.</num>
            <text>Use, possession, sale, or distribution of alcohol, or being under the influence of alcohol on Pueblo premises, or in-Pueblo-supplied vehicles, whether during working hours or non-working hours.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>8.</num>
            <text>Refusing consent to testing or refusing to submit a urine sample for testing when required by the Pueblo.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>9.</num>
            <text>Failing, when requested by the Pueblo, to enroll in any alcohol or other drug treatment or counseling program and failing to adhere to the requirements of the program.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>10.</num>
            <text>Being indicted or convicted under any criminal drug statute for a violation occurring in the workplace or outside the workplace.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>11.</num>
            <text>Failing to notify the Pueblo of any indictment or conviction under any criminal drug statute within 5 days of the event.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>12.</num>
            <text>Failing to comply with rules and regulations promulgated under any testing programs maintained by the Pueblo pursuant to such rules and regulations.</text>
          </para>
          <text>Employee Responsibility</text>
          <text>The Pueblo believes that each employee has a responsibility to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>Report to work at all times free of alcohol or other drugs and their effects.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text>Participate in and support Pueblo-sponsored drug and alcohol education programs.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>3.</num>
            <text>Seek and accept assistance for alcohol and other drug abuse related problems before job performance is affected.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>4.</num>
            <text>Support the Pueblo efforts to eliminate alcohol and other drug abuse among employees where it exists.</text>
          </para>
          <text>Implementation</text>
          <text>Each Program within the Pueblo will be responsible for implementing these policies and procedures. If an individual program requires a more specific plan tailored to meet its needs, it must be consistent and support this policy. Each of these specific plans is subject to review for consistency and compliance with the Pueblo's policy on substance abuse and must first be approved by the Pueblo.</text>
          <text>
            <u>EMPLOYEE EDUCATION AND AWARENESS PROGRAM</u>
            <strong>(step 2)</strong>
          </text>
          <text>Self-Referral</text>
          <text>Employees with personal drug or controlled substance abuse problems should request assistance through their individual Programs, the Human Resources Department or the Pueblo's employee assistance program. Assistance will be provided on a confidential basis, and each employee will be referred to the appropriate treatment and counseling services. Employees who voluntarily request assistance in dealing with drug or controlled substance abuse problems may do so without jeopardizing their continued employment with the Pueblo subject to the Special Consideration  below.</text>
          <text>Pueblo Referral</text>
          <text>Employees who test positive for illegal drug  use or controlled substance abuse and who are referred, at the Pueblo's request, for counseling or treatment will be limited to one opportunity for counseling or treatment to cease the use of illegal drugs and alcohol. A second positive test following treatment for the use of illegal drugs will result in immediate termination.   Employees</text>
          <text>terminated for this reason will be ineligible for rehire.</text>
          <text>Special Consideration</text>
          <text>All Pueblo-referred, employee counseling and/or treatment, will require that the employee immediately cease any illegal drug and/or controlled substance abuse and the employee be subject to periodic unannounced testing for a 12 month period following enrollment in the program.</text>
          <text>Undergoing treatment or counseling for the first time will normally not jeopardize an employee's</text>
          <text>employment. However, the Pueblo is required in certain situations to report an employee's involvement with drug use or controlled substance to Government agencies (DOT) concerned with national security, health and safety-sensitive. In these situations, the Pueblo will be required to remove the employee from a position involving national security, health, safety-sensitive, or confidential matters. If other work cannot be found, the employee may be subject to termination.</text>
          <text>Alcohol Use or Possession on Pueblo Premises</text>
          <text>The use, possession, sale, or distribution of alcohol on Pueblo premises, or in Pueblo-supplied vehicles, whether during working hours or nonworking hours,is prohibited and constitutes a violation of policy.   Such action will be handled pursuant to the Pueblo's policy on work</text>
          <text>performance and conduct.</text>
          <text>Program Testing</text>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>The Pueblo will establish a testing program for alcohol, illegal drugs and controlled substances for all employees and will; in its sole discretion, determine and say at any time change the requirements, extent, and frequency of employee testing (with the exception of DOT requirements) upon approval from the San IIdefonso Tribal Council.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text>The Pueblo will test all applicants, whether new employees or rehires. The Pueblo requires that every newly hired and rehired employee be free of alcohol, illegal drug use and controlled substance abuse. Each offer of employment shall be conditioned upon the successful completion of a test for illegal drugs and controlled substances as prescribed by the Pueblo. The applicant's signature on the employment application is an agreement by that applicant to submit to pre-employment drug testing. Any applicant who tests positive in the pre-employment drug test shall be rejected and shall be ineligible for hire for 12months unless the applicant adequately establishes a legal basis for the use of the drug or controlled substance with respect to which the</text>
          </para>
          <text>applicant tested positive.</text>
          <para>
            <num>3.</num>
            <text>Whenever the Pueblo, during the course of an investigation by its designated representative suspects or has reasonable suspicion that an employee has used illegal drugs or engaged in controlled substance abuse, whether during working hours or nonworking hours, on or off Pueblo premises, the Pueblo may require the employee to submit to a urine or other acceptable sample for testing, as prescribed by the Pueblo.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>4.</num>
            <text>The Pueblo will afford applicants and employees subject to testing the opportunity, prior to testing, to list all prescription and nonprescription drugs and controlled substances they have used and to explain the circumstances surrounding the use of such drugs and controlled substances.   Failure of any employee to establish adequately a legal basis for the use of any drug or controlled substance with respect to which the employee tests positive shall constitute a violation of policy.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>5.</num>
            <text>Applicants and employees subject to testing must, prior to testing, sign an approved form agreeing to the testing, authorizing the release of test results to the Pueblo's designated representative, and authorizing the disclosure of the results by the designated representative to the Human Resources Department, the employee's supervisor, higher management, and other persons who have a bona-fide need to know. The designated representative will obtain the results</text>
          </para>
          <text>of the analyses and communicate or disclose such results to the Human Resources Department, the employee's supervisor, higher management and any other person in accordance with the Pueblo's policies and procedures.</text>
          <para>
            <num>6.</num>
            <text>The Pueblo will establish and maintain any and all additional testing programs and requirements that may be necessary or appropriate to comply with applicable rules and regulations of all Government agencies including the Federal Highway Administration (FHWA)</text>
          </para>
          <text>requirements mandated by the U.S. Department of Transportation.</text>
          <text>Consequences for Violation of the Drug-Free Policy</text>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>Violation of this policy may result in severe disciplinary action, including termination, at the Pueblo's sole discretion.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text>In addition to any disciplinary action, the Pueblo may at its sole discretion, refer the employee to a treatment or counseling program (EAP) for illegal drug use or controlled substance abuse. Employees referred to such a program by the Pueblo must immediately cease any illegal drug use or controlled substance abuse, must comply with all other conditions of the treatment or counseling program and disciplinary action. After successful completion of all requirements of this section, employees will again be subject to the testing program applicable to all employees. Appropriate Pueblo representatives shall determine whether an employee referred for illegal drug use or controlled substance abuse treatment or counseling should be reassigned to another position. Individuals in safety-sensitive positions as defined by the Department of Transportation must be removed from these positions and reassigned to non-sensitive positions if a position is available, if not the employee may be terminated (see drug testing, step' 5).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>3.</num>
            <text>The Pueblo will promptly terminate any employee who tests positive for illegal drugs or controlled substances, unless the employee establishes a legal basis for their use, if:</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>a.</num>
            <text>Undergoing or after completion of treatment or counseling when such treatment or counseling is required by the Pueblo;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>b.</num>
            <text>The employee has tested positive for illegal drugs or controlled substances on a previous occasion;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>c.</num>
            <text>The employee has been referred at Pueblo request for treatment or counseling on a previous occasion.</text>
          </para>
          <text>
            <u>SUPERVISORY TRAINING</u>
            <strong>(step 3)</strong>
          </text>
          <text>Purpose</text>
          <text>Supervisors are the key to a successful substance abuse program and therefore should be</text>
          <text>trained on all aspects of substance abuse and its effects in the work place. They have a legitimate</text>
          <text>right to initiate corrective actions when a worker's performance begins to decline. If it appears that personal problems including substance abuse may be impacting on performance, the use of constructive confrontation is one of the most effective ways known to get an employee to seek help.</text>
          <text>Confronting a worker about a performance problem can be constructive when a caring but</text>
          <text>firm attitude on the part of the supervisor is coupled with a referral to an appropriate source from</text>
          <text>which the employee can receive help for any personal problem. However, the supervisor's responsibility for monitoring job performance does not extend to diagnosing and resolving the personal problem. As the people in direct contact with workers, supervisors can detect performance problems that may indicate substance abuse. But their responsibilities should be limited, and that should be clearly explained to them.</text>
          <text><u>EMPLOYEE ASSISTANCE PROGRAM</u> (EAP) <strong>(step 4)</strong></text>
          <text>Employees who desire help with an alcohol or related problem may request assistance  through</text>
          <text>the Pueblo's Human Resources Department or Employee Assistance Program (EAP). Assistance</text>
          <text>will be provided on a confidential basis, and each employee will be referred to the appropriate treatment and counseling services. Employees who voluntarily request assistance may do so without jeopardizing their continued employment with the Pueblo. Employees may utilize the benefits programs that the Pueblo recently implemented or be afforded the use of any recognized agency to identify the source of  the problem and find practical solutions as quickly as possible.</text>
          <text>EAP services are available to the employee without charge, however, the cost of referrals to</text>
          <text>treatment or rehabilitation  is the responsibility of the employee if the cost is not completely</text>
          <text>covered by insurance. In support of our drug-free workplace, our insurance plans include some</text>
          <text>coverage for the treatment of addiction. An employee who tests positive on an alcohol and/or drug test may be referred to the EAP for assessment and rehabilitation recommendations. The</text>
          <text>employee's decision to participate in the recommended treatment, successful completion of the</text>
          <text>program and additional treatment recommendations will be communicated to the organization.</text>
          <text>
            <u>DRUG and ALCOHOL TESTING PROGRAM</u>
            <strong>(step 5)</strong>
          </text>
          <text>Applicability</text>
          <text>The Pueblo has established the following procedures for drug and alcohol testing of all its employees, potential employees, contracted or otherwise.</text>
          <text>Specific Testing Requirements</text>
          <text>To ensure the Pueblos commitment to maintaining a drug-free work force and eliminate the use and abuse of drugs and alcohol in the work place, urine specimens will be collected and tested for the following specified drugs utilizing the DHHS cutoff levels (see definitions) to determine</text>
          <text>if a sample is positive.  Substance Abuse Forensic Evaluation (SAFE) Non-DHHS 10+ drug/alcohol panel:</text>
          <text>Amphetamines,</text>
          <text>Cannabinoids,</text>
          <text>Cocaine,</text>
          <text>Phencyciidine(PCP),</text>
          <text>Barbiturates,</text>
          <text>Methadone,</text>
          <text>Opiates,</text>
          <text>Propoxyphene,</text>
          <text>Senzodiazepines,</text>
          <text>Methaqualone, and</text>
          <text>Alcohol (urine)</text>
          <text>Department of Health and Human Services DHHS/SAFE drug panel 5 (DOT):</text>
          <text>Amphetamines,</text>
          <text>Cannabinoids,</text>
          <text>Cocaine,</text>
          <text>Opiates, and</text>
          <text>Phencyclidine (PCP) E</text>
          <text>Evidential Breath Testing (EST) is also required by DOT--(all DOT safety-sensitive positions) Functions and Period of the Work Day Covered.  Employees will only be tested for alcohol while they are at the work site. He or she is not subject to alcohol testing until an employee reports for work.</text>
          <text>Alcohol Concentration</text>
          <text>Pueblo employees may not report for duty or remain on duty in a position requiring the performance of safety-sensitive functions while having an alcohol concentration of 0.04</text>
          <text>Types of Testing</text>
          <text>The Pueblo will conduct illegal drug and controlled substance testing for the following  instances:</text>
          <text>Pre-Placement /Pre-Employment (illegal drug and controlled substance only)</text>
          <text>Random</text>
          <text>Reasonable Cause</text>
          <text>Post Accident</text>
          <text>Return to Duty</text>
          <text>Follow up</text>
          <text>Pre-Placement/Pre Employment</text>
          <text>An applicant shall consent in writing (employment application) to illegal drug and controlled substance testing and successfully pass the test as a pre-qualification of employment.</text>
          <text>Implementation Procedures</text>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>All applicants will be notified in writing (employment application) that passing a</text>
            <text>drug and alcohol test shall be a condition for employment with the Pueblo.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text>Upon selection notification, the Human Resources Department will contact the Behavioral Health Program (collection site) to schedule an appointment and send the candidate(s) to the collection site.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>3.</num>
            <text>The Pueblo will hire a candidate only when confirmation of a negative test result has been received by the Employee Assistance Coordinator (EAC) from the Medical Review Officer (MRO).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>4.</num>
            <text>All persons will be tested under this category before being assigned to a safety-sensitive position from a non-safety sensitive position.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>5.</num>
            <text>Records of all tests will be maintained at the Behavioral Health Program and remain confidential with access strictly on a "need to know" basis.</text>
            <text>Random Testing</text>
            <para>
              <num>1.</num>
              <text>A percentage equal to 25 percent of employees (50 percent for safety-sensitive positions) will be tested annually.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>2.</num>
              <text>Random drawings will be done by the MRO on a quarterly basis.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <text>Post Accident Testing</text>
          <text>All employees employed by the Pueblo involved in or contributing to an accident, or who cannot be completely discounted as being contributing factors to an accident, shall be tested as soon as practicable after an accident. Employees in safety-sensitive positions must be tested for controlled substances no later than 32 hours after the accident and no later than 8 hours after the accident for alcohol testing as mandated by DOT. DOT places the burden .of compliance with post-accident alcohol and drug testing regulations on the individual in safety-sensitive positions</text>
          <text>and requires both a breath alcohol test and urine specimen.</text>
          <text>Individuals will be notified by their Program or the Human Resources Department to report to the EAC for testing. In the event that the individual is seriously injured and unable to provide a</text>
          <text>specimen at the time of the accident, he/she shall provide the necessary authorization for obtaining hospital reports and other documents that would indicate whether there were any controlled substances in his/her system.</text>
          <text>For the purposes of post accident testing, an "accident" is defined as an incident that results in property damage, death of a human being, or bodily injury to a person who, as a result of their injury, immediately receives medical treatment away from the scene of the accident. DOT regulations specify that except for a fatality accident, verification of responsibility of those individuals in safety-sensitive positions (i.e. truck drivers, bus drivers) in the above mentioned</text>
          <text>accident scenario must be established by a citation to the driver.</text>
          <text>Post Accident Procedures</text>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>An employee of the Pueblo must be tested  if involved in an accident wherein the covered employee's performance either contributed to or cannot be completely discounted as a contributing factor to the accident and the accident meets the definition criteria as described above.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text>The Pueblo/ supervisor will determine that post-accident testing will not be required by the employee if the Pueblo and/or Investigating Officer has determined that the employee's involvement was not a contributing factor in the accident. (Drivers may be hours away from an</text>
          </para>
          <text>immediate supervisor. In such cases, the Pueblo/supervisor should call the enforcement agency</text>
          <text>involved and speak with the investigating officer or shift commander).</text>
          <para>
            <num>3.</num>
            <text>The Pueblo/supervisor is responsible to insure the employee reports to the Behavioral Health Program (collection site) in San Juan Pueblo after an appointment has been made with the EAC or a designated representative but no later than 32 hours after the accident for controlled substance testing and 8 hours after for alcohol testing when safety-sensitive positions are involved.</text>
          </para>
          <text>Return to Duty</text>
          <text>When an employee is returned to duty after a rehabilitation process, the Pueblo will ensure the</text>
          <text>employee receives both an alcohol and controlled substance test before being reinstated to is/her</text>
          <text>previous job. A positive test will result in termination. Safety-sensitive positions must undergo</text>
          <text>a return-to-duty alcohol test with a result of less than a 0.02 BAC or receive a confirmed negative result from a controlled substance urinalysis test.</text>
          <text>Follow-Up testing</text>
          <text>When an employee is returned to duty after a rehabilitation process, the Pueblo will ensure the employee receives random alcohol and controlled substance tests over an  8-month  period. The</text>
          <text>number and frequency of such follow-up testing shall be as directed by the MRO through the EAC. (Employee's in safety-sensitive positions will conduct at least six tests in the first 12 months following the employee's return to duty.</text>
          <text>Follow-up testing shall not exceed 60 months from the date of the employee's return to duty). The EAC after discussion with the MRO may terminate the requirement for follow-up testing at</text>
          <text>any time after the first six tests have been administered, provided the EAC determines such testing is no longer necessary.</text>
          <text>DHHS/NIDA and SAFE Certified Laboratories</text>
          <text>All testing is performed by a DHHS/NIDA approved laboratory. The Pueblo has contracted with</text>
          <text>the following Laboratory to perform all its testing:</text>
          <text>S.E.D. Medical Laboratories</text>
          <text>5601 Office Blvd N.E.</text>
          <text>Albuquerque, New Mexico 87109</text>
          <text>800-999-LABS (5227)</text>
          <text>S.E.D. Laboratories in Albuquerque holds dual forensic drug testing certifications:</text>
          <text>Department of Health and Human Services (formerly NIDA) required for federally regulated testing, and Forensic Urine Drug Testing by the College of American Pathologists (CAP-FUDT).</text>
          <text>Routine Laboratory inspections and periodic testing challenges is required for ongoing certification and to assure and maintain quality control. Copies of these certifications are available to the Pueblo upon request. The Pueblo has contracted the following Medical Review</text>
          <text>Officer (MRO) through S.ED. Medical Labs:</text>
          <text>Dr. Renee Gonzalez</text>
          <text>101 Hospital Loop. NE Suite 215</text>
          <text>Albuquerque, New Mexico 87109</text>
          <text>505-291-5444</text>
          <text>Collections</text>
          <text>Collections will be done at the Behavioral Health Program located in San Juan Pueblo (#505/852-2788). The Employee Assistance Coordinator (EAC) and or designated representative</text>
          <text>will conduct specimen collections and ensure chain of custody procedures in accordance with procedures established by the testing laboratory. The standard legal protocol checklist for SAFE drug screen collections will be utilized for both standard and split-sample collections. S.E.D. Labs provides a bonded courier service for collections pickup Monday through Friday to transfer the specimen from the collection point to and from the laboratory. They also provide all testing supplies (800999-LABS).</text>
          <text>Negative drug test results are available within 24 hours of the time the specimen arrives</text>
          <text>at the Laboratory in Albuquerque. Positive screening tests require confirmatory testing which require an additional 24-48 hours. These results are sent to the MRO. The MRO will contact the</text>
          <text>employee(s) who have positive drug testing results to determine if the result is due to prescription drugs. The MRO will then either call or FAX results to the Behavioral Health Program followed by written results sent by mail. Positive results will be reviewed by the EAC</text>
          <text>and forwarded to the Human Resources Director for consultation with the employees Program Director. A referral can then be made to the Pueblo's EAP (based on previous substance abuse history) or potential termination of employment.</text>
          <text>Employees in safety-sensitive positions as defined by DOT will be required to do a split-pecimen</text>
          <text>(see definitions &amp; DOT procedures).</text>
          <text>
            <strong>703. Harassment Policy</strong>
          </text>
          <text>The Pueblo will not permit or tolerate harassment of employees by other employees. This includes harassment because of race, sex, religious, creed, color, national origin, ancestry, disability or medical condition, age, or any other basis protected by federal law. Such conduct by an employee could result in corrective action up to, and including termination of employment.</text>
          <text>No harassment will be tolerated and sexual, racial, religious, ethnic, disability, sexual orientation and other form of legally impermissible harassment in any manner or form is expressly prohibited.  If an employee becomes aware of inappropriate harassment in the workplace whether directed at himself/herself or any other person, they have an obligation to bring it to the attention of their director, the Tribal Administrator, Human Resources Coordinator or any other Pueblo official with whom they are comfortable discussing the</text>
          <text>issue. The situation will then be investigated appropriately and privacy will be maintained</text>
          <text>to the extent feasible under the circumstances. Retaliation against any individual who complains about an incident of harassment or cooperates in any investigation of alleged harassment is strictly prohibited.</text>
          <text>
            <strong>704. Progressive Discipline</strong>
          </text>
          <text>The purpose of this policy is to state the Pueblo of San Ildefonso's position on administering equitable and consistent discipline for unsatisfactory conduct in the workplace.</text>
          <text>The Pueblo's own best interest lies in ensuring fair treatment of all employees and in making certain that disciplinary actions are prompt, uniform and impartial. The major purpose of any disciplinary action is to correct the problem, prevent recurrence, and prepare the employee for satisfactory service in the future.</text>
          <text>Although employment with the Pueblo is based on mutual consent and both the Employee and the Pueblo have the right to terminate employment at will, with or without cause or advance notice, the Pueblo shall use progressive discipline for those activities or conduct that do not require immediate termination.</text>
          <text>Progressive disciplinary action should include these four steps:</text>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text><u>Verbal Interview</u> - When an employee violates any rules or regulations mentioned in this Policy or for some other reason requires Management attention, the first step may be in the form of a verbal interview, initiated by the employee's Director. The Director will develop a memorandum documenting the verbal interview and route as follows: the original notice to the employee, then a copy to Tribal Administrator, and then another copy to the employee's personnel file. The intention of the verbal interview is to discuss and suggest corrective actions for the employee's job performance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text><u>Written Warning Notice</u> - When an employee violates any rules or regulations mentioned in this Policy and/or has been given a verbal notice or for some other reason warrants immediate Management attention, The employee's Director will develop a notice that describe the nature of the violation and route as follows: the original notice to the employee, then a copy to Tribal Administrator, and then another copy to the employee's personnel file. The written notice will outline corrective actions to be made within the specific time frame. Successful completion of these corrective actions will be documented and added to the employee's personnel file.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>3.</num>
            <text><u>Suspension Without Pay</u> - A Director may suspend an employee without pay. A hearing shall be scheduled, with the Governor or his designee, for the third working day after the employee's formal notification of suspension. The Director, the Human Resources Coordinator, the employee, the Tribal Administrator, and the Governor should be present for the hearing. The employee shall not be suspended for more than (3) working days. No Department of the Tribe shall hire the suspended employee during the suspension period. The hearing shall determine whether or not the employee will be retained or terminated. The employee shall receive a written notice of the suspension and records will be routed in the following manner: one copy for the employee's Director, one copy for the Tribal Administrator and one copy for the employee's personnel file.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>4.</num>
            <text>
              <u>Termination of Employment</u>
            </text>
            <text><u>Involuntary</u> - A Director may request termination for any of the following actions or omissions including but not limited to:</text>
            <text>
              <ul>
                <li>Theft or attempted theft, including the unauthorized removal of Pueblo property;</li>
                <li>Omission, falsification, misuse, or manipulation of information on employment applications, time sheets, or other Pueblo records;</li>
                <li>Malicious abuse of Pueblo equipment or property;</li>
                <li>Absence for three (3) consecutive working days without proper notification;</li>
                <li>Possession or use of alcoholic beverages or illegal drugs during working hours, or appearing for work duty under the influence of alcohol or illegal drugs;</li>
                <li>Harassment of any type as a threat or action against any person during working hours;</li>
                <li>Unauthorized possession of firearms, weapons, or explosives;</li>
                <li>Conviction of any crime for which the employee is subject to a jail term or which brings unfavorable publicity to the Pueblo;</li>
                <li>Gross professional negligence;</li>
                <li>Unauthorized public statements or release of confidential information;</li>
                <li>Fighting or attempting to injure others during working hours;</li>
                <li>Repeated violations of any written part of the Personnel Policy;</li>
                <li>Initiating malicious gossip which injures another employee's professional reputation; and/or</li>
                <li>Where the continuing employment of the employee would cause the Pueblo or specific program continuing harm.</li>
              </ul>
            </text>
            <text>The Director will notify the employee in writing of the reasons for his or her termination immediately after obtaining the Tribal Administrator's concurrence, and termination, which will take effect immediately. The Tribal Administrator will use this same procedure for directors.</text>
            <text>Employees terminated will be paid for any salary due, plus unused annual leave (up to 240 hours until 2009) upon submission of a signed or approved clearance form by their immediate supervisor and the Human Resources Director (see Sections 504 and 505).</text>
            <text>An employee may be involuntarily terminated if physical or mental impairment prevent the employee's performance of required duties. Termination, due to mental or physical disability must be supported by medical evidence acceptable to the immediate supervisor.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>705. Grievances and Appeals</strong>
            </text>
            <text>It is the policy of the Pueblo to ensure that all employees have access to a process for workplace grievances to be heard in a safe and fair manner.  A grievance, as established in this policy shall be defined as an employee's unresolved dissatisfaction with any aspect of the working conditions (except termination) or working relationships which is brought to the attention of a supervisor or Human Resources Department (HR).  An employee filing a grievance shall be free from restraint, coercion, discrimination, or reprisal.  The Pueblo recognizes the importance of open communication in resolving disputes.  All complaints shall receive full and fair consideration.  The grievance process shall be kept confidential and all communications, documents, and records relating to a grievance shall be kept in a separate file and maintained by the Human Resources Department.</text>
            <text>A probationary employee shall not be permitted to file a grievance.  A termination of an employee shall not be subject to the grievance process.  An employee filing a grievance shall be responsible to comply with the requirements of this policy including any time deadlines.</text>
            <text>
              <strong>
                <u>Grievance Procedure</u>
              </strong>
            </text>
            <para>
              <num>1.</num>
              <text>The following grievance procedures shall apply to all grievances within the executive administration under the authority of the Governor:</text>
              <text><strong><u>Step 1 (Informal):</u></strong> An aggrieved employee is encouraged to attempt to resolve the dispute or problem in an informal, non-confrontational manner by making an appointment with their immediate Supervisor to discuss the matter. The Supervisor shall promptly inform his/her supervisor and the HR in writing that an aggrieved employee has requested a meeting to discuss an issue.  The aggrieved employee and Supervisor shall promptly meet to discuss and attempt to resolve the matter.  If the matter cannot be resolved informally, or if the employee does not believe that a discussion with their Supervisor is appropriate, then an aggrieved employee shall be required to go through the following steps to file a formal grievance or to appeal a grievance decision:</text>
              <text><strong><u>Step 2 (Formal):</u></strong> An aggrieved employee shall file a written grievance with the next supervisor in the chain of command that is not a party to the grievance within thirty (14) calendar days of the occurrence of the event or incident with a copy to the HR.    That supervisor shall schedule a meeting with the employee within five (5) calendar days following the submission of the grievance with a copy to HR. That supervisor shall make a decision regarding the grievance, in writing, within three (3) calendar days after the meeting and shall notify the aggrieved employee of the decision in person and by mail.  That supervisor shall provide a copy of the decision to the Human Resources Department.  If that supervisor fails to act in a timely manner, then the employee may proceed to Step 3.</text>
              <text><strong><u>Step 3 (Appeal to Ad Hoc Committee):</u></strong> If the employee is not satisfied with the decision of the supervisor who made the decision in Step 2 the employee may file an appeal of the decision with the HR. Filing must take place within five (5) calendar days after supervisor's decision or, in case of no action, within five (5) calendar days after the final day of the supervisor's decision-making time limit.</text>
              <text>The HR Director shall schedule a meeting with the aggrieved employee and the Supervisor within five (5) calendar days of the appeal. The aggrieved employee may present witnesses and other evidence in a reasonable manner.</text>
              <text>The HR shall randomly select 1 supervisor from the pool of supervisors and 1 randomly selected non-supervisor and 1 randomly selected employee from the entire pool of employees, and these 3 shall serve on an Ad Hoc Committee who shall hear the appeal.</text>
              <text>The Ad Hoc committee shall make a decision regarding the grievance, in writing, within three (3) calendar days after the meeting and shall notify the aggrieved employee of the decision in person and by mail.  The Ad Hoc committee shall provide a copy of the decision to the Human Resources Department.  The decision of the Ad Hoc Committee shall be final.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>2.</num>
              <text>A grievance shall not exist until such time that an employee makes known to their supervisor or the HR that employment dissatisfaction exists.  A formal grievance shall be in writing and shall be specific and supported by factual evidence. The employee filing a grievance shall be required to be present at each proceeding of their case.  Failure to follow the steps above, will result in a dismissal of the grievance.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>3.</num>
              <text>Employees shall be required to appear as witnesses as part of the grievance process when requested by the aggrieved employee, or any other party to the grievance or the TA, Ad Hoc Standing Committee.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>4.</num>
              <text>The Governor shall have the authority to intervene and address an employee grievance against any employee of the executive branch of government under the authority of the Governor notwithstanding the requirements of this policy.  Depending on the nature of the grievance, the Governor shall have the sole discretion to address a grievance in a manner other than the process established in this policy and may reasonably modify the deadlines in this policy due to unforeseen or extraordinary circumstances.  The Governor may not involve himself in a grievance if any party to the grievance is an immediate family member or  closer relative.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </include>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R12-015"/>
          <annotation app="2020-12-30" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R20-028" eff="2020-12-30" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>19.4</num>
    <heading>Distributions</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>19.4.1</num>
      <heading>Distributions</heading>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes">This law was originally enacted pursuant to Council Resolution No. SI-R17-001, dated January 18, 2017.</annotation>
      </annotations>
      <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-001"/>
      <section>
        <num>19.4.1.010</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Council finds that it is in the best interest of the Pueblo to authorize distributions of available funds to all members of the Pueblo from time to time.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Council hereby enacts the attached law 	entitled the "TRIBAL MEMBER DISTRIBUTION AUTHORIZATION ACT."</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-001"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.4.1.020</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as, the "TRIBAL MEMBER DISTRIBUTION AUTHORIZATION" ("Act").</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-001"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.4.1.030</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of the Act is to authorize distributions of money to all members of the Pueblo on an equitable basis when funds for such purposes become available, subject to the appropriation of such funds by the Council.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-001"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.4.1.040</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From time to time, the Pueblo receives discretionary funds from various sources including proceeds from lawsuits, settlements, leases, rights-of-way, investment proceeds, and other sources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In the past, the Pueblo has authorized and distributed discretionary funds it has received to all members of the Pueblo;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Council has determined that it is in the best interest of the Pueblo to authorize the distribution of discretionary funds to all members of the Pueblo when such funds become available and no other overriding need exists for the use of such funds.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>In 2017, the Council enacted the original Tribal Member Distribution Act to provide for an annual distribution of funds to all Members of the Tribe from discretionary funds received from various sources; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>since 2017, the Pueblo has authorized and distributed discretionary funds directly to all members of the Pueblo typically at the beginning of each year; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>the Council has determined that it is the best interest of the Pueblo to authorize and direct an immediate distribution of discretionary funds to all members of the Pueblo to address the immediate economic hardships caused by the COVID-19 pandemic.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-001"/>
          <annotation app="2020-08-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R20-016" eff="2020-08-14" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.4.1.050</num>
        <heading>Distribution Process Requirements</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Governor is hereby authorized to provide a distribution of funds in an equal amount to all members of the Pueblo when funds for such purposes are specifically appropriated by the Council in an approved Annual Budget or Budget Modification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Governor shall not be authorized to distribute any funds to members of the Pueblo that have not been specifically appropriated by the Council for such purposes.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Governor shall establish and implement fair and equitable procedures to notify members of the Pueblo of the availability of funds for distribution and to distribute such funds.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Governor is hereby authorized and directed to issue an immediate distribution of funds in an equal amount to all members of the Pueblo from the line item designated for such purposes in the current 2020-2021 Annual Budget.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-001"/>
          <annotation app="2020-08-14" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R20-016" eff="2020-08-14" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>19.5</num>
    <heading>Master Planning</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Part</prefix>
      <num>19.5.1</num>
      <heading>Act Adopting and Ratifying the 2014 Master Land Use Plan Scheme 3</heading>
      <section>
        <num>19.5.1.010</num>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>This enactment shall be known as the "ACT ADOPTING AND RATIFYING THE 2014 MASTER LAND USE PLAN SCHEME 3 ("Act")."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-07-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-020" eff="2017-07-08" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-07-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-020" eff="2017-07-08" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.5.1.020</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this Act is to adopt and ratify a selection of one of the "Schemes (schematics)" from the 3 Schemes (options) outlined in the 2014 Master Land Use Plan, a study which was contracted through the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority and prepared for the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-07-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-020" eff="2017-07-08" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-07-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-020" eff="2017-07-08" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.5.1.030</num>
        <heading>Findings</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Pueblo, through the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority, contracted a study by Indigenous Design Studio + Architecture, LLC, to examine land use within the Pueblo boundaries, and as a result, the 2014 Land Use Plan (report) was developed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The 2014 Land Use Plan has been provided to the Pueblo de San Ildefonso through both hard copy and electronic forms, provided to the Executive and Legislative Branches, as well as housed at the Northern Pueblos Housing Authority offices.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The 2014 Land Use Plan that was prepared for the Pueblo identifies 3 Schemes (or schematics) as options for use as a foundation to do further, detailed land use planning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Council understands that none of the 3 Schemes currently fit the dynamic of the stages of planning and development that has been and is occurring since the document was presented in 2014, however, in order to continue enhancing and preparing for planning, preparation and development, one selection is needed to move forward.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>In order for pueblo to proceed into the next phase of developing a Master Community Land Use Plan, the Council needs to select one "Scheme" from the 2014 Land Use Plan as a basis to work off of and to use as a framework for long-term planning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Council has determined the need to adopt and ratify a selection of one of the schematics from three (3) viable alternatives that were provided and discussed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Council has chosen to adopt and ratify the selection of 'Scheme 3' for use in development of the Master Community Plan.  A copy of Scheme 3 is attached as Exhibit A.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-07-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-020" eff="2017-07-08" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-07-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-020" eff="2017-07-08" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>19.5.1.040</num>
        <heading>Authorizations</heading>
        <text>The Council hereby approves and adopts this resolution in accordance with the requirements of the Agreement, according to published Council procedures, and authorizes and directs the Governor or his designee to take such actions as deemed necessary to carry out the intent of this resolution.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation app="2017-07-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-020" eff="2017-07-08" path="" type="History"/>
          <annotation app="2017-07-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-020" eff="2017-07-08" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <annotation app="2017-07-08" doc="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-020" eff="2017-07-08" path="" type="History"/>
  </container>
</container>
