<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-003">
  <num>SI-R17-003</num>
  <heading>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO COUNCIL RESOLUTION NO. SI-R17-003</heading>
  <heading type="law">Personnel Policy Manual Clarification Act</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2017-03-10</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res">Council Resolution No. SI-R17-003</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2017-03-03</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <preamble>At a duly called meeting of the Council of San Ildefonso Pueblo on the 
      3rd        day of       March       , 2017, the following Resolution was adopted:</preamble>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Pueblo') is a sovereign and self-governing Tribe, recognized as such by the United States of America; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council is authorized to make laws for the Pueblo de San Ildefonso pursuant to Section 5 of the Agreement; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>prior to the adoption of the Governing Agreement in December 2011, the Tribal Council approved a Personnel Policy Manual governing the employment rights and practices for employees of the Pueblo; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>in March 2012, after the adoption of the Governing Agreement, the Council reaffirmed its approval of the Personnel Policy Manual for the Pueblo by enacting Resolution No. SI-R12-015; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>in July 2016, the Governor unilaterally amended the Personnel Policy Manual by issuing a memo announcing that the Personnel Policy Manual "…has been amended…" by altering Section 411 to decrease the number of days employees may take administrative leave, and by altering the process for obtaining administrative leave; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on February 3, 2017, the Governor issued an "Executive Order" declaring the Personnel Policy Manual enacted by the Council "null and void" and attempting to unilaterally adopt a new "Personnel Policy Manual 2017 Edition;" and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on February 27, 2017, the Governor issues a memo rescinding the "Executive Order" leaving the original Personnel Policy Manual in place.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Council hereby enacts the attached law 			entitled, "PERSONNEL POLICY MANUAL CLARIFICATION ACT."</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on     March 3      , 2017, at a meeting with a vote of      8    	 in favor,	 1      opposed,	     0      abstaining and    1       absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
    <text>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE SPONSOR(S):    Lt. Governor Moquino/CR Irene Tse-Pe</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
          <th>YES</th>
          <th>NO</th>
          <th>ABSTAIN</th>
          <th>ABSENT</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Glenda Fred-Weahkee</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Terrence K. Garcia</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td>X</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Darryl Martinez</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>M. Wayne Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Perry Martinez</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Tim Martinez</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Chris Moquino</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Donald Pena</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Irene Tse-Pe</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION TO THE GOVERNOR:</text>
    <text>Resolution No. SI-R17-003  was presented to the Governor of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso on the     3rd         day of          March           	, 2017, pursuant to the Governing document of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Agreement"), GOVERNOR, Sec. 4(c), and will become effective after signature by the Governor or veto override by the Council.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
    <subheading>GOVERNOR'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>{    } 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>{    }	VETO - RETURNED TO COUNCIL WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this __________ day of _______________________, 2017.</text>
    <text>James R. Mountain, Governor</text>
    <text>Presented by the Governor to the Council on the _______ day of ________________, 2017.</text>
    <subheading>COUNCIL'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>Override of Governor's veto:</text>
    <text>{    } 	YES</text>
    <text>{    }	NO</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
          <th>YES</th>
          <th>NO</th>
          <th>ABSTAIN</th>
          <th>ABSENT</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Glenda Fred-Weahkee</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Terrence K. Garcia</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Darryl Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>M. Wayne Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Perry Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Tim Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Chris Moquino</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Donald Pena</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Irene Tse-Pe</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on _________________, 2017, at a meeting with a vote of ______ in favor, _____ opposed, _____ abstaining and _____ absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <attachment id="law">
    <text>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO</text>
    <heading>PERSONNEL MANUAL CLARIFICATION ACT</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.1</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text>This enactment shall be known as, "PERSONNEL POLICY MANUAL CLARIFICATION ACT" ("Act").</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.2</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of this Act is to reaffirm the Personnel Policy Manual as originally approved by the Council as the law of the Pueblo and to clarify that the Council, not the Governor, is vested with the authority, under the Governing Agreement, to enact and amend the laws of the Pueblo.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.3</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Prior to the adoption of the Governing Agreement in December 2011, the Tribal Council approved a Personnel Policy Manual governing the employment rights and practices for employees of the Pueblo; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>In March 2012, after the adoption of the Governing Agreement, the Council reaffirmed its approval of the Personnel Policy Manual for the Pueblo by enacting Resolution No. SI-R12-015; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>In July 2016, the Governor unilaterally amended the Personnel Policy Manual by issuing a memo announcing that the Personnel Policy Manual "…has been amended…" by altering Section 411 to decrease the number of days employees may take administrative leave, and by altering the process for obtaining administrative leave.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>On February 3, 2017, the Governor issued an "Executive Order" declaring the Personnel Policy Manual enacted by the Council "null and void" and attempting to unilaterally adopt a new "Personnel Policy Manual 2017 Edition."</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>On February 27, 2017, the Governor issues a memo rescinding the "Executive Order" leaving the original Personnel Policy Manual in place.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>It is in the best interest of the Pueblo and its employees to reaffirm and clarify that the Council, not the Governor, is vested with the power to enact and modify the laws of the Pueblo including the Personnel Policy Manual.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.4</num>
      <heading>Reaffirmation of the Personnel Policy Manual as Pueblo Law</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Pursuant to the Agreement, THE GOVERNMENT – Section 5, the Council is vested with the authority to enact laws for the Pueblo, and the Council has</text>
        <text>previously reaffirmed the enactment of the Personnel Policy Manual as the law of the Pueblo when it passed Resolution No. SI-R12-015.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Council again reaffirms its enactment of the Personnel Policy Manual as the law of the Pueblo, and clarifies that the Council, not the Governor, is vested with the authority to modify the Personnel Policy Manual.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Governor is prohibited from modifying or amending the Personnel Policy Manual by memo, Executive Order, or otherwise.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The unilateral changes to Section 411 of the Personnel Policy Manual allegedly made by the Governor pursuant to his memo dated July 7, 2016, and the new "Personnel Policy Manual 2017 Edition" allegedly approved by the Governor by Executive Order, are hereby repealed, the Governor's decision to rescind the "2017 Edition" of the Personnel Policy Manual is hereby acknowledged, and the original Personnel Policy Manual including the original Section 411 as approved and reaffirmed by the Council shall remain in full force and effect.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The Council invites the Governor to offer and propose suggested amendments to the Personnel Policy Manual at any time for consideration by the Council.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </attachment>
</document>
